<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title corresp="#CT021"><date when="1888-08-19">Sunday Morning, August 19, 1888</date></title><sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">newtFire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor><sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Rebecca Parker</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName>Gregory Bondar</persName></respStmt><!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:--><!--<respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="yyyy-mm-dd">yyyy-mm-dd</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt>--></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2016-03-18">2016-03-18</date>. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text.</p><p>Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original.</p><p>When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p><p><!-- Make note that not holding capitalization in the headlines when versioning with the Barkley text --></p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head><title><name ref="#CT">Chicago Times</name> <date when="1888-08-19">Sunday Morning, August 19, 1888</date></title></head><div type="headlines"><list><item><app><rdg wit="#CT021">A <hi rend="double">Times</hi> Reporter Gets Into a Paper-Box Manufacatory That Puzzles and Bewilders Him.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></item><item><app><rdg wit="#CT021">He Finds Little Children Toiling Away for a Miserable Pittance of $2 or $3 a Week.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></item><item><app><rdg wit="#CT021">The Employers Are Not Altogether to Blame for Having the Unfortunate Youngsters at Work.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></item><!--rjp: The following two headlines are the only ones that appear in the Barkley text. Which is ironic because the last part of the article that is being referred to by the final headline doesn't appear in the Barkley text at all.--><item>A Proposition of Marriage to a Pretty and Brainy Seamstress Is Taken Under Consideration.</item><item>Correcting an Erroneous Impression that <hi rend="double">Nell Nelson's</hi> Articles Are Not Founded on Fact.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p>Nothing short of a <placeName type="city">Philadelphia</placeName> lawyer, a <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> health officer, a proprietor or a <hi rend="double">devil-chaser</hi> that hits the spot once in a thousand times could, without a guide, explore the labyrinth that is known as <orgName ref="#HSC" type="exposedCompany"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">H. Schultz</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">H.S.</rdg></app> &amp; Co.'s paper-box manufactory</orgName>, <placeName ref="#HSC" type="address"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">34 to 38 East Randolph</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">on R&#8212;</rdg><!--rjp: em dash???--></app> street</placeName>. <seg>It occupies only the three upper floors of a four-story building, but the stairways are so dark and narrow that one must grope <phr><w type="poss">his</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr> from somewhere to a suppositious somewhere else, which resembles nowhere when he gets there, because the rooms are so overcrowded with material that one <choice><sic>employe</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employee</reg></choice> cannot in many instances see <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> nearest <w type="noun" ana="#workingGirl">neighbor</w></phr> two yards away.</seg></p><p>Of the 120 <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employees</reg></choice>, ten are mere girls, who get from $2 to $3 a week, while the others receive from $5 to $7.50. <seg>Each girl keeps <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> own <w type="noun">account-book</w></phr>, and at the request of the proprietor submitted it to inspection.</seg> It showed the exact amount the owner had been paid each week for many weeks. One advantage of working in this stuffy place is that there is work the year around.</p><p><seg><persName ref="#employer">Mr. <app><rdg wit="#CT021">Schultz</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">S.</rdg></app></persName> had the usual explanation to make as to the employment of young boys and girls, and no doubt made it truthfully. <!-- rjp: should we have a child employee archetype??? --><phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">Their</w> <w type="noun">parents</w></phr> needed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">assistance</w></phr> and would sign any sort of certificate as to age, and supplement it with personal solicitation asking employment as a charity.</seg><seg> In extreme cases he negotiated a compromise with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#employee">judgment</w></phr>, as most manufacturers do, and gave the child employment.</seg></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">What kind of work do you do?</said> a group of five boys was asked at the noon hour.</p><p><said who="#employee" ana="male">All but him binds packages; he glues.</said></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">How old are you?</said></p><p><said who="#employee" ana="male">We's pretty old and gettin' older all de time.</said></p><p>The closets are separate and fairly decent.</p><p>The ventilation is bad.</p><p><!-- rjp: in a way this reporter seems like a benefactor ... should we call him that archetype? --><said who="#reporter" ana="male">I am a man of few words and you have no time to lose, so I will proceed direct to business. Do you want to get married?</said></p><p><seg>The proposition was made by a <name ref="#CT">TIMES</name> reporter to an attractive young woman employed as a seamstress in a custom shop on the fourth floor of <phr><orgName ref="#SN" type="exposedCompany"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">S. Nelson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">S. N</rdg></app></orgName><w type="poss" ana="#SN">'s</w> <w type="noun">building</w></phr> <app><rdg wit="#CT021">at</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">on</rdg></app> <placeName type="address" ref="#SN">the southwest corner of <app><rdg wit="#CT021">Wesson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">W.</rdg></app> and <app><rdg wit="#CT021">Hobbie</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">H.</rdg></app> streets on the North side</placeName>.</seg></p><p>The reporter had seen the young woman but once before, and after that meeting the following paragraph was printed in <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> on August 13:</p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown"><!-- rjp: kinda confused on the representation of this in both Barkley and the original pdfs: I think it is a word for word quote from the article printed on the 13th but not entirely sure --><seg>An intelligent trio, evidently good friends, gathered in a corner, and between bites talked freely. One was a thorough American, lived on <placeName type="locRef">May street</placeName>, and walked back and forth from <!-- rjp: ok so here we know she is talking about her workplace do we ana this to employer or it is not exactly like that ... I guess I know the answer to this to be no, but when we write up our methods of choosing when its a subtype refTo or not we should consider these close calls... perhaps though by extending the seg or creating the s around the context tho we could eliminate this ambiguity --><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr>, the round distance being fully three miles.</seg> Another, whose yellow hair bespoke an ancestry from the region of the midnight sun, walked about the same distance. <seg>Many an avenue belle would give half <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">inheritance</w></phr>, for the form, face and figure, to say nothing of the brains of this every-day sewing girl, wearing out <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> young <w type="noun">life</w></phr><!-- rjp: her life being worn out by her employement by employer ... ugh ambiguity??? do we refTo? --> for $6 a week.</seg> But she made no complaints. Independence more than compensated her for the hardships of the weary day.</said></p><p>Usually <hi rend="double">popping the question</hi> is a trying ordeal to a man, even when none but the two parties most interested are present. What must it have been in this case when half a score of pairs of bright eyes were gazing in astonishment and as many ears were trained to catch every syllable? Usually, too, the woman addressed is very much embarrassed, or seems to be. This one was not. With a musical laugh followed by an interrogation point, she awaited further developments, <persName ref="#workingGirl">Emma</persName>, the American girl, rallying her good-naturedly the while.</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">You know you want to get married,</said> said <persName ref="#workingGirl">Emma</persName>. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Why don't you say <hi rend="single">yes?</hi></said></p><p>Not wishing to prolong the agony beyond the proper limit the reporter produced the following letter:</p><p><placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName>, <date when="1888-08-13">Aug. 13</date>. - TO THE EDITOR: <seg>One who reads <phr><w type="poss" ana="#CT">your</w> <w type="noun">articles</w></phr> with more than passing interest, and who deeply sympathizes with the cause of honest labor, has sufficient romance in <phr><w type="poss">his</w> <hi rend="double"><w type="noun">make-up</w></hi></phr> to perform <phr><w type="poss">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">part</w></phr> in assisting the young lady of brains referred to, and if honesty of purpose, good bringing up, etc., accompany the brains, the lady can find at the head of an honest, temperate, <phr><w type="poss">working-man's</w> <w type="noun">home</w></phr><!-- rjp: first thought is to put emploee in the ana, but this a more general employee and not one of an exposed company like how we typically use that archetype... here its seems kind of like a benefactor position but do we want to use that archetype like that? --> a peace and comfort not found in <hi rend="double">wearing out <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> young <w type="noun">life</w></phr></hi> in pursuit of a mere existence.</seg> This is in good faith, and any acknowledgment of it will call forth - confidentially, of course - the name and address of the writer.</p><p><seg>It was interesting to watch the play of the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">girl's</w> <w type="noun">features</w></phr> as she read the letter.</seg> At first curiosity was uppermost; then came an expression of sadness as the passages expressing sympathy for honest labor were reached, and finally a slight flush and a smile as she read the offering clause.</p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">Will you accept?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Don't you do it at once,</said> said <persName ref="#workingGirl">Emma</persName>, tantalizingly. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Keep him waiting for a while till he gets real anxious.</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Who is the writer?</said> asked the girl to whom the letter referred. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">He must live where girls are scarce.</said></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">The letter is dated and postmarked <hi rend="single"><placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName></hi>.</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Well, I should like to see the writer. It takes something more than temperance and honesty to make a man. I shall not embrace the present opportunity to answer.</said></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="male">Nor the man either?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Nor the man either,</said> she said with a merry laugh as she caught the gentler force of the play upon the words.</p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">Will you answer the letter?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I will take it under advisement, as politicians say.</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">If you don't accept turn the letter over to me,</said> chimed in <persName ref="#workingGirl">Emma</persName>. <seg>And then noticing the grounds in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">coffee</w></phr></seg> she added: <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Can you tell fortunes?</said></p><p>Everybody on <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> tells fortunes, and of course the visitor could. <said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">This man is a blonde, tall, somewhat portly, and a widower with three children,</said> he began.</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Can't you make it five? She just dotes on children. If she won't take him I'll be No. 2 and run for the chance. Can't you induce him to call here? We are tailoresses here, but when we appear upon the street we are&#8212; ---</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Well, what are we then?</said> asked the girl with the light hair.</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Why, then - then we are ourselves. What time is it?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Seventeen minutes to 1 o'clock.</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Then we have just two minutes to live,</said> and <seg>the trio began preparations for renewing <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">toil</w></phr> after the forty-five minutes allowed for lunch</seg>. <seg>The author of the letter might wait a long time before finding a brighter or better head for <phr><w type="poss">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">household</w></phr> than this girl whose ancestors worshipped <persName>Thor</persName> and <persName>Woden</persName>.</seg></p><p><hi rend="double">Nell Nelson,</hi> in a recent article in <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>, described the trousers manufactory of <orgName ref="#Oleson" type="exposedCompany"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">K. B. Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">K.B.O.</rdg></app></orgName>, on <placeName type="address" ref="#Oleson"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Sedgwick</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">S.</rdg></app> street near Division</placeName>, as a two-story and basement frame, the stories being used for girls and the basement for horses. This is true as to the girls, and only the qualifying expression <hi rend="double">in part</hi> is needed to make it fit the basement, the rear portion of it being used for stabling, with all that the word implies. <seg><persName ref="#nellNelson">Miss Nelson</persName>, it will be remembered, worked an afternoon at this place, making a pair of trousers for 5 cents, and after relating <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">her</w> <w type="noun">experience</w></phr><!-- rjp: again is there ambiguity here in that the experience is of a workingGirl --> quoted the words of a young woman who sat at the same table and who complained that the shop was cold.</seg></p><p><seg>Of course the girl had no idea that <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">language</w></phr> was to appear in print and spoke carelessly.</seg> <seg>But <persName ref="#employer"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Mr. Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Mr. O.</rdg></app></persName> was displeased and the girl was promptly discharged from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">employ</w></phr>.</seg> The <orgName ref="#KnightsOL">Knights of Labor</orgName> were <app><rdg wit="#CT021"></rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">promptly</rdg></app> notified and so was <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>. <seg>Yesterday a reporter was instructed to investigate the case and if the facts were as reported to assure the girl, whose name is <persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary Kane</persName>, that <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> would secure for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> another and better <w type="noun">position</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><seg><persName ref="#employer"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Mr. Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Mr. O.</rdg></app></persName> was found on the upper floor of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">shop</w></phr> and pretty mad yet, though he had had a week to cool off in.</seg> But he soon quieted down, led the way to the office in the basement, and sent for <persName ref="#foreperson"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Foreman Matson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Foreman M.</rdg></app></persName>. Then <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> article was read and liberally commented on, <persName ref="#foreperson"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Matson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">M.</rdg></app></persName> doing most of the talking because he could turn sharp corners in English a trifle more skillfully than <app><rdg wit="#CT021">Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">O.</rdg></app></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male"><persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary Kane</persName> has left, but she wasn't exactly discharged,</said> said <persName ref="#employer"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">O.</rdg></app></persName> <said who="#employer" ana="male">If the rooms are cold in winter why didn't she complain to me instead of <hi rend="single"><persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName>?</hi> I know they are cold at times, but not for half a day. I frequently feel chilly myself in the early morning. I know the house is not a model; It was built directly after the fire and needs many improvements. Why didn't <persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary Kane</persName> complain to me?</said></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">She preferred no charges against you. In a casual way she stated to a table-mate that the shop was cold in winter as you now acknowledge. The situation is this: If you have discharged <persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary Kane</persName> because of a chance word, <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> will see to it that she immediately secures a situation in some other shop.</said></p><p><seg>After a few moments <persName ref="#employer"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Mr. Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Mr. O.</rdg></app></persName> said the girl was one of the best in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">employ</w></phr>, that nothing could be said against <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr> or <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">character</w></phr>, and he would be willing to take her back.</seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">You may tell <persName ref="#workingGirl"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Mary Kane</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Mary K.</rdg></app></persName> she may come back to work if she wishes to. I don't want to do anybody any injustice. <seg>All I had against her in all the years she worked for me was that remark about <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">my</w> <w type="noun">shop</w></phr> being cold.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#reporter" ana="unknown">But I may not see her, as she is away from home.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male"><seg>Well, just go over and tell <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">mother</w></phr> that it's all right and <persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary</persName> can go to work when she likes.</seg></said></p><p><seg>It was the work of an hour, but no bull-dozing or pleading was used. The case was squarely discussed on <phr><w type="poss">its</w> <w type="noun">merits</w></phr><!-- rjp: uh again what gets the ana -->, and if <persName ref="#workingGirl"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Mary Kane</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">Mary K.</rdg></app></persName>, whom all the neighbors, including <app><rdg wit="#CT021">Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">O.</rdg></app> himself, say is a steady, industrious, and thoroughly deserving girl, walks into the shop today she can have <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> old <w type="noun">seat</w></phr><!-- rjp: ambiguity?? --> and at the same time the consciousness that she has not compromised herself or been compromised in the least.</seg> Both <persName ref="#employer"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Oleson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">O.</rdg></app></persName> and <persName ref="#foreperson"><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Matson</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23">M.</rdg></app></persName> will be glad to welcome her back, which is much to <!-- should we ana the actual company or the employer ... hmmmm--><phr><w type="poss" ana="#Oleson">their</w> <w type="noun">credit</w></phr>.</p><!-- THIS IS THE END OF THE BARKLEY TEXT TRANSCRIPTION OF THIS ARTICLE! --></div><div type="headline"><list><item><app><rdg wit="#CT021">FACTS NOT FANCIES</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></item></list></div><div type="headlines"><list><item><app><rdg wit="#CT021"><hi rend="double">The Times</hi> City Slave Girl Exposures Are Not Sensational</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021"><!-- rjp: to say unidentified here and above seems ambiguous we know that above the person is another Times reporter and here we know that the person speaking is a prominent member of the labor organizations in Chicago: added archetypes #promMen and #reporter --><said who="#promMen" ana="male">Are not the <hi rend="single">white slave</hi> articles in <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> somewhat sensational?</said></rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">The man who asked the question was <persName ref="#promMen">Charles L. Hutchinson</persName>, president of <orgName ref="#BOT">the board of trade</orgName> and also president of <orgName ref="#CEB">the Corn Exchange bank</orgName>. The reporter for <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>, to whom the question was addressed, answer in this manner:</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Yesterday accompanied by an inspector from the health department, I vistied and inspected <orgName ref="#Doremus" type="exposedCompany">Doremus laundry</orgName> at <placeName type="address" ref="#Doremus">269 and 271 South Paulina street</placeName>. The front is a two-story brick, a new building only partially occupied as yet, but the work-shop is an old three-story frame in the rear. Here about ninety girls and ten men work ten hours a day, and three of the girls are less than 15 years old. Last week three of the girls succumbed to the heat, one of them being so completely prostrated that she had to be sent home in a carriage. The upright box on the second floor, called by courtesy a closet, is disgustingly unclean, but it is a summer resort as compared with the one on the third floor. <seg>At the time of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#reporter">my</w> <w type="noun">visit</w></phr><!-- rjp: not positive this is Nelson reporting?? Don't think it is soooo who gets the ana? --> not a particle of water flowed into it, and it could only be flushed and cleaned by means of buckets full of water, brought by hand and dumped into it.</seg> <seg>It was <phr><w type="poss">nobody's</w> <w type="noun">business</w></phr><!-- rjp: oh boy who is the ana? do we leave it blank? options? more general and doesn't need an ana reference or that it is meant as an employee?? --> to bring in this water.</seg> Seldom was it fetched at all. Your imagination can supply the rest. On this floor are employed some forty women and several men. The city ordinance requires that there shall be separate closets for every twenty <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employees</reg></choice>.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">This is <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="5"/><unclear/> premises. And <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="5"/><unclear/> moral anathema. Back of this horrible hole is a storage-room filled with an accumulation of rubbish that would smell to heaven were it not for the fact that it is too near hades for aught but a cyclone to cover the intervening distance. <seg>There is scant room for two persons to pass each other. And yet in this filthy hole the girls remove <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> street <w type="noun">clothes</w></phr> on entering the establishment in the morning, and in this same hole they don them at the end of the <phr><w type="poss">day's</w> <w type="noun">toil</w></phr>.</seg> The least experienced goes through this ordeal for $3 a week. Older hands endure for $3 a week. Older hands endure it for $5, $6, $8, and the one or two exceptional cases for $13 a week. I will guarentee to prove every statement I have made to you by the proprietors themselves. Is there anything sensational in this statement?"</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">Another sample institution is <orgName ref="#Loomis" type="exposedCompany">Loomis laundry</orgName>, at <placeName type="address" ref="#Loomis">193 and 195 West Monroe street</placeName>, somprising a one-story and basement shanty. <seg>If any man has a particle of doubt as to the truthfulness of <phr><name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name><w type="poss" ana="#CT">'</w> <w type="noun">representations</w></phr> he can visit this or any other establishment that has been inspected and see for himself.</seg> In the wash-room in the basement men and women wade around in slops half an inch deep. The only redeeming feature of the disgusting premises is that one of the dirtiest of the dirty closets is under the sidewalk, some four feet removed from the windows. so that part of the stench escapes the twenty-five girls employed, and is gratuitously distributed among the patrons of the sidewalk above. In every instance <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> has given names and street numbers so that any person taking an interest in the labor question, and having the slightest doubt as to the truthfulness of the reports can satisfy himself with but little trouble. Of course it must be understood that there is a difference between.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><seg><app><rdg wit="#CT021"><hi rend="double">Sappho<!-- rjp: persName? --> at <phr><w type="poss">her</w> <w type="poss">toilet's</w> greasy <w type="noun">task</w></phr><!-- rjp: yea I don't know what to do with this at all... lol -->, And Sappho fragrant at an evening mask.</hi></rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></seg></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">The shops and factories have been seen by <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> as they are from day to day. As a result of the inspection hundreds that were in an unsavory condition a month ago have been placed in a cleanly and fairly sanitary condition. If nothing else should be accomplished by this investigation the results would amply repay the effort to better the condition of the working women. But more marked results are to come.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">All laundries are not disagreeable. That of <orgName ref="#Munger" type="exposedCompany">Munger</orgName>, at <placeName type="address" ref="#Munger">520 West Madison street</placeName>, is clean, airy, and the <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employees</reg></choice> give evidence of tidiness and thriff. <seg>The women usually start in at about $4 a week and increase <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">wages</w></phr> to $6 and $8 in a few years.</seg> Much of the work is done by the piece. <seg>One girl gets <num type="fraction" value=".5">1/2</num><!-- rjp: should consider how to format these so they actually look like fractions --> cent for starching a <phr><w type="poss">man's</w> <w type="noun">shirt</w></phr>, another <num type="fraction" value=".375">3/8</num><!-- rjp: should consider how to format these so they actually look like fractions --> cent for ironing the bosom, another the same price for ironing the body, and still another <num type="fraction" value=".5">1/2</num><!-- rjp: should consider how to format these so they actually look like fractions --> cent for ironing the collar-band and folding.</seg> Most of this work is done by machinery run by steam. Closets and ventilation are all that could be asked.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p><p><app><rdg wit="#CT021">At the <orgName ref="#OrienLaun" type="exposedCompany">Oriental laundry</orgName>, on <placeName ref="#OrienLaun" type="address">West Madison street</placeName>, of which <persName ref="#employer">E. Jennings</persName> is proprietor, there are eighty women and twenty men employed. <seg>Quite a number of the women are past <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">prime</w></phr>, but some are young and looking ahead.</seg> <seg>One jolly woman of 62, who has worked eighteen years in this establishment and earns from $5 to $7 a week, said the only way to increase wages was to stop immigration. She was quite a philosopher in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr>.</seg> The range of wages is from <num type="fraction" value="87.5">87 1/2</num><!-- rjp: should consider how to format these so they actually look like fractions --> cents a day to $8 a week. It is here that the laundering is done for the <orgName ref="#PPcar"><damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">Pullman</supplied></unclear> Palace Car company</orgName>, at least 20,000 pieces being handled daily. They are returned to the different depots by delivery-wagons and in bales. One bale contains 200 sheets, another 900 pillow-slips, and a third 1,400 towels. Most of the curtains for the <orgName ref="#PPcar">Pullman</orgName> cars are made on the upper floor of this building, the sewing girls averaging about $7 per week. Everything possible is done by machinery. The stairways are lighted and ample. There are fire escapes. The closets are separate and in good condition. In short, the establishment is well arranged throughout.</rdg><rdg wit="#WSGC23"></rdg></app></p></div><!-- RJP: continued after this article there is a column title "PUBLIC OPINION" with letters to the editor regarding the Nelson series. The ending column under this title is partially legible and can be transcribed; however, the continuing column (the far right column of the page) is cut off in the available NYU PDFS. Ideally the project would want to have all parts of the series including these direct responses in our database, but until we are able to re-photograph these articles the transcription will have to end here or sit mid-paragraph unfinished. Note: these responses are also not included in the Barkley text.--></div></body></text>
</TEI>
