<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div>
    <div type="article">
        <head>
            <wit id="CT_02">
                <pb n="1" id="CT_02"/>
                <headline type="main">The Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday Morning,
                        July 31, 1888</date></headline>
                <headline>CITY SLAVE GIRLS</headline>
                <list>
                    <item>Further Details of the Factory Investigation Conducted by “The Times” Lady
                        Reporter.</item>
                    <item>A Cloak Concern Where Nothing but Fear of the Law Seems to Prevent the Use
                        of the Lash.</item>
                    <item>A Sickly Child of Fifteen Compelled to Work Nine and a Half Hours for
                        Sixteen Cents.</item>
                    <item>The Unfortunate Insulted and Abused by Their Employer and Humiliated by
                        the Forewoman.</item>
                    <item>Eighty Cents a Week for Laboring from 7:30 in the Morning Until 5:30 in
                        the Evening.</item>
                </list>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSG_04">
                <list>
                    <item>A CLOAK CONCERN WHERE NOTHING BUT FEAR OF THE LAW SEEMS TO PREVENT THE USE
                        OF THE LASH.</item>
                    <item>EIGHTY CENTS A WEEK FOR LABORING FROM 7:30 IN THE MORNING UNTIL 5:30 IN
                        THE EVENING.</item>
                </list>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSFA_01">
                <p>In Chicago according to the statements given with names and places by the <hi
                        rend="italics">Times</hi> newspaper, the conditions are as bad. In many
                    places where women work there is not even a pretense of cleanliness. It is
                    proven that in one factory the women are locked in without any possi-bility of
                    leaving the room for any purpose. When the knitting girls struck in St. Louis,
                    it was shown that in some cases prostitution was one of the conditions of
                    getting and keeping work, and that many girls could not make enough money to buy
                    bread and fuel wuthout resorting to the streets. It is the general custom in
                    almost all places to discipline women workers by fining them for an infraction
                    of the rules, and there are many instances on record where the fines have taken
                    up the whole of the week’s wages although the employer got the whole of the
                    week’s work. Can anyone wonder that out of 2,000 women of the town in New York,
                    1,820 had been working girls before they took to the streets? Can anyone wonder
                    why Madison street, in Chicago, is nightly crowded with unfortuuates?</p>
                <p>But it will be well to give here in detail some of the results of the Times
                    investigations of the conditions surrounding female labor in Chicago. They have
                    additional value from the fact that they were made for a responsible newspaper
                    by a woman who shows in every line of her work her fitness for the task. It has
                    not been deemed advisable here to give the names of the firms and corporations
                    but those sufliciently interested may peruse the files of the Chicago <hi
                        rend="italics">Times</hi> beginning with July 30, 1888, and there read the
                    articles under the heading “City Slave Girls,” which should make the <hi
                        rend="italics">nom de plume</hi> of the writer, “Nell Nelson," forever dear
                    to all toiling womankind:</p>
            </wit>
        </head>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"/>
                <wit id="WSG_04"/>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">
                    <p>Tuesday July 10, according to instructions, I made up for the role of shop
                        girl, and with a list of factories in one hand, and gentle peace in the
                        other, sailed down town under a brown baize veil as impene-trable as an iron
                        mask. </p>
                </wit>
                <wit id="CT_01">
                    <p>Tuesday, July 10, according to instructions from THE TIMES, I made up for the
                        role of shop-girl, and with a list of factories in one hand and gentle peace
                        in the other sailed down State street under a brown braise veil as
                        impenetrable as an iron mask. </p>
                </wit>
            </app>
        </p>

        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">I did not realize the ignominious position of
                    respectable </wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">poverty</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">pov-erty</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">poverty</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01"> till I </wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">went to Ellinger’s cloak factory, 282 Madison street</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">went to E’s cloak factory</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">reached a cloak factory on Madison street</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">, where labor is bondage, the laboror a slave, and
                    flesh and blood cheaper than needles and thread. Corporations are said to be
                    without heart, but this concern is a commercial inquisition. It puts its help on
                    the plane of slavery, and nothing but civil law prevents the use of the
                    lash.</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">The factory is on the third floor of the large brick
                    building</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"> at the east end of Madison street bridge on the south side of the
                    street.</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04"> at the east end of Madison street bridge on the south side of the
                    street.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">.</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">Elevator? Not much.</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">An elevator is a luxury, and luxuries have no place
                </wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">at Ellinger’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">at E’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">here</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">. You will be short of breath when you reach the top
                    of the fourth flight, but in recovering you have time to take in the<pb n="18"
                        id="WSFA_01"/> surroundings - a great barn of a place with a single charm of
                    good light. There is plenty of vacant room, but the women are huddled together,
                    elbows touching along the line of machines. Beneath the west windows flows the
                    river; at the south end of the room, not ten feet from the crowded table, is a
                    tier of closets, and on hot days the combined odor of the two is shocking.
                    Nobody in his employ dare complain about smells, cold, heat, work, wages or
                    rules. But </wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">whoever</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">whoever</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">who-ever</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01"> heard of martyrs complaining?</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">My experience began at 7:50 </wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">a.m.</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04"><pb n="22" id="WSG_04"/>A. M.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">a.m.</wit>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01"> and lasted just three hours. When I climbed the
                    dusty stairs I took a ten-minute rest at the top. Everybody was at work but a
                    hungry-looking man about 27 years old, with skin the color of a Russia turnip
                    and thin, peaked features. He was dressed in a pair of heel-less slippers, a
                    white shirt, and a pair of shop pants that a clothing store pays 18 cents for
                    making. Neither collar, vest, coat nor suspenders burdened his emaciated form.
                    He moved among the workers with a cat-like tread, his shoulders drooping and his
                    knees opening and shutting with a sort of accordion movement at every step. He
                    passed me several times as I stood at the desk and eyed me so unpleasantly that
                    I turned my back to him.</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">After waiting at the desk for three-quarters of an
                    hour, I asked the clerk, a sweet little girl of 16 years, with pretty red cheeks
                    and dark eyelashes and hair, for work, and was told to wait till the forelady
                    came round. A dozen girls were waiting, too, some with cloaks, others with
                    check-books and tickets, and a few with hand-made fringe. The fringe-girl I
                    spoke to. She told me she received 5 cents a yard for making an imitation of
                    seal-ball fringe, such as winter cloaks are trimmed with. She had a piece three
                    yards and a quarter long that had taken her all the previous day to make. Here
                    was a child of 15 working nine and a half hours a day for a competence of 16 1/4
                    cents. Will the Prairie avenue woman, who, at the suggestion of Mrs. Ormison
                    Chant, is trying to find one hundred girls who are earning less than 28 cents a
                    day please enter Maggie W--- on the list, and will the women of the Protective
                    agency who want a new field of inquiry, call and see this slim, snake-gaited,
                    jaundice-faced creature who has charge of this human mill.</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04 WSFA_01">Maggie’s fringe being measured and her book checked,
                    she was given another box of material and went off to weave it into
                    tassel-trimming. The girl who took her place would not be interviewed. She
                    didn’t know how much stitchers earned<pb n="23" id="WSG_04"/> and wouldn’t tell
                    how much a week she could make.” She was, possibly, 25 years old, with a deathly
                    pale face, and looked as if she hadn’t eaten any breakfast.<pb n="19"
                        id="WSFA_01"/> Her successor was less reticent. “I’m here since May, but I
                    don’t like it; the boss is a horrid thing. Him and the forelady watches us all
                    the time, and they don’t give us hardly any work. I can only make one cloak a
                    day; some pays 30 cents, some 40 cents, and some 50 cents. Yesterday I had only
                    60 cents coming to me for two days. Are you long here? Oh, you won’t stay. They
                    search your bag and your pocket when you go home nights to see if you have any
                    thread or pieces about you.”</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"/>
                <wit id="WSG_04"/>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"> After waiting an hour the disguised investigator was properly
                    enrolled among the toilers of this particular cloak factory, assigned to a place
                    in the work-room and given a good-sized bundle of material, which was to be made
                    into a garment. </wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">Before I had a chance to talk with another unfortunate the
                    little rosy-cheeked clerk told me “it’s against the rules for new hands to stand
                    here. You must go over by the stairs and wait till the forelady comes.” I smiled
                    at the pretty child and she rewarded me by bringing a chair to me a few minutes
                    later. All means of </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">communication</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">cummunication</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"> being cut off I amused myself making sketches of the
                    shirted, slippered, sleuth-like creature as he passed.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">This pastime was interrupted by the appearance of a fat
                    woman. She had on a black sateen suit that fitted her puffy figure like the
                    raiment of a well-boiled suet pudding. She carried herself like a drum major on
                    a dress parade and by way of ornaments wore a gold watch with a double coil of
                    gold chain at her belt, gold earrings, a gold breast pin, gold cuff-buttons and
                    two gold rings. Bigger than bust or bustle was the woman’s head I discovered
                    when I asked:</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Are you the forewoman?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Forelady, yes. What do you want?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Work.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“What can you do?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Sew.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Where have you been working?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Never-Rip company.</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">N. R. Co.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"><pb n="242" id="WSG_04"/>“Want to stitch?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“No, I would rather finish.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Give your name to the clerk.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">I complied and was entered on his book as the resident of a
                    vacant lot on Monroe street. The forewoman selected a bundle as <pb n="2"
                        id="CT_02"/> big as a Kamschatka baby from a mountain of bundles and
                    said:</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Here, go over there and wait till I come.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“How much do you pay for this class of work?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“I don’t know. It seems to me you’re mighty
                    particular.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“If you don’t know who does?” I asked.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“You make me dizzy,” she said, dropping the bundle and giving
                    me a look of intense disgust. She took a small book from her pocket containing
                    the price-list and asked me what number.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“I don’t know.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Look.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Where?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“You’ll come down a peg or two before long,” and with a groan
                    she bent over the bundle at her feet, flushed apoplectically and said “360."
                    Referring again to her price-list: “Them’s sixty-five cents,” and left me.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">I raised that 65-cent ulster, and with my arms folded about
                    the fuzzy, ill-smelling thing, moved “down there,” as directed, and halted at
                    the edge of a huge rag-box. Here I stood for twenty minutes, when the forewoman
                    came aft and bade me “this way.” I pursued. There was a halt about the middle of
                    the shop and I seized it for a “scoop.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“How many girls have you here?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Never counted them.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“What can experienced cloak hands earn in a day?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Never asked them.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“How much of your salary is for politeness?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“You can sit here,” pointing to a cane chair with half the<pb
                        n="25" id="WSG_04"/> seat gone. “That girl with the black dress will do your
                    stitching; the one at the end of the second table will bind the seams, and Annie
                    down there in brown calico - she’s fixing the machine now - will give you any
                    help,” and she was off.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“I beg your pardon, did I understand you to say I would get
                    sixty-five cents for making this cloak?” following her.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Now your’re just a little bit too fresh. If you don’t want
                    the work, say so.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“I do want the work, but I want to know what it will pay
                    first.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"> “This is a 65-cent cloak. Do you get that through your head? The
                    stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder gets 15 cents, and you get 30 cents for
                    finishing if the work is right. If it isn’t, you get out.” </wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04"> “This is a 65-cent cloak. Do you get that through your head? The
                    stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder gets 15 cents, and you get 30 cents for
                    finishing if the work is right. If it isn’t, you get out.” </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01">“This is a 65-cent cloak,” said the hard-featured spinster who
                    acted as forelady. “The stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder 15 cents, and you get
                    30 cents for finishing, if the work is right.”</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"> I thanked her and was alone. Here I thought lay my fortune. Thirty
                    cents for making a long cloth cloak, after the seams were stitched. It had to be
                    trimed down the back gores around the collar, cuffs, and pockets with mohair
                    plush; the sleeves had to go in, eighteen buttons sewed on, eighteen holes
                    worked, and all the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty cents! To
                    save my life I couldn’t have finished the garment in ten hours. I was just
                    reaching that conclusion when the forewoman appeared with a small book, two
                    checks, and a piece of tailor’s chalk as big as a dime. </wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04"> I thanked her and was alone. Here I thought lay my fortune. Thirty
                    cents for making a long cloth cloak, after the seams were stitched. It had to be
                    trimed down the back gores around the collar, cuffs, and pockets with mohair
                    plush; the sleeves had to go in, eighteen buttons sewed on, eighteen holes
                    worked, and all the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty cents! To
                    save my life I couldn’t have finished the garment in ten hours. I was just
                    reaching that conclusion when the forewoman appeared with a small book, two
                    checks, and a piece of tailor’s chalk as big as a dime. </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"> Here was, indeed, a fortune! Thirty cents for making a long cloth
                    cloak after the seams were stitched. It had to be trimmed down the back gores,
                    around the collar, cuffs and pockets with mohair plush; the sleeves had to go
                    in-eighteen button-holes to be worked and a corresponding number of but-tons
                    sewed on, and the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty cents, in
                    other words, for a good day’s work of ten hours! </wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Your number is 180; chalk it on all these pieces and if you
                    lose any you will be fined.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“How much?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“How much? You cheeky thing! The cost of the cloth and the
                    cutter’s time. That’s how much. Give this check to the binder and that one to
                    the stitcher.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Will you please tell me how this side gore goes?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Go to Annie. I ain’t here to learn you how to sew.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“May I have a needle?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Furnish your own needles.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"><pb n="26" id="WSG_04"/>“May I have basting cotton?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“There aint any. You have to wait till it gets here.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">I gave a girl a penny for a needle and stole some thread from
                    an absentee’s stock. Then I waited fifteen minutes while the binder got through
                    and basted up the seams for the stitcher. That much done I got to work on the
                    plush. The forewoman passed by and told me I </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">was not “showing enough fur. Go over to the sample and look at the
                    work.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">“was not showing enough fur. Go over to the sample and look at the
                    work.”</wit>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">She sneered when I asked her where the samples were, but a
                    neighbor volunteered the information. There was no sample on the rack and I
                    stepped over to inform the forewoman, who curtly told me it was none of her
                    affair.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Will you please tell me how wide to make this
                    trimming?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Go to Annie.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">Poor Annie was doctoring a machine and said “in a minute.” On
                    her way to me three stitchers implored her to look at their miserable implements
                    and I waited patiently till I caught sight of the forewoman looking at her bangs
                    in a handglass. Apologizing for the intrusion I asked her if the sample had come
                    yet.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“No.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“I wish you would kindly show me how wide to make this
                    trimming.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Go to Annie, I told you.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Annie is too busy. She’s mending machines.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Well, I won’t be bothered with you.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“What’s the reason you won’t?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Cause I won’t”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“Well you will. Tell me how wide you want this plush or I
                    will </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">see Mr. Ellinger.</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">see Mr A---”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">“See him. I don’t care. There he is,” pointing to the snaky,
                    half-starved creature whose shanks I had been sketching and on whom I had
                    scornfully turned my back. It was too much to ask of a free-born American woman
                    to recognize the</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">su-periority</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">superi<pb n="27" id="WSG_04"/>-ority</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"> of such a person. He came up to us in an instant. The
                    forewoman was livid with rage and she began to talk as fast as her tongue could
                    move. Some fifty or more girls heard the tirade breathlessly. Before the
                    half-dressed proprietor had a chance to get over his astonishment I threw the
                    front of the cloak at his face, the side body at the forewoman, and walked off
                    to my disabled chair with </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Mr. Ellinger</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">Mr. A.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"> for a bodyguard. He was the color of a sanitarium babe when
                    we reached my work table. He had the two pieces of cloak in his hand, and when
                    he raised his fist to strike me I worked up an Indian-club attitude and dared
                    him.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04">He escorted me to the toilet-room, where I went for my hat
                    and jacket, and before slamming the door in his face by way of a hint as to the
                    privacy of the place I threw my needle and thread at him. </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">A. Ellinger</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_04">Mr. A.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_04"> saw me across the shop and down the first flight of stairs.
                    And there ended my first experience in a cloak factory.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>

        <head><app>
            <wit id="CT_02">
                <list>
                    <item>SIXTY CENTS A WEEK.</item>
                    <item>For Working from 7:30 in the Morning Untill 5:30 in the Evening --- And
                        Still the Poor Girls Complain that Prices Are Being Continually Cut
                        Down.</item>
                </list>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSG_05">
                <list>SIXTY CENTS A WEEK FOR WORKING FROM 7:30 IN THE MORNING UNTIL 5:30 IN THE
                    EVENING.</list>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
        </app></head>

        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">I next made application for work at </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Wetherell’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">W’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">, on Wabash avenue, where hundreds of girls are employed on
                    corsets, bustles, skirts, jerseys and cloaks. Boarding the freight elevator I
                    was drawn up to the top floor, where a pretty little Jewess informed me that </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Mr. Saalsbery</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">Mr. S.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> was engaged, but would see me in a little while. She showed
                    me to a seat in the rear end of the store at the entrance to the shop-room, and
                    for a single hour I listened to the drop, drop, drop of the heavy machinery and
                    the snatches of song and merriment between the iron roar. Presently </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Mr. Wetherell</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">Mr. W.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> came and sat by me.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Did you want work?” he asked.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"><pb n="28" id="WSG_05"/>“Very much.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“What kind of work have you been doing?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">I admitted I had never worked in a factory, but told him I
                    could sew and was willing to do anything that would give me a living.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Well, you ought to have a chance - a good chance if you are
                    willing to work - but it’s dull just now and I don’t see where we can put you.
                    You say you can sew. Run the machine, too? Well, we start our skirt and cloak
                    rooms in a couple of weeks and then we can try you.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“But I must have work,” I persisted, “at once. </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">I can’t wait two weeks.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05"/>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Mr. Wetherell</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">Mr. W.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> sighed a little and left me to see a customer who had just
                    then entered. While I was fixing up a romance in case any inquiry was made as to
                    my age, name, residence and position in life a sad-faced Irish mother came up
                    the four stories with a 16-year-old daughter. They were as poorly dressed as
                    myself, but considerably less happy. The mother’s hands were hard, thin and
                    work-worn, and her face seamed with care. She wore an old bonnet, a coarse black
                    dress, poor shoes, an old shawl, and an expression of injury, despondency and
                    severity. Annie was a well-developed girl, with a good, wholesome face, red
                    cheeks, bright, fun-loving eyes, big hands and feet, a most ungainly manner, and
                    a nice figure. She had been crying, for her lashes were wet, and she seemed
                    expectant that a crisis of some sort was near at hand. I soon learned that the
                    mother missed her calling when she adopted maternal duties. The family lived in
                    the region of Blue Island avenue and consisted of the parents and growing
                    children, two or three having married. Annie was the youngest and “had to do
                    something for her grub, “ as the mother said. For a long, time she worked in a
                    box factory and made good wages, but the work was not steady, and last January
                    she came to </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Wetherell’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">W.’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">And what do you think she did?</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">She earned 80 cents a week cutting dress reeds from 7:30<pb
                        n="29" id="WSG_05"/> o’clock in the morning until 5:30 in the evening. Annie
                    will be 17 years old in September. Here is her account of the work:</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Oh yes, I like it. They don’t pay me much, but the </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">forelady’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">fore-lady’s</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> good to me, and </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">Mr. Saalsbery</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">Mr. ---</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> is awful kind. The girls is nice, too. The only thing I
                    don’t like is that they’re always cuttin’ me down. I can’t make hardly
                    nothing.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Last week? Oh, last week I wasn’t here. I staid home. It was
                    so hot I didn’t want to take the trouble to come down for 13 cents a day and
                    walk and put up my lunch.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Thinking the girl’s calculations were amiss I turned to the
                    mother, who confirmed the statement, adding: “It don’t pay to feed that kid to
                    work on the pay she’s getting.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“It’s what all the girl’s gets,” added Annie, beginning to
                    cry. I played mother for a little while, told her she was a good girl to help
                    her parents and not to mind, for there was plenty of work, and if she comes to </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">THE TIMES</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">the <hi rend="italics">Times</hi></wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> I’ll help her get it.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">After the Irish gray eyes had been dried with both corners of
                    her little black shawl she gave me the prices at which she had been working.
                    Here they are:</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">One cent a gross for cutting steels in eleven, fifteen and
                    eighteen inch length. The work is done by machine, the operator using one foot
                    and both hands constantly.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Four cents a gross for sewing buckles on bustles.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Three cents a dozen for basting bustles.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Four cents a dozen for springing bustles.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Seventy cents a dozen for putting elastics on reeds and
                    boxing the same.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Wages in this department vary from 60 cents to $3 a week,
                    $1.50 being a very fair average, and this, too, for girls of 19 years and
                    less.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>

        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">When the manager had dismissed his guest he waited on<pb
                        n="30" id="WSG_05"/> Annie’s mother, who turned traitress, betraying her own
                    child to the enemy in this style:</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Can Annie come back, sir?” she asked.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Why, I guess so. What’s been the matter?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">Annie rolled her finger up in black fringe, hung her head,
                    and allowed the tears to stream down her cheeks.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Oh she’s so sassy,” kindly volunteered the mother, “and she
                    comes home to me with a batch of stories every night about your cuttin’ down the
                    prices. Sure I can’t believe a word she says.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Well, you come in the morning, Annie, and I’ll see what we
                    can do for you.” With this dismissal, poor Annie followed her mother, who
                    doubtless felt that she had done her duty by the child.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">I recited my piece to the low-voiced gentleman, who said
                    there was plenty of work in the bustle department, but he guessed it wouldn’t be
                    pleasant for me, as the girls were only sixteen or so. I tried to assure him
                    that I didn’t care about the company, that I only wanted a chance to make a
                    living for myself.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Well, I don’t think you could earn enough to support
                    yourself at machine work. Come in about Monday and I </wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02">think</wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05">thin</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05"> we can give you something at $3 or so.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Three dollars a week?”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“Yes.”</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02 WSG_05">“God have mercy on the girls,” I said reverently and
                    departed.</wit>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
        <p>
            <app>
                <wit id="CT_02"> NELL NELSON. </wit>
                <wit id="WSG_05"/>
                <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
            </app>
        </p>
    </div>
    <div type="advertisement">
        <app>
            <wit id="CT_02">
                <p>The White Factory Slaves --</p>
                <p>Read THE TIMES</p>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSG_05"/>
            <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
        </app>
    </div>
    <div type="lettersToEditor">
        <app>
            <wit id="CT_02">
                <pb n="4" id="CT_02"/>
                <head>“SLAVE GIRLS OF CHICAGO”</head>
                <div id="CT002_LE1">
                    <head>The Good Work Begun by “The Times” Heartily Seconded.</head>
                    <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-30">CHICAGO, July 30 - TO THE
                            EDITOR:</inLineHead> Oh, how long have I looked for a friendly hand to
                        be extended in behalf of the poor working girls of this city. African
                        slavery in the south never could, I think, compare with the white slavery of
                        Chicago. What are we living for? That’s the question. Here I am, working as
                        a type-writer for a millionaire and getting $3 a week. If such men are not
                        to be punished in this world then I can only cherish the hope that there is
                        another, where punishment will be meted out to them. Whoever connected with
                        your paper too this bold stand to right the wrongs of the hard-worked,
                        industrious, poor girls of this city may heaven bless him. Could I but
                        declare myself and make known the indignities to which I have been subjected
                        the earth might better for them open and swallow up the accursed. My prayer
                        is that your valuable paper will leave no inquiry unsatisfied, but will
                        fearlessly and to the point strike for the rights and the life of the girls;
                        and I hope to see the business men of Chicago aroused to a proper sense of
                        their meanness.</p>
                    <p type="signed">MARY.</p>
                </div>
                <div id="CT002_LE2">
                    <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-30">CHICAGO, July 30 - TO THE
                            EDITOR:</inLineHead> Your exposure of “Life Among the Slave Girls of
                        Chicago” ought to awaken a deep interest among our people. Who can forget
                        that memorable utterance of Horace Greeley: “I am glad to have lived in that
                        day and generation which gave the deathblow to American slavery and to
                        imprisonment for debt.” But today we have another and most damnable system
                        of slavery carried on for the greed of people at the expense of life and
                        health, virtue, home, and, it may be, heaven. This hideous crime practiced
                        upon defenseless woman is all to make the “rich richer and the poor poorer.”
                        It must come to an end. The thought of this state of things must some day
                        burn the hearts or sting the conscience of our commercial people. ’Tis a
                        shame and disgrace, and I hope your articles will be the means of calling
                        effectual attention to it.</p>
                    <p type="signed">J.W.B.</p>
                </div>

            </wit>
            <wit id="WSG_05"/>
            <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
        </app>
    </div>
    <div type="advertisement">
        <app>
            <wit id="CT_02">
                <pb n="8" id="CT_02"/>
                <head type="main">The Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday, July 31,
                        1888.</date></head>
                <head>
                    <p>The White Slaves.</p>
                    <p>Continuation of the Exposures now being made by</p>
                    <p>The Chicago Times</p>
                </head>
                <p>Another chapter printed this morning, and still another ready for tomorrow
                    morning.</p>
                <p>The lead is being followed up. The deeper we go the more abominable are the
                    outrages revealed.</p>
                <p>Have girls and women any rights that overbearing, ignorant, and brutal employers
                    are bound to respect?</p>
                <p>The men who are pauperizing and degrading female labor. How they do it, where
                    they do it, what they make by doing it.</p>
                <p>Read the second chapter today, the third chapter tomorrow, and every chapter till
                    the story is told.</p>
                <head>Read The Times.</head>
            </wit>
            <wit id="WSG_05"/>
            <wit id="WSFA_01"/>
        </app>
    </div>
</div>
