<div type="section" n="22">
PATHETIC STORIES OF THE LITTLE ONES WHO ARE SACRIFICING YOUTH, BEAUTY, AND LIFE ITSELF TO MAMMON.
HOW THE QUESTION OF MARRIAGE IS AFFECTED BY YEARS OF CLOSE APPLICATION TO SHOP DRUDGERY.
P. K. company! Pretty name, isn't it? Done in gens d'arm
blue letters on a navy-blue ground it makes an exceedingly
effective sign. The very colors suggest the claims of long
descent and blue blood.
<pb n="130"/>
But the P. company on West Washington street has nothing
to do with blue blood or gentle women, and there is nothing
pretty about it but the sweet young girls of fifteen and sixteen
and the frail children of nine and ten whose lives are being
wound about the great wooden bobbins, and from whose
cheeks the roses of health and beauty are slowly absorbed by
the flying threads in shuttle, needle, and spindle.
P. K. company is only another name for the women's shirt
factory at West Washington street. Up one flight of stairs I
pass into a tidy little office where a fine looking gentleman
gives me greeting and calls the forewoman, Mrs. M. She is
young and pretty. Her voice is sweet and she has a good
face.
"Yes, I have work but it won't pay you. You can't
live on the salary. I wouldn't advise you to take it. The
table girls only get three dollars a week. Their work consists
in sewing on buttons and finishing the armholes of the shirts.
We have generally employed little girls of twelve and thirteen
to do it. Better work pays by the piece, five and ten cents
a dozen for knitting a finish about the neck and armholes and
bottom of the shirts. But you would have to be experienced;
we couldn't take the time to teach you."
I told her I would try the table work until I could get
something that paid better, as I was wholly dependent on my
own resourses<!-- RJP:10/29/15:spelling retained from original -->.
"That's it, you see. I don't like to take you and have you
leave as soon as you begin to be useful."
"But I can't live on three dollars a week to save my soul,
unless I subsist on cold water and wind and sleep with the
birds."
In as mild a manner as possible she told me that the P. K.
company never meddled with the private affairs of its employes,
and agreeing to promote me whenever a vacancy occured that
I was able to fill. I started to fasten the tail ends of knitted
<pb n="131"/>
shirts at the munificent sum of fifty cents a day, or five cents
an hour, work beginning at 7 a. m., and closing at 5:40 p. m.
with thirty minutes for lunch. I paid five cents for a paper of
sewing needles and five cents for a set of crochet needles before
doing a stitch of work, so that at noon I had but fifteen cents
to my credit.
When the forewoman took me to the furnishing table I
failed to see where she could put me. Down the long sides
and across the ends were the girls, thirty or more, unpleasantly
crowded, for the weather was hot, the room close, and the
double row of shirts piled two and three feet deep intercepted
any breeze that came in through the side windows. Beginning at one end she made the girls "shove up a little," and
with this allowance from fifteen room enough was made for
another chair to which I was assigned.
The work was light, requiring but a few stitches at five or
more places. Where the pattern was imperfect I had to crochet a couple of scallops, otherwise a few stitches with a zephyr
needle sufficed. The slowest girl finished five dozen shirts a
day, and some twice that number. A few at the board sewed
on buttons and a regiment filed past with armfuls of shirts, in
or ready to be put in boxes. We were so crowded that nearly
every passer-by knocked me in the head with her elbow or
load, while the girl at my left drew her needle under my very
nose at each stitch. I could neither take up nor lay down my
scissors without annoyance to the little girl on my right.
I marveled as I looked at these girls that they should be
permitted to labor as they did, ten hours a day in a dark, hot,
room, exposed as they were to all manner of disease and the
dangers of fire, for scarcely more wages than sufficed for food
and car-fare. There was not a single attractive feature about
their surroundings. The smoke from the engine had blackened
the walls and the ceiling so that in the rear of the shop no
calcimine was visible. At either end were two windows and
<pb n="132"/>
two more had been cut in the west wall, without supplying
the needs of the round-shouldered workers, not a few of whom
had defective sight.
The distribution of a pair of closets and a brace of sinks in
no way enhanced their value, for at noon-time the girls stood
in line and waited for their turn to get near them.
The sink at which I tried to fix my toilet was filled with
dirty water, in which the little girls washed, drying on their
own or a neighbors apron. There was a towel but it had
exhausted its usefulness.
The shirts were knitted by machines - thirteen or more
little girls standing before the conical bobbins simply to keep
the threads from getting tangled. These children were on
their feet all day and at noon they sat on the floor and ate
their lunches, leaning against the straps and legs of the knitters. Whatever these girls may have been in years - in face,
form, size and strength they were little more than infants.
Pale? Yes; bleached by confinement and thin as reeds
from loss of sleep, loss of sunshine, of pure air, of wholesome
food, and of play. Many of them had to be up at five o'clock
in the morning, and all at six to get to the shop by seven. In
return for their service they are paid three dollars a week, or
five cents an hour. Poor indeed is the home that must depend
on such a mean compensation for all that is lost to the child - 
health, vigor, youth.
The machine-girls who trimmed the little woolen glove-fitting shirts were paid by the piece, most of them earning
seventy-five cents a day and a few one dollar. So far as I
could learn all the hands lived at home and each was one of a
large family. They were mostly of foreign extraction, but not
a few American families were represented by little sisters or
daughters who were working for five and ten cents an hour to
buy ribbons and theater tickets. To be just, they were in the
minority; the vast army of youthful martyrs worked that
<pb n="133"/>
younger brothers and sisters might have bread and shoes and
a shelter.
Here is some of the talk I overheard :
"How are you feeling, Maggie?"
"I'm terribly sick, I can tell you. I slept with plasters on
my feet, and I havn't sat down all morning. My mother told
me to come home this noon if they kept me running and I
didn't feel well. No, I guess I'll try and stay. I'm savin' up
for a cloak and have only four dollars so far."
Another child: "Didn't have hardly no lunch 'cause it was
six when mother called me, and I eat my breakfus with her
buttnin' my clothes, and shoved what I could in my box.
There's no butter on this, and I didn't get no meat, but I don't
care, mother's goin' to make me pancakes tonight."
Still another wished "they'd permote" her, because she
had had nothing to wear since the rent was raised. The
evening before they "went for chips and got loads of blocks
from the pavement."
Hanging about were the usual rules and regulations relative
to punctuality and property. One requiring that a three-days'
notice preparatory to leaving, under penalty of forfeiting a
week's salary, had greater prominence than the rest.
</div>