<div type="section" n="7">
STARVATION WAGES.
"Boy, don't take her down! Don't go down!! do you hear?
I'll discharge you if you let her escape."
There I was in S's freight elevator with my day's work in
my arms and the wire screen separating me from the furies of
<pb n="34"/>
Mrs. J. S., her forewoman, the second assistant, and the book-
keeper.
It was 5:30 o'clock Tuesday afternoon. I had made a big,
black cloth cloak all but sewing on the buttons, had resigned
my position as slave-stitcher, and had asked to be paid off. I
had been refused by the quartet outside of the elevator screen,
and so was on my way to the head of the firm, work in arms.
It was a great day for S. and me, particularly me.
It was another verification of putting "a beggar on horseback," of getting a "nigger" to drive a "nigger."
At 7:40 in the morning I had rolled my hat in my factory
jacket, and, stowing the bundle away in one of the holes
designed for that purpose by J. S. &amp; Co., presented myself at
the office, a square of six feet near the center of the work-room
inclosed in a wire fence, where the forewoman and an examiner were trying on two models the finished cloaks of the previous day. The models were tall, rather fine-looking girls.
They, I learned, received $8 a week and did nothing but "try
on and look at themselves in the glass," representing the highest
class of, factory girls. The forewoman, who jerked these
tall, animate figures fore and aft to see the front of a beaver
"empress," or the back of a seal-plushy "mi-lady," was very
nicely dressed in a black sateen figured with crosses of white.
And oh, how she talked! , In dislocated English, in a shrill
rasping voice, compared to which the notes of a pea-hen would
be melodious. My steady gaze annoyed her, and stopping at
the hem of a long coat she was inspecting she asked:
"Why are you sitting there so much?"
I told her I wanted work. Bidding me "come along" she
pushed me with anything but motherly tenderness toward the
desk and told " Rosy" to give me "von of them samples."
I took a place with nine others who were waiting for "Rosy"
to provide them with more work, and fell to studying my
neighbors. "Rosy," the girl who kept the shop-book, gave
<pb n="35"/>
out the work and trimmings, and properly checked it all, may
have been 14 years old. She was short in stature, work having
stunted her growth, and emaciated in face and figure. Her
hands were black with dye from handling the bundles of work.
"I can't give any of you work till Mary comes back," she
said. "She's gone down to tell John to send up some."
I placed a small box on the counter containing some graham
wafers and a lemon, which, being pushed across the board,
attracted Rosy's attention. She uncovered the box.
"Look at the lunch," she said, and a bunch of heads came
together to see.
‘‘And a thimble," said a blonde.
‘‘Yes, and scissors. Oh, and the little watch! And whose
is it?"
‘‘Them's awful nice cakes," observed a little creature of
about 13 years.
I offered the child a cracker, and when she refused I pressed
it on her till a hungry little friend said: "She dasn't. She'll
be fined if she eats before the whistle."
When Mary came up I was entered on Rosy's book, given a
number and a "Homer."
"How much does a ‘Homer' pay?" I asked.
Rosy didn't know. Neither did Miss Seebert, the teacher.
I went to the forewoman and was told to get out of her way.
Persisting in knowing what revenue the "Homer" would
bring, the attenuated, corset-cramped "forelady" asked me to
go away and find out any particulars whfen Mrs. Stein returned.
The teacher gave me a chair at a long, low table with fifteen
girls on either side, and asked me where I had worked before.
I mentioned the "Never Rip" factory.
"Make cloaks?" she asked.
"No. Jerseys."
"Did you never make a cloak?"
"Never."
<pb n="36"/>
"Oh, you'll have a hard time."
Thirty pair of eyes looked at me.	.
"Can you sew?" I was asked.
"You bet."
This bit of slang captured the teacher and set me on a com-
fortable plane with my neighbors. Reversing the tactics of
Ella Wheeler Wilcox, I began at the hardest task first, and
got the blonde-haired teacher to show me how to arrange the
collar. It was a rolling affair that was attached to a cape, and
had to be double-faced with satin. The bands were cut on the
bias, and novice-like I stretched the first one and had to rip it
off. Three times I ripped it and sewed it, and when I showed
it to a girl at my right hand she said: "It ain't right. She'll
pull it off."
"Would you tell me how to fix it?" I asked.
"Oh, I can't. Go to Miss S." She screamed to Miss S. to
come. Despairing of her aid I made another attempt.
"I'd show you if I had time," my neighbor explained, but
I've been on this cloak two and one-half days, and its only
45 cents."
There are chords in a woman's heart which are struck by
accident only - strange, varying strings which, remaining mute
to the most earnest and passionate appeals, respond at once to
the slightest and most casual touch. I sympathized with the
poor little woman, who turned about and opened her
heart to me.
"It's an awful hard place to work in," she said. "Prices
are going down all the time, and the girls can hardly earn
anything. Yesterday was pay-day. We're paid the 1st and
15th. I had only $6.10 coming to me for the two weeks. I
have the toothache all the time and I am a month at the dentist's. He's filling my teeth with cement and I don't have
anything coming to me when I pay him. All I keep out Of
my wages is thirty cents for car-fare. I live out on F. and R.
<pb n="37"/>
streets and can't always walk in the morning and get here at
7:45. Sometimes I do, but I never ride home. If I didn't
live home I'd—I'd—I'd—I'd starve. I would. What'd prevent it?"
Interested in our talk a pretty, brown-eyed girl across the
table told us that she had been trying to get a pair of shoes
since June. I live at Englewood and have to keep out $1.25
for car-fare," she continued. "Monday I took out this 40-cent
cloak and it isn't done yet. I took it to the forelady this morn-
ing and she said it was all right. Just a minute ago I showed
it to her and she ripped all these plaits and pulled the bustle
out. I'll not be able to get it done tonight, I know. Last
fortnight I made only $4.20."
"Here, you girls, stop your talking and do your work or I'll
have to fine you," said the teacher.
"You'r new and I'll excuse you," she said, turning to me,
but you musn't talk any more. Where's your collar? Oh!
you have the hooks and eyes on the wrong side. Rip them off
and put the hooks on the right and the eyes on the left. Then
press out your seam."
I took my turn at the gas-stove, skirmished round for a piece
of paper or a rag large enough for a holder, burned my finger
and came near burning a hole in "Homer's" neck. When I
went back to my chair the little Englewood girl was in tears.
She had the fur down the front of her cloak too tight and was
ripping it off for the third time. The fur may have been nine-
tenths wool, but so uncertain was the hair that the girl had
taken a fine comb from her box and was trying to comb up the
nap to hide the needle line. Her companion, Mary, had been
in equally hard luck. Five times she took her brown "mi-lady" and five times came back with it. First the felting was
not thick enough; next the color was wrong; the third time
the buttons were not plumb; the fourth complaint was made
against a crescent bustle, Mrs. S. having expressed a preference
<pb n="38"/>
for two small square bags, and finally the ornaments on the
shoulders and front darts were not straight. Mary was a
pudgy young Irish maiden on whom the men and the world in
general had soured.
"What will I do when I'm old? I'll be an old maid and live
by myself," she remarked. "I'm saving to buy a house for
that time. Good Lord, I havn't saved a cent in three years.
I'm here now two years, but I'm going to get another place.
Here's my third day on this rag of a cloak that only pays 60
cents. Yesterday I got $6.10 for the fifteen days in July. I'm
sick of it now. Where do I live? I have a room on Bleeker
street. I pay $1.50 a week for it and $1 for food. After I take
the price of lunches and car-fare from the rest I havn't enough
to pay for washing the bedclothes."
The teacher heard the best part of this account, and, coming
over to our table, put her arms about the morose little worker
and said: "Don't get blue; you'll do better in a day or two."
At noon the whistle blew and we stopped for lunch. Some
of the hands made tea and coffee on the gas stoves, but not a
soul left the shop but Mrs. S. and the models.
You pampered daughters of fashion, you children of ease,
you epicureans, who enjoy soups, entrees, fritters, roasts, pastries, could you but see the meal spread out at noon in this
factory, the chances are there would be a diminution of your
fastidiousness.
No. 99 was a pretty, brown-eyed, happy girl with curly hair
and a merry, brave, good face. She had two cuts of cherry
pie that did not aggregate a surface as wide as her hand. She
finished the juicy crust and I insisted on her eating a pair of
my graham wafers. Ninety-nine had a headache and was
going off for an afternoon in Lincoln park. The girl next to
her, who said she was "the very devil," devoured two links of
Frankfort sausage and a pear. A near neighbor had a slice of
<pb n="39"/>
brown bread and two tomatoes, and the girl she talked with ate
green apples and soda-crackers.
At five minutes past 12 we had eaten, drank, and were at
work again. Many of the girls went to the sink to wash their
arms, neck, and faces, scour their teacups or coffee cans and
comb their hair. While I was exploring the toilet (?) section
two men came in and I scampered. A nice arrangement this,
but no one seemed to mind it. If Dr. De Wolf wants to do
something for the factory girls he will have one of his assist-
ants go over and scent this portion of the S. estate, for it
"smells to heaven."
The excellent light that filled the Jersey company and flooded
the workshop of E's top floor I missed at S's, where the ceiling is low and the ventilation and light inadequate. A skylight cuts the center of the roof, but with the curtains drawn
to keep out the burning sunlight the machine operators had
difficulty in threading their needles.
"Please do not take any paper," was the notice posted above
a pile of work ready for delivery. It seems the girls were in
the habit of going to this pile for bits of paper in which to
wrap their lunch-box or an old shop skirt, and when the
"searcher" found it difficult to look into the parcels for the
possible spool of two-cent thread the firm took this method of
stopping the practice.
Over the iron sink was a placard warning the girls "against
throwing any slops into this sink under penalty of 50 cents."
On the opposite wall hung the literary gem of the factory.
Here it is:
"Ladies and Gentlemen it is your interest and that of your neighbors that no talking is allowed. Whoever talks loud is fined 10 cents."
<pb n="40"/>
This rather ambiguous motto hung above the hat rack: "In
order to protect the lunches of our employes<!-- RJP:10/20/15: spelling retained --> no eating is
allowed till 12 o'clock. Anyone breaking this rule will be fined."
Another legend informed the army of martyrs the J. S. &amp; C. had no goods at retail. Anyone waiting to purchase must
ask Mr. S. Apropos of the subject I learned that a girl paid
$14 for a garment that I feel sure could have been bought for
$9 in any retail house. She took it on the easy payment plan,
and for three months lived on tea-dust and broken crackers.
"The tea was 15 cents a pound," she told me, " and I got the
crackers at a Thirteenth street bakery, two pounds for 5 cents.
It was a heavy cloak, though, and I had it on the bed nights.
What did I do with my money?. Oh! God, but you're fresh.
One dollar and fifty cents for the room, 60 cents for three baskets of coal, 30 cents for car-fare, $1 for the housekeeping and
$1 to S. for cloak. Sometimes I only made $6 in two weeks,
and often when it rained or snowed I took the car home, and
then I run behind."
I finished my cloak about 5:20 o'clock and carried it to the
desk to see about having it examined. I showed it to Miss S.
"Your work is very neat," she said, "and you have nice
corners. Now I'll try you on a jacket."
"Thank you : I guess I won't work any more. If you will
get me the buttons I'll sew them on and go home.
She called me her dear, told me to try a month or so, that I
could earn four dollars a week before next year, and finally
said that she couldn't give me the buttons because the cloak
had to go down stairs to the pressers.
"Well I'll wait until it comes up."
"But it won't come up maybe for a week," she remarked.
"How will I get my pay, then?"
"You can't get paid till the 1st. Go and see the forelady."
That party told me to go away and let her alone.
<pb n="41"/>
"But I have no car-fare," I said by way of molification.
Without molifying a bit, she asked:
"What's that to me? I ain't no car company."
"I am not going to work here any more. I want to go home.
I live far out and must have car-fare. Won't you take my
order-ticket and advance me thirty-five cents?"
"Thanks. I take no orders from you," and giving her
wiry features another twist she left me. "Rosy" called for
the cloak which I hugged in my arms and refused to surrender.
I carried my woolly burden to the book-keeper, told my
trouble, and asked for an order for my pay.
"I can't give you an order" said that party. "We don't
pay but twice a week. See Mrs. S."
Mrs. S. runs the shop and runs it with shrewdness. A
dozen or fifteen years ago she graduated from a local factory
to become the wife of Mr. S. She has a beautiful home up on
Dearborn avenue, and several children, all of whom are cared
for by competent servants. Mr. S. manages the business and
Mrs. S. bosses the cutters, the pressers, the finishers, the
operators, the clerks, forewomen, and models connected with
the factory. She is a yellow-haired little woman with a sharp
voice, a trim, graceful figure, generous jeweled hands and
features that were not addicted to relaxation. And her eyes!
Nothing escapes them, sewing or sewess. Nothing goes that
is not right-"precisely right" to use her own words. Every
girl has a number which is put on the cloak she is to make.
If there is a flaw or a false stitch in the work, all Mrs. S. has,
to do is to scream out the number on the ticket and the hapless
girl advances with more or less timidity for the never-failing
tongue-lashing - alias corrections.
While I stood at the book-keeper's desk with the finished
"Homer" in my arms Mrs. S. appeared. She was gorgeous
in black satin with a goblin blue basque trimmed with gold
lace and fastened at the throat with a gold serpentine brooch.
<pb n="42"/>
In deference to all this finery, I began with some degree of
obsequiousness.
"I beg your pardon; is this Mrs. S.?"
"That's my name," was the answer as she disappeared in a
packing box and hauled up a handfull of patterns. Seeing
that she did not intend to refer to me, I took a tighter grip on
"Homer" and plunged into the fray.
"I made this cloak today and wish to sever my relations
with your very excellent establishment," I continued.
"Then put that cloak over on the presser and go."
"I want to be paid."
"You can not. Pay days are the first and fifteenth."
"I will have my pay now. What do you give for the
'Homer?'"
"I do not know."
"Who does?"
Here she screamed to the forewoman to know why she was
"troubled by such a creature as this." The party addressed
labled me with a few choice epithets in hysterical English, and
for an instant I thought Mrs. S. was going to jump on me.
"Give me that cloak," she demanded with heaving breast
and swelling nostrils.
"Not until you give me my money," I replied.
She called me insolent, beggarly and worthless, and when I
told her that a woman who had been reared a factory girl
should have some pity for the class, she was a model for the
queen of tragedy.
The audience was speechless and the forewoman so affected
that she rattled like an agitated bag full of clothes pins.
While the lookers-on were waiting for something to turn up,
the elevator ascended and I stepped in the car, still hugging
"Homer." I was going to see Mr. S. when his wife raised
her voice and jeweled hand and ordered the boy not to take me
down. "Homer," the boy, and I stood on the inside of the
<pb n="43"/>
wire screen and looked out, and the three women and the
book-keeper stood on the outside and looked in.
"Raise the door boy. Your number's 101 isn't it?" An
armistice I thought and answered: "You have said it."
"Go and sew on the buttons and get your pay - seventy-
five cents."
Miss S. escorted me to the desk, Rosy counted out thirty-six
buttons, and I went back to my chair to button "Homer." It
was 5:45 o'clock and the hands were beginning to leave. The
cashier would be gone, too, in fifteen minutes, and it was not
possible to sew on three dozen buttons in that time. However,
I had made up my mind not to surrender "Homer" until I
was paid. The teacher, bless her fair hair, came and helped
me to space the button line, and we had three sewed on when
Mrs. S. appeared and mentioned her pride at having been
factory-born.
"You need not put those buttons on. I'll make you a
present of the wrork"
I declined her offer and was told to go to the desk and get
paid. The book-keeper made out a check and asked for the
cloak which I gave up with alacrity. When I got in the
elevator the boy asked if I had a pass.
"No."
"Then I'll have to search you."
"For what?"
"Stolen goods."
I defied him to touch me and the presence of the book-keeper
averted another war.
At the desk I was identified and received seventy-five cents
for making a thirty-five dollar cloak. I went up-stairs again to
Mrs. S. and threw five nickles on the board for the unfortunate
girl who sewed the buttons on my cloak. The rest of my
wages I gave to the teacher, the only person connected with
the firm of J. S. &amp; Co. who showed me any kindness.
<pb n="44"/>
The fidelity of the girls passed entirely unnoticed. Not a
word of commendation came from the manager or her assistants
who were most prodigal of reproof. By the men and boys
these poor, patient, uncomplaining shop girls were pushed
about in the elevators, on the stairs, and in the narrow aisles
like so many sheep, and three little girls, two Marys and.
Francis were made the slaves of everybody.
How these little girls live in winter is a mystery. With
few exceptions their dresses were poor and insufficient, coarse
and shapeless. Many were torn and showed the stitches of
thread and cord drawn across the holes.
But worse than broken shoes, ragged clothes, filthy closets,
poor light, high temperature, and vitiated atmosphere was the
cruel treatment by the people in authority. There are pains
that rack a sensitive nature to which no physical agony can be
compared, and shots from malicious eyes that fatally wound,
but raise no cry of injury. There are robberies of a gentle
life that beggar peace and joy, and cuts of hatred that murder
forever the sweet faith that belongs to woman's nature.
</div>