<div type="section" n="20">
<head><list><item>LITTLE HEROINES WHO WORK FOR THREE MEALS, A ROOF AT NIGHT, AND THEIR CAR-FARE.</item>
<item>THEY DO NOT HAVE TIME EITHER TO READ DAILY PAPERS OR ATTEND DIVINE WORSHIP.</item></list></head>
In all this wide, weary, work-a-day world there is not a
better, brighter, nobler girl than the one who stitches, lines,
binds and vamps your slippers and shoes.
She is a heroine if there ever was one outside of a civil or
religious war. She knows nothing of self-love, nothing of fear,
<pb n="120"/>
and nothing of her own just rights. Her life is made up of
years of toil, months of privation, and weeks of struggling and
striving to keep up with the rushing throng, ravenous for her
bread and envious of her miserable position. She works from
dawn almost to dusk, carrying every dollar of her earnings to
some wretched home in which abide parents, brothers, and
sisters - often, too, relatives having absolutely no claim on her,
none of whom love her, and none of whom show by word, act,
or deed that her generosity, goodness, and real nobility of soul
is appreciated.
She goes without shoes the best part of the year, albeit in the
employ of a shoe manufacturer; she goes without pretty
dresses that younger sisters may be clad, and the money that
should go to the purchase of the hundred little niceties that
add so much to the beauty and charm and daintiness of budding
womanhood is withheld for the purchase of family flour or
text-books for the younger children who are at school. What
does she get?
Three meals a day, a roof at night, and car-fare.
Perhaps you think she doesn't know any better, hence the
bliss of ignorance.
Well, now, don't be too sure about that.
I had just been to P., D. &amp; P. shoe factory, on the top floor
of the N. R. J. building, looking for work. The girls were
crowded together like sheep in a stock-yard pen. All were at
machines. Some stitched shoe-linings; others lined the
vamps and uppers; others "tapped;" a few worked button-
holes, and all the experienced hands turned the shoe. This
consisted in hammering down the seams till the crash lining
could be turned in and made "to lay smooth." To accomplish this each girl had to wield, not a wooden mallet, but a
heavy iron hammer, from three to ten strokes being necessary
to flatten out the leather seam. This done there was the top
facing to put in, the holes to be made; and the buttons to be
<pb n="121"/>
marked, and the same process repeated again and again until
5:30 o'clock. The wages vary.
In order to get work I was told to begin at table-work. That
means sewing on buttons - two stitches for each button, finishing button-holes, and pasting sock-lining in the sole of
the shoe.
How much? Two dollars a week.
At the end of a year I would get a raise of $1. At the end
of four years I would be given a machine and a yearly raise
till I reached $8, the maximum wages for female help. But
Messrs. P., D. &amp; P. didn't need any help, and I left the big,
barn-like shop with its naked timber roof and brick walls,
glad to leave the leathery atmosphere and the hollow-eyed,
stoop-shouldered, miserably-clad men, youths and girls. Like
their neighbors across the court, the firm disregards the necessity for modern conveniences. There are a few closets and a
sink, and there all obligation ceases. Nothing is thought of
the four flights of steps to climb, of the deafening machinery
overhead, of the impure air and the dirty floors and stairs.
As I was leaving the building I met two girls on the landing
who asked, "What luck?" I told them there was no show for
inexperienced girls.
"Oh, we're broke in long ago. Worked for the U. S. company four years. It's a good enough place, but I got a lame
wrist turning shoes. The hammering is too hard. I'll take a
machine but I won't turn any more.
"Oh, I make $6 a week. Began at table work for $2.25.
They raised me to $3 in six months; after that I got $3.50,
then $4, then $4.50, then $5, and last January they gave
me $6.
"We have six children and I give all my money to my
mother. My father is a builder. He doesn't have much work
in the year, and winter times when he's laid off I don't have a
cent to myself. Only car-fare, that's all. Sometimes I don't
<pb n="122"/>
have any new dress the whole year. My sister is younger than
me. She works at neckties and makes $9. We two keep the
family.
"Fun, any fun I have is walking once in awhile. We don't
go out nights. Mother won't let us. She makes us go to bed
so we can get up early. We're always up at 6.
"I'd a good deal rather be a boy, because boys have a better
time. They can keep their money if they want to, but girls
have to give up all they make.
"No, I don't read the papers and I don't go to church either.
Haven't anything to wear. Most of the time I stay home and
sew. My mother goes to church."
At the factory of the U. S. company, West Lake street, I
took a machine and tried to stitch shoe linings by steam power.
I didn't get on well. The girls were very good to me. One
put my machine in order and the way she handled it amazed
me. She could not have been a day over 16, but she pulled off
the belt, took out the shuttle, threw the whole top over on its
side, and examined into the very bowels of the little engine,
using first a screw-driver, then the tention gage, and after
tightening and loosening alternately, she oiled the whole thing,
cleaned it and set it up again. For more than thirty minutes
she worked on a piece of morocco before getting the right tention, bravely persisting, however, till all was right, when she
gave me a lesson and went back to her own work. The steam
was too much for me. I couldn't manage it. It kept running
off the seam, and I pressed my knee against the starting wheel
to make it go slow until the buckle on my garter got red hot.
Kate's sister sat across the aisle making button-holes, and seeing my helplessness, came over and gave me another lesson.
"Take it slow," she said, "like this," flying down the heel
seam like a flash of lightning. "Don't worry, you'll learn.
I learned myself. You must press the wheel real hard with
your leg and then it will go slow."
<pb n="123"/>
I thanked her, and for an hour pressed the wheels on the
outer side of my right fore-leg which tore the cloth, raveling the
edge, and getting very much disgusted with my clumsiness.
Just as I was beginning to admire the grateful taciturnity and
generous forbearance of Foreman S. he told me I had "better
get out," but I begged for tolerence, and sewed away on a pair
of rags for another hour. A second time I was told to quit,
and again I begged for mercy, but when the wheel in the region of my knee began to burn, I threw down the few pairs of
lining I had succeeded in stitching and retired.
The shop where I had my struggle with the steam-power
was cut off from the rest of a factory by a partition. Along
the windows looking south were the machines, making two rows
or aisles, and set so closely together that they almost touched.
At each was a girl whose powers of endurance were seemingly
no different from the machine operated. Some young girls sat
at a cross table finishing buttonholes, for which they were paid
$3 and $4 a week. Men stood at side tables cutting out shoe
and slipper uppers, and behind the machines were young boys
of 12, 13 and 14 years, cutting linings. Younger boys were
employed in an adjoining department pasting sole-lining in
the newly-made shoes, and scores of men were engaged soling,
heeling, shaping, and polishing. The walls and ceilings were
paneled with soot; oil dripped from the rumbling machinery
overhead, and the floors were as black as ink. Although I saw
no evidence of rigid discipline, every man, boy, and girl labored with more than conscientious zeal. The labor was servile. Convicts could not have been more industrious with the
prison lash curling about them. Work began at 7 o'clock,
and while I was wrestling with the steam I saw a number of
girls stop work and eat part of their lunch.
Notwithstanding the patient fidelity and untiring industry of
these people, their neglect is a disgrace to the manufacturers
of Chicago. The closet in which I hung my hat was so dark
<pb n="124"/>
that I had to find a nail with my hands. Thinking my eyes
had been tardy in adjusting themselves to a low light, I remained in the hole long enough to know that nothing but feline optics would suffice to scan it. At the entrance was a triangular piece of looking-glass that some good soul had bolstered up between nail heads as a tribute to beauty. Neither
the stairs nor hall-ways gave evidence of recent sweeping, and
I would question the judgment of anyone venturing to assert
that they had been stubbed this year. The closets were in a
shocking condition - unfinished, unswept, and abominating to
the senses. Not only the outer door, but the three inner doors
were unhinged and lay in the filthy inclosure obstructing the
unfortunate girls who enter the place. I saw with my own
eyes, that the girls visited this model toilet-room, in groups of
not less than two, one acting as guardian for the others. At
the very entrance of this inclosure is the sink, a small iron
affair of the cheapest character, supplied with a single faucet.
Towels? No, nor soap, either! But who wants them?
You can't wash in the dark, and although there is a window
on the landing, the dust and dirt that cover it is as good a
shade as a curtain of brown Holland would be.
One of the girls told me she had been in the shop three
years and was getting four dollars a week. "Lots of the girls
earn five and less, but some I know get seven and eight.
They are old hands and work on fine shoes."
I asked a girl what she got when she was late.
"Get? We get jawed. But we ain't late; were all here .
at seven o'clock."
There was but a thirty-minute rest at noon as the factory
closes at 5:30. Work is good the year round.
At S. &amp; A's., on the floor below, where I inquired for work,
I received this edifying piece of information from the foreman:
"No, I guess I can't take you. If you were an experienced
operator I could give you a job, but it won't pay me to teach
<pb n="125"/>
you I can get little girls of twelve for $2.50, and all I want
for $3 a week to finish. When table work is dull I put them
at the machine and show them how to work it. The novelty
attracts them and I find they spend their noon and every spare
minute running up seams. In that way they soon pick up the
work, and when I am satisfied that they can run a machine, I
give them one, raise their salary fifty cents or one dollar, and
get raw girls again to do the table work."
Both firms might be reminded that there is some law relative
to the hiring of child labor and the necessity for fire-escapes.
I found the physical condition of the girls much better than
among the cloak-makers, tailoresses, and seamstresses, but in
point of poverty all seem akin. The girls wore clothes that
were ragged and dirty, many giving the very young girls the
appearance of little sweeps. Worthless shoes were worn as
much from necessity as from a sense of comfort, and nothing
in the habits or habiliments of these little money-makers
betrayed even the ordinary comforts of life.
</div>