<div type="section" n="17">
<pb n="106"/>
<head><list><item>NO REST FOR THE WEARY AND WRETCHED CHILDREN THIS SIDE OF THE GRAVE.</item>
<item>A DAY AMONG THE BUTCHER-SHOPS AND CANNED-MEAT FACTORIES OF THE STOCK YARDS.</item></list></head>
The birthright of an American girl may be a glorious attribute on the deck of a transatlantic steamship or the floor of a
London ball-room, but it is not worth the flop of a brass farthing in the cloak factories of Chicago.
It was high noon by the Jesuit college clock When I got to
the rear of --West Twelfth street, where David K. has his shop.
Nobody in but an old man. His face is seamed with wrinkles.
He has a big nose the color and texture of a mushroom; his
head and half his face is covered with hair of chinchilla shades;
his back is humped at the shoulders and his clothes are filthy
and worn. I ask for work and am told that no hands are
needed. He has a pocket that hangs across his waist and into
which he puts rags, pieces of thread, hooks and eyes, pins,
buttons, and the empty spools that lie on the floor about the
vacant machine chairs. I watch the silent old man as he
drags his loose slippers across the floor, and behold I have the
key to wealth! But it doesn't profit me worth a copper. So
I survey the premises.
One room, windows on three sides, and all shut. From the
north windows I get a view of a two-story hen-house. Filth
inside and out. The outlook from the east side is a picture of
poverty, squalor and filth. The buildings have no paint. In
some are human beings, in others dumb brutes. Half-washed
<pb n="107"/>
clothes dangle from window-sills and clothes-lines in tatters
and rags. In the yards are heaps of manure and the alleys
are foul-smelling and filthy. Along the street move flannel-
shirted, horny-handed, sooty-faced men, to smoke, to rest, to
quarrel, and to dinner. Passing and repassing all day long
and every day—Sunday and Saturday—are young women and
old women, youths, maidens, and children, with as many
cloaks or coats or pants as they can carry. The garbage boxes
are reeking with filth. Some one had thrown ashes or sweepings in the box, and neither the swill man nor the ash man will
remove the contents. Mayor Roche and Dr. De Wolf, equally
ignorant of the manner in which their subordinates discharge
their duty, permit this sort of thing to go on till the very
neighborhood is poluted and the air poisoned by these reeking
masses of corruption.
"Oh, it's nothing," I am told, and I see for myself and
count from Karasick's window and door eleven of these garbage piles that swarm with maggots and flies. The sun beating down on the cheap pine box has made the wood shrink,
and from constant kicking and shaking amd probing of the
miserable rag-pickers who inhabit this locality the frame-work
has been loosened and the wood carried off for fuel, leaving on
almost every block one or more naked heaps of decaying
matter.
Out of the south windows I look into the kitchen of some
dozen wretched families. The children are numerous and almost naked. They are unshod and unclean, so very unclean
that it is barely possible to tell their complexion. The mother
breaks a loaf in pieces in one house and throws it to the little
dirty faces on the doorstep. In another home the children eat
from a frying pan and next door all drink from the spout of the
teapot. Down in the yard is a pile of filth in which the children play and are followed by a lot of chickens. The stable
below stairs is locked, but stronger than bolt or hinge is the
<pb n="108"/>
smell from within, and viler still is the stench from the closets
in and about the yard.
At 12:45 o'clock the hands began to arrive from lunch, first
a young Pole, then a Russian, then a German Jew. They
wear woolen shirts and do the machine work—do it beautifully,
too, and their machines go like the wind. The patriarch in
skull cap and slippers goes round the shop looking at one and
the other, watching each operator to see that no extra waste of
thread is left at the end of the seams. Two more men and
then a girl. She does binding, nothing else, and gets $4 a
week. At 1 o'clock six young girls are sitting at a table in
the northwest corner of the shop. They have been running.
They are hot, full of fun, and one throws the window up.
Like a volley from the enemy roll in the closet and stable
smells and I move away to escape it. The boss is three
minutes late. He is a slight, meek man of 35, with a shirt
the color of brown soap, dark trousers and a cheap coat. A
light beard covers his mouth and chin, and the expression in
his eye has that soft, quiet, gentle quality sometimes seen in
cattle and sheep. I tell him I want work.
"Machine?"
"No."
"Can you finish cloaks?"
"Yes."
"Where have you worked? "
"A dozen places. S's, E's, B's, Os, N's, S's, etc."
"Here finish this. I will see what you can do."
"How much?"
"Eight cents, and I pray, Father Abraham, forgive this thy
son's oppression."
I am given a chair at the table with the girls. Propped up
on slender sticks is a stout cord, on which is a lot of spoolthread—white and black, fine, coarse and medium. Some
more of the philosophy of Mr. K's old father-in-law. The
<pb n="109"/>
thread is not wasted and the girls are not liable to carry it off.
I am given a big cotton and wool—principally cotton—ulster
to finish. I work like a lash-driven convict on the facings and
collar and cuffs till 4 o'clock, and am almost overcome by the
air that floats up from the yard below. It is done and I take
it to the boss, who examines it for fully five minutes.
"Too fine. Custom work. Don't need so good on such
work. You stay?"
"How much a week?"
"Five dollars. You Christian?"
"Work Sunday?"
"Never!"
"Then I don't want you. Shop closed Saturday. Shop
open Sunday."
"How much if I work five days?"
"No, you must work six days, like all."
"Not Sunday. Pay me, please."
I get out. Out past the stable-door, past the children in the
manure pile, past the ragged, yellow clothes on the line, past
the back door, past swill boxes, and the poor, pale-faced women
carrying cloaks to and from neighboring shops, till I reach
Twelfth street, where Isaac B. hires me. His shop is over a
rag store and the smell is far-reaching. Mr. and Mrs. B. work
with the men and girls. There are two rooms, poor light,
bad ventilation, low ceilings, disgusting smells from the
kitchens, the snarling, fault-finding remarks of the man, the
petulance of his wife, the filthy condition of the place and the
revolting contiguity of so many people were something not to
be endured. I occupied my chair in the dark, crowded room
fifteen minutes and left. Like David K's this shop is open all
day Sunday.
In the rear of Taylor street I was offered work by a tailor.
He had two small rooms in which men and girls were working
<pb n="110"/>
like slaves on custom coats. There was a fire in the stove on
which men heated their irons, and two boxes of garbage just
outside on the pavement filled the room with their odors.
Leaving the field of cloth and cloaks I applied to E. A. M.,
the confectioner, on West Jackson street. The forewoman is a
thin, bloodless young woman, with wild eyes and unmistakable
evidences of overwork.
"No, I can't give you a place. You are too big. I want
little girls. All these hands have been sent to us by peddlers
because they are so very poor. You couldn't live on the salaries
we pay. These children get $3 and the old hands up-stairs $4."
The midget laborers are filling pans with chocolate and maple caramels. Young boys cut the sheet of soft, brown saccharine stuff into squares which a dozen little girls transferred to
the tins. At deep troughs filled with pop-com and gum-drops
were other children filling small paper bags. Up-stairs the
girls worked on stick goods. Their quarters, while rude and
bare and hot from the steaming syrup-pots, were light and
airy.
At Brougham's packing-house on Jackson street, I applied
for work in the canning-room. The foreman was kind. He
took me out in the dark, little packing-room, in which the
light and breeze were fenced off by walls of tin cans. The
girls were pale and thin and very young. But, oh, how they
did paint! Each stood near a wall of cans that had just been
filled with meat—pressed corned beef, tongue or ham—still
warm. At hand was a pot of Japan paint with which the girls
brushed the ends and rims of each can. I told the foreman I
knew I could do the work. He tried me. I daubed on the
paint, held the brush wrong, and got more color on my hands
than on the can. The girls laughed at my awkwardness; so
did the foreman. I was chagrined with my failure and asked
for some water to clean my hands. The man gave me a benzine bath and then showed me to a basin of dirty water on the
<pb n="111"/>
surface of which a hundred or more dead flies were afloat.
The quarters in which these girls work are little more than
deadly—no sunlight, no free, fresh air, no place to sit, and the
blue paint smeared over their hands and arms and dripping
from the breast and belt of their dresses. Their wages are $5,
but each is expected to paint at least 1,500 cans per day.
Dirty little girls in rags and broken shoes, many of their wrists
not bigger than your two fingers, were in the rear of the shop
scouring cans, for which they are paid $3 a week. The hours
of toil are from 7 o'clock to 12 and from 1 o'clock to 5. The
girls were gay and inclined to be happy in their dungeon slavery, for, after all, they ate better paid than scores of help in
the employ of P., J. S., E. and Mrs. W.
At the suggestion of the foreman I took a Halsted streetcar
for the stock yards and with so much experience presented myself at the F. C. company. I did not see Mr. N. K., and what
is more, didn't want to see him. The girls, numbering a hundred or so, were at work up on the second floor in one of the
numerous buildings. They painted and labeled by the piece,
getting 5 cents a hundred. Plenty of girls handled 2,500 cans
a day, giving them a salary of $7.50 a week. Experienced
hands earned $9 and beginners and dryers $4 per week. No
provision was made for the comfort of these girls. They swept
the greasy floor when necessary, packed the goods and were
jostled and pushed about by the bloody butchers and greasy
packers. All worked in cast-off clothing, many literally dripping with paint. A great many of the girls were Irish, but
the Swedes and Germans were numerous. I cannot understand
how they endure the work which, while purely mechanical,
requires them to be on their feet from 7 to 5:30 every day, and
from all I could learn they do not stand it. Few with whom
I talked had been in the yards five years; all wanted to get
married, not to have money and nice clothes and theater tickets,
but to get rested.
<pb n="112"/>
At P. D. A's packing-house the girls were paid 3 cents to
5 cents per hundred for labeling and japaning cans, wages
varying $6 to $9. Beginners received 75 cents a day for two
weeks, or until they could handle 1,500 cans per day, when
they received $6, and were raised to the minimum figure as
their skill increased. As at F's, they were young girls with
haggard faces, emaciated figures, and work-weary bodies. At
noon they sat in the windows to eat their lunch, and fhe vessel
on the zinc from which they slacked their thirst was nothing
more elaborate than a tin-can cut down. It is certainly very
good of Mr. A. to build Sunday-schools, educate struggling
artists, buy pictures, and patronize music, but these young
women are human, if their senses are dulled to the sickening
smells of the slaughtering establishment, and a clean sitting-
room with neat walls and chairs in which to rest at noon and
clean towels for the 6 o'clock toilet, would not be wasted
charity.
These girls are called "tough." Perhaps they are. Perhaps their language is not chaste nor their manners pleasing,
but Mr. A. and Mr. F. know as well as need be known that
their hearts are pure and their lives blameless. Considering
their origin, their nature, their surroundings, and their associates they are too good to be put on the level they are.
</div>