<div type="section" n="9">
WHILE AMONG CHICAGO'S WEAK SERFS "THE TIMES'" LADY REPORTER FINDS MR. GOSS' "GOOD JEW."
IN A SMALL, DIRTY ROOM FILLED WITH A CROWD OF WOMEN LIFE SEEMS LIKE A HIDEOUS DREAM.
Two weeks ago Rev. Mr. Goss preached a sermon relative to
the morals and progress of the working woman. Among other
things he referred to "a good Jew" who, having the comfort
of the hundred odd girls in his cloak factory at heart, "pro-
vided every day for 1 cent a substantial lunch." I sent the
reverend gentleman a note, inclosing a stamp for the address
<pb n="52"/>
of the "good Jew," and in reply came the name of H. R---,
Monroe street. On went poverty's respectable rags, and off I
posted for shop-work and a penny spread.
The elevator carried me to the top of the building, where
every week thousands of jackets, sacques, circulars, dolmans,
and cloaks are turned out to supply the country trade of the
northwest. Here in a crowded room, with low ceiling and
dingy walls, poorly ventilated and insufficiently lighted, sit
between eighty and 150 young girls, surrounded from Monday
morning until Saturday noon by the ceaseless clatter of the
sewing-machines in an atmosphere so thick that it can be cut
with a knife. The machines are run by steam, and notwithstanding the great buckram fans overhead that revolve with a
crackling noise, the ceiling is so low and the air so hot as to
be positively stifling to the uninitiated. There is the smell of
dye from brown, blue and black cloaks coupled with the still 
more offensive odor from "English plaids;" along the pressing-
table are the gas-stoves where irons are heated and where the
girls sponge and press collars and seams, each operation attended by a little cloud of steam and stuffy, scorching smell
that blows about and around the whizzing fans; clouds of lint
from the textures in hand covers everything, and is constantly being inhaled by the sewers. Then, too, there is the
smell of rancid machine oil; the overpowering exhalations from
so many perspiring and unkempt persons and an occasional
whiff from the six or seven toilet closets, all powerful factors of
one mighty smell that must be smelled to be appreciated. The
"good Jew" had all the windows open, but the place was so
foul I almost fainted.
I have a seat in the middle of the room, and a thirty-five
cent Norfolk to make. It is so dark that I can hardly see my
stitches as I bind the sleeve hole with black muslin. The fore-
woman can't see either till she takes the work over to a window
to examine it, and returns with a gratifying "Guess that'11 do."
<pb n="53"/>
We are so crowded along the line of tables that the girls are
told to take short threads, and I duck my head every time the
pale-faced, hollow-eyed girl at my left pulls her needle out, to
escape being hit. She has only been able to make three fifty-
cent long cloaks in five days and says:
"You won't mind my taking long threads, will you, if I
don't hit you?"
I tell her to pull away and offer to fell the bottom hem of
her cloak, to which she agrees. She has on a cheap jersey
waist, a calico skirt, and the little bit of underwear that shows
at her neck where she has opened her collar is as black almost
as her jersey. Her shoes are broken and one of the uppers is
mended with black thread. She lives with her folks and has
"a lot of little brothers and sisters, but the 'Q' strikes have
put them all out" so she hasn't bought anything for herself
this year except a hat at the Fair.
"Do you go to church?" I ask.
"What'd I go to church for?"
"For the music and the sermon."
"I want a seat, though, and I'd rather ride down to the
shop and back than pay ten cents to get in a pew.
A poor little bony and grimy, and wild-eyed as the "marchioness," goes down on her knees and turns out the dust in the
cracks of the floor with the eye of her needle.
"I'm huntin' for pins," she says, "to fix on the braid."
"Doesn't Zimmerman provide you with pins?"
"Indeed he doesn't; nor with nothin' else but fannin' and
what's the good of fans in an oven?"
The child turns up the pins, some of them bent, and puts
them first in her mouth to straighten them and then in the
bosom of her dress, humming to herself "Rock of Ages, Cleft
for Me." At the expiration of the hunt a new difficulty befalls
her. The needle's eye is stuffed, as she says, and in the effort
<pb n="54"/>
to remove the filling off goes the head, optic and all. Nobody
has another to lend and I give her mine. 
She says she is thirteen and the daughter of a Twelfth street
teamster. Her mother is living, and she and her brother
"help the family along."
"Yes I went to school and learned numbers and gogerfy,
but I can't sew very well. The forelady says that's why I
don't make more. I got $2.75 one week, but I don't know
how much I'll earn this week. I used to be in the Fair and
they gave me two dollars runnin' checks. I didn't like it
there because I never got home till eight at night and the boys
was guyin' us all the time."
At noon-time the girls crowded into the wash-room and
those unable to reach the already wringing-wet towel that
hung near the sink dried on their dresses. I saw a tall young
German woman wash her arms and neck and shake off the
water as well as she could with the palms of her hands before
putting on her dress waist again. Another, a girl of fourteen,
who wore a plaid skirt and an old velvet jacket, dried her
hands on her underclothing. The lunch the "good Jew"
served consisted of a cup of black coffee that was neither
nutritious nor fragrant, and minus cream and sugar, for which
the girls paid two cents a cup. Then there were cuts of pie at
five cents each, which delicacy, architecturally speaking, had
two stories, substantially built, with a water-proof inner lining
of fruit mucilage. The top crust had bubbled up in the baking till it was as warty as tripe, and the tenacity of the under
dough would have sufficed for hinging a cellar door. This is
certainly not the lunch Rev. Mr. G. described, but it is the
only one the girls in the Z. factory know anything about.
However profitable the menu may have been to the firm it
was anguish to many of the hungry' toilers unable to procure it.
We girls who had no money to invest in appetizing (?)<!-- RJP:10/21/15: this is in text DON'T REMOVE --> viands
sat by begging with our eyes and following with melting
<pb n="55"/>
mouths every morsel on its way down the throats of our neighbors. One of us, a mite of a girl, wan-faced and hectic, who
had been watching the mastication of a well-fed machine hand,
waited till the leathery tangle of peach-paste had almost, disappeared and then asked the consumer to "give her the crust."
When the well-fed party said "naw," the child called her a
"dirty beggar," and laid her little head on her arm for a nap.
I went out to buy a needle, and some day when "it rains and
the wind is never weary" I shall send in a bill for the seven
and one-half cents H. Z. owes me on a cotton-back Norfolk.
Only a half-hour was allowed for the noon rest, during which
the girls washed and combed, trimmed their finger-nails with
scissors, talked, or went to sleep.
All hands were on deck at 7:30 in the morning, in which
manner and the 5:30 hour of closing, the Saturday half-hour
was made good to the firm. Many of the girls told me they
made ten cloaks a week which averaged fifty cents apiece.
Work was good, the season covering ten months of the year.
A number of men at work on the long cloaks had chairs at the
side of the girls, and while well enough personally I did not
relish them, for they were saturated with tobacco fumes and
emitted a sour, sweaty, sickening ordor.
</div>