<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:id="WSGC04">Section 4</title>
                <!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each book chapter -->
                <!-- RJP: each section will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and section number (add  a zero in front of early sections so we have consistent format with sections that will be double digits). For example: the first section in the Barkley text will be xml:id="WSGC01" -->
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire
                        server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh
                        Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref>
                    server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                    <!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp -->
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of
                        Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-06"
                        >2015-11-06</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->.
                    This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s
                    in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based
                    Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at
                        Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project
                    begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                        <author>NELSON, Nell, pseud.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Barkley Pub. Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                        <publisher>Research Publications No. 3519 Inc.</publisher>
                        <date when="1976">1976</date>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
                        <availability>
                            <p>139 p. 19 cm. Microfilm. 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at
                    the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text.
                    Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to
                    make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the
                    information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the
                    original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the
                    document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination
                    to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>A CLOAK CONCERN WHERE NOTHING BUT FEAR OF THE LAW SEEMS TO PREVENT THE
                            USE OF THE LASH.</item>
                        <item>EIGHTY CENTS A WEEK FOR LABORING FROM 7:30 IN THE MORNING UNTIL 5:30
                            IN THE EVENING.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="sectionBody">
                    <pb n="21"/>
                    <p>I did not realize the ignominious position of respectable pov-erty till I
                        went to E's cloak factory, where labor is bondage, the laboror a slave, and
                        flesh and blood cheaper than needles and thread. Corporations are said to be
                        without heart, but this concern is a commercial inquisition. It puts its
                        help on the plane of slavery, and nothing but civil law prevents the use of
                        the lash.</p>
                    <p>The factory is on the third floor of the large brick building at the east end
                        of Madison street bridge on the south side of the street.</p>
                    <p>Elevator? Not much.</p>
                    <p>An elevator is a luxury, and luxuries have no place at E's. You will be short
                        of breath when you reach the top of the fourth flight, but in recovering you
                        have time to take in the surroundings - a great barn of a place with a
                        single charm of good light. There is plenty of vacant room, but the women
                        are huddled together, elbows touching along the line of machines. Beneath
                        the west windows flows the river; at the south end of the room, not ten feet
                        from the crowded table, is a tier of closets, and on hot days the combined
                        odor of the two is shocking. Nobody in his employ dare complain about
                        smells, cold, heat, work, wages or rules. But whoever heard of martyrs
                        complaining?</p>
                    <pb n="22"/>
                    <p>My experience began at 7:50 A.M. and lasted just three hours. When I climbed
                        the dusty stairs I took a ten-minute rest at the top. Everybody was at work
                        but a hungry-looking man about 27 years old, with skin the color of a Russia
                        turnip and thin, peaked features. He was dressed in a pair of heel-less
                        slippers, a white shirt, and a pair of shop pants that a clothing store pays
                        18 cents for making. Neither collar, vest, coat nor suspenders burdened his
                        emaciated form. He moved among the workers with a cat-like tread, his
                        shoulders drooping and his knees opening and shutting with a sort of
                        accordion movement at every step. He passed me several times as I stood at
                        the desk and eyed me so unpleasantly that I turned my back to him.</p>
                    <p>After waiting at the desk for three-quarters of an hour, I asked the clerk, a
                        sweet little girl of 16 years, with pretty red cheeks and dark eyelashes and
                        hair, for work, and was told to wait till the-forelady came round. A dozen
                        girls were waiting too, some with cloaks, others with check-books and
                        tickets, and a few with hand-made fringe. The fringe-girl I spoke to. She
                        told me she received 5 cents a yard for making an imitation of seal-ball
                        fringe, such as winter cloaks are trimmed with. She had a piece three yards
                        and a quarter long that had taken her all the previous day to make. Here was
                        a child of 15 working nine and a half hours a day for a competence of 16 1/4
                        cents. Will the Prairie avenue woman, who, at the suggestion of Mrs. Ormison
                        Chant, is trying to find one hundred girls who are earning less than 28
                        cents a day please enter "Maggie W--- on the list, and will the women of the
                        P--- agency who want a new field of inquiry, call and see this slim,
                        snake-gaited, jaundice-faced creature who has charge of this human mill.</p>
                    <p>Maggie's fringe being measured and her book checked, she was given another
                        box of material and went off to weave it into tassel-trimming. The girl who
                        took her place would not be interviewed. She didn't know how much stitchers
                        earned <pb n="23"/> and wouldn't tell how much a week she could make." She
                        was, possibly, 25 years old, with a deathly pale face, and looked as if she
                        hadn't eaten any breakfast. Her successor was less reticent. "I'm here since
                        May, but I don't like it; the boss is a horrid thing. Him and the forelady
                        watches us all the time, and they don't give us hardly any work. I can only
                        make one cloak a day; some pays 30 cents, some 40 cents, and some 50.
                        Yesterday I had only 60 cents coming to me for two days. Are you long here?
                        Oh, you won't stay. They search your bag and your pocket when you go home
                        nights to see if you have any thread or pieces about you."</p>
                    <p>Before I had a chance to talk w'ith another unfortunate the little
                        rosy-cheeked clerk told me "it's against the rules for new hands to stand
                        here. You must go over by the stairs and wait till the forelady comes." I
                        smiled at the pretty child and she rewarded me by bringing a chair to me a
                        few minutes later. All means of
                        cummunication<!-- RJP:10/20/15:retained spelling --> being cut off I amused
                        myself making sketches of the shirted, slippered, sleuth-like creature as he
                        passed.</p>
                    <p>This pastime was interrupted by the appearance of a fat woman. She had on a
                        black sateen suit that fitted her puffy figure like the raiment of a well
                        boiled suet pudding. She carried herself like a drum major on a dress parade
                        and by way of ornaments wore a gold watch with a double coil of gold chain
                        at her belt, gold earrings, a gold breast pin, gold cuff- buttons and two
                        gold rings. Bigger than bust or bustle was the woman's head I discovered
                        when I asked:</p>
                    <p>"Are you the forewoman?"</p>
                    <p>"Forelady, yes. What do you want?"</p>
                    <p>"Work."</p>
                    <p>"What can you do ?"</p>
                    <p>"Sew."</p>
                    <p>"Where have you been working?"</p>
                    <p>"N. R. Co."</p>
                    <pb n="24"/>
                    <p>"Want to stitch?"</p>
                    <p>"No, I would rather finish."</p>
                    <p>"Give your name to the clerk."</p>
                    <p>I complied and was entered on his book as the resident of a vacant lot on
                        Monroe street. The forewoman selected a bundle as big as a Kamschatka baby
                        from a mountain of bundles and said:</p>
                    <p>"Here, go over there and wait till I come."</p>
                    <p>"How much do you pay for this class of work?"</p>
                    <p>"I don't know. It seems to me you're mighty particular."</p>
                    <p>"If you don't know who does?" I asked.</p>
                    <p>"You make me dizzy," she said, dropping the bundle and giving me a look of
                        intense disgust. She took a small book from her pocket containing the
                        price-list and asked me what number.</p>
                    <p>"I don't know."</p>
                    <p>"Look."</p>
                    <p>"Where?"</p>
                    <p>"You'll come down a peg or two before long," and with a groan she bent over
                        the bundle at her feet, flushed apoplectically and said "360." Referring
                        again to her price-list: "Them's sixty-five cents," and left me.</p>
                    <p>I raised that sixty-five cent ulster, and with my arms folded about the
                        fuzzy, ill-smelling thing, moved "down there" as directed, and halted at the
                        edge of a huge rag box. Here I stood for twenty minutes, when the forewoman
                        came aft and bade me "this way." I pursued. There was a halt about the
                        middle of the shop and I seized it for a "scoop."</p>
                    <p>"How many girls have you here?"</p>
                    <p>"Never counted them."</p>
                    <p>"What can experienced cloak hands earn in a day?"</p>
                    <p>"Never asked them."</p>
                    <p>"How much of your salary is for politeness?"</p>
                    <p>"You can sit here," pointing to a cane chair with half the <pb n="25"/> seat
                        gone. "That girl with the black dress will do your stitching; the one at the
                        end of the second table will bind the seams, and Annie down there in brown
                        calico - she's fixing the machine now - will give you any help," and she was
                        off.</p>
                    <p>"I beg your pardon, did I understand you to say I would get sixty-five cents
                        for making this cloak?" following her.</p>
                    <p>"Now your're just a little bit too fresh. If you don't want the work, say
                        so."</p>
                    <p>"I do want the work but I want to know what it will pay first."</p>
                    <p>"This is a sixty-five cent cloak. Do you get that through your head? The
                        stitcher gets twenty cents, the binder gets fifteen cents, and you get
                        thirty cents for finishing if the work is right. If it isn't, you get
                        out."</p>
                    <p>I thanked her and was alone. Here I thought lay my fortune. Thirty cents for
                        making a long cloth cloak, after the seams were stitched. It had to be
                        trimed down the back gores around the collar, cuffs, and pockets with mohair
                        plush. The sleeves had to go in, eighteen buttons sewed on, eighteen holes
                        worked, and all the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty cents!
                        To save my life I couldn't have finished the garment in ten hours. I was
                        just reaching that conclusion when the forewoman appeared with a small book,
                        two checks, and a piece of tailor's chalk as big as a dime.</p>
                    <p>"Your number is 180; chalk it on all these pieces and if you lose any you
                        will be fined."</p>
                    <p>"How much?"</p>
                    <p>"How much? You cheeky thing! The cost of the cloth and the cutter's time.
                        That's how much. Give this check to the binder and that one to the
                        stitcher."</p>
                    <p>"Will you please tell me how this side gore goes?"</p>
                    <p>"Go to Annie. I ain't here to learn you how to sew."</p>
                    <p>"May I have a needle?"</p>
                    <p>"Furnish your own needles."</p>
                    <pb n="26"/>
                    <p>"May I have basting cotton?"</p>
                    <p>"There aint any. You have to wait till it gets here."</p>
                    <p>I gave a girl a penny for a needle and stole some thread from an absentee's
                        stock. Then I waited fifteen minutes while the finder got through and basted
                        up the seams for the stitcher. That much done I got to work on the plush.
                        The forewoman passed by and told me I "was not showing enough fur. Go over
                        to the sample and look at the work."</p>
                    <p>She sneered when I asked her where the samples were, but a neighbor
                        volunteered the information. There was no sample on the rack and I stepped
                        over to inform the forewoman, who curtly told me it was none of her
                        affair.</p>
                    <p>"Will you please tell me how wide to make this trimming?"</p>
                    <p>"Go to Annie."</p>
                    <p>Poor Annie was doctoring a machine and said "in a minute." On her way to me
                        three stitchers implored her to look at their miserable implements and I
                        waited patiently till I caught sight of the forewoman looking at her bangs
                        in a handglass. Apologizing for the intrusion I asked her if the sample had
                        come yet.</p>
                    <p>"No."</p>
                    <p>"I wish you would kindly show me how wide to make this trimming."</p>
                    <p>"Go to Annie, I told you."</p>
                    <p>"Annie is too busy. She's mending machines."</p>
                    <p>"Well, I won't be bothered with you."</p>
                    <p>"What's the reason you won't?"</p>
                    <p>"Cause I won't"</p>
                    <p>"Well you will. Tell me how wide you want this plush or I will see Mr
                        A---"</p>
                    <p>"See him. I don't care. There he is," pointing to a snaky, half-starved
                        creature whose shanks I had been sketching and on whom I had scornfully
                        turned my back. It was too much to ask of a free-born American woman to
                        recognize the superi- <pb n="27"/> ority of such a person. He came up to us
                        in an instant. The forewoman was livid with rage and she began to talk as
                        fast as her tongue could move. Some fifty or more girls heard the tirade
                        breathlessly. Before the half-dressed proprietor had a chance to get over
                        his astonishment I threw the front of the cloak at his face, the side body
                        at the forewoman, and walked off to my disabled chair with Mr. A. for a
                        bodyguard. He was the color of a sanitarium babe when we reached my work
                        table. He had the two pieces of cloak in his hand, and when he raised his
                        fist to strike me I worked up an Indian-club attitude and dared him.</p>
                    <p>He escorted me to the toilet-room, where I went for my hat and jacket, and
                        before slamming the door in his face by way of a hint as to the privacy of
                        the place I threw my needle and thread at him. Mr. A. saw me across the shop
                        and down the first flight of stairs. And there ended my first experience in
                        a cloak factory.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
