<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:id="WSGC13">Section 13</title><!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each book chapter --><!-- RJP: each section will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and section number (add  a zero in front of early sections so we have consistent format with sections that will be double digits). For example: the first section in the Barkley text will be xml:id="WSGC01" -->
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --> 
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-06">2015-11-06</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                        <author>NELSON, Nell, pseud.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Barkley Pub. Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                        <publisher>Research Publications No. 3519 Inc.</publisher>
                        <date when="1976">1976</date>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
                        <availability>
                            <p>139 p. 19 cm. Microfilm. 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>A BASEMENT THAT ON A HOT DAY IS SO STIFLING IT REMINDS ONE OF THE "BLACK HOLE OF CALCUTTA."</item>
                        <item>WORKING FROM 7:45 UNTIL 6:30 AND RECEIVING IN EXCHANGE FOR THE TERRIBLE DRUDGERY AND HARD LABOR A MISERLY $2 OR $3 A WEEK.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="sectionBody">
                    <pb n="83"/>
                    <p>For dismal surroundings, economy of comforts, and heartless
treatment, to the B. store belongs the palm.</p>
<p>I did not work in that establishment, although I tried very
hard to do so. I was in the store at 8 o'clock on Friday morning as arranged with Mr. H. who had partially promised to hire
me. "One of the girls in the hosiery department" he had
said "is sick, and if she doesn't come back Friday morning I
will try you."</p>
<p>I could not find the gentleman, although I hunted the main
floor and the floors above and below. My plan of fluctuation
was to take the elevator up one story and walk down, then ride
up two and walk down the third flight. In that way I took in
the entire store and a great part of the employes. I began at
the bottom and spent a full hour in the basement, where I saw
so much and suffered so much that the upper floors had no surprises for me. In the first place the atmosphere was almost
unendurable.</p>
<p>Hot! It must have been 100 degrees above!</p>
<p>Out in the open air not a breeze was stirring and the heat
was sizzling. Down where I was I could not see a single
opening to admit the air, fiery as it was, except the open door
<pb n="84"/>
at the extreme southeast corner of the floor, leading up a short
pair of steps to the sidewalk. About this doorway so many
goods were piled and draped and hung that the passage of air
was obstructed. There must have been forty, and there may
have been eighty, clerks, cash boys, and girls on this floor and
five times that number of customers surged in and out under
the glaring rays of gas-jets and electric burners. Babies
squirmed and cried under the suffocating heat; children
screamed and fretted; men and women fanned and wiped their
faces, but the little cash girls and the languid clerks endured
their prison uncomplaining. Add to the heat from gas-jets,
electric lights, and machinery, the exhalations from so many
people, the moldy smell from damaged goods, the dampness of
the freshly mopped floor, the fumes from a stray disinfectant,
and the mildew that lurked in dark corners, and you have some
idea of the quarters in which customers are invited to look for
bargains, and where helpless, honest, freeborn American men
and women, boys and girls are forced to work for clothes and
bread.</p>
<p>What about the soul? It's mockery to mention it to these
slaves in such a dungeon.</p>
<p>On a rude plank door painted black is the word "Ladies."
The irony of it! "Serfs" would be less impertinent and
"bond-women" or "drudges" better than either.</p>
<p>The door yields to my touch and I enter the toilet and cloak
room. The atmosphere is so intense and the effluvia so offensive that I am almost stifled. A window about eighteen inches
square has been cut in the side of the staircase leading from the
street, and here I stand, my face turned up to the clouds of
dust that float in from the feet and skirts of the passing customers. By and by I get accustomed to the foulness and turn
round to explore the place. The floor is black and wet from
recent mopping; the janitor has swept all the previous day's
rubbish in from the basement and it forms a big pile behind
<pb n="85"/>
the door. There is only one gas-jet in the room and I do not
see the wet sweepings until I have stepped in them. On either
side of the inclosure are the cloak-boxes, communication to
which is afforded by a window a foot square. A young and
very pretty colored woman is in one section and in the opposite window is a little boy possibly 13 years old. All the female
help pass their hats, wraps and lunches through these windows,
and they are put in a cubby-hole the number of which corresponds to the number of the clerk. The smell of mold forcibly
assails the senses, and mingled with the foul odor of the adjoining closets the effect on the lunches must be left to the
imagination. On the east side of the partition is the toilet
inclosure, built like the rest under the pavement. But for the
perforated coal-hole covers over head the place would be pitch
dark. It is damp, dirty and smelly, the stone sidewalk forming a ceiling, and gray flagstones the floor. The closets, four
or five in number, have not even the luxury of doors, and in a
space at one end is a dirty little iron sink into which runs a
stream of water. As only two girls can approach the narrow
trough for water at a time it is not hard for the reader to understand how great a luxury this single stream of clear, cool water
is to the slave-girls. At one time I counted twenty-eight girls
in this filthy little hole, which is unfit for cattle and in which
no man would water a faithful dog.</p>
<p>When I had accustomed myself to the deadly smell that pervaded the place it was 9:30 o'clock and the girls were beginning to come in to wash their hands and clean up, after arranging their stock. About the little mirror were seven girls, some
combing their hair, some dressing it, and all trying to get a
peep at their wan faces. The closets were crowded, and while
three young girls were washing at the sink five moved about
with bits of soap in their hands, their arms and faces covered
with lather. The soap may have been furnished by the house,
but of the absence of towels I am positive. Most of the girls
<pb n="86"/>
had their own comb, soap and towel, and where do you suppose they carried them?</p>
<p>In the bosom of their dresses.</p>
<p>I cautioned a girl who had opened the front of her waist
against putting the wet towel so near her breast, but she only
laughed and said "nothin'll hurt me."</p>
<p>"But it is wet and may cause a lung trouble."</p>
<p>"Indeed it won't. I used to put it there all last winter, and
it didn't hurt me. When it was awful cold I wore it home
and I never even had a cold." As she spoke she folded the
little towel, and laying it against her underwaist buttoned her
dress and went to the hole in the north cloak box for a glass of
lemonade. I told her I was very thirsty and asked for a drink.
"Oh, you have to pay. It's 3 cents a glass."</p>
<p>The colored girl and her little white slave had a bucket full
of the beverage—a very excellent article, by the way which
they retailed at the price stated. The ebony vender refused to
sell to me till I convinced her that I expected to commence in
the hosiery stock as soon as Mr. H. came down. The girl
with the wet damask in her bosom drained her glass to the
last drop, ate the slices of lemon rind and pulp, and with the
help of her finger transferred every grain of undissolved sugar
to her mouth. She lapped the mouth of the glass with her
tongue and when the boy took it from the ledge it was as dry
as could be. I could not get her to confide her salary, but she
said: "It ain't nothing like $5. For two years I only got
$3, but now I have more."</p>
<p>I found a girl named Bessie in the closet-room lying against
the wall, the very picture of death. Her face had no more
color in it than a china cup, her lips were blue, dark lines
increased the brilliancy of her blue eyes, and her hands were
cold and clammy. She told me she was "awful sick," but her
mother made her come because she didn't want her to lose
her place.</p>
<pb n="87"/>
<p>"The floor-walker 'ud leave me go home if I ast him, but I
havn't any car-fare and I don't want to walk. I lost my tea
money and all cornin' down in the cars this morning. I was
asleep." I offered to pay her car-fare.</p>
<p>"No; if I ride in the air I'll be better before I get to the
bridge."</p>
<p>I bought her a glass of lemonade and gave her "tea pennies"
for a week, after which we became quite confidential.</p>
<p>"I get $2 a week here, and give it to my mother to buy
meat. Sometimes I ride home, but them's the days that I
don't buy tea, cause it costs too much for both. The tea is 3
cents a cup and the car-fare, if you ride both ways, is 10 cents,
and that's 13 cents."</p>
<p>Seventy-eight cents subtracted from $2 would leave a
precious small sum for meat.</p>
<p>"The most I ever spend is 50 cents a week. That's how
much mother lets me keep out. Oh, there kind of good to us.
Last night when it rained Mr. H. gave nickles to the cash
girls that didn't have car-fare nor gossamers. But I guess
he'll keep it out of their wages pay-day. Some of the clerks
don't be good to us. They pull us everywhere and push us
when we don't go fast, and we never dast ride in the elevator.
The clerks can, but the cash-girls has to walk. They don't
fine us if we come late, though, and they do the clerks, some
15 cents and some 25 cents, and if any of us is sick we lose the
whole day out of our wages. The one I like most is Miss
Gannon; she is awful good; she puts three lumps in the tea,
and trusts the girls when they haven't any tea pennies."</p>
<p>A larger girl, possibly nineteen, showed me her odd shoes.</p>
<p>"I'm wearing this one with the tips to break it in. I have
to stand all day and my feet are so sore I can hardly bear a
new shoe. I got these new ones in June. Oh, they'll last till
Christmas I guess. My salary is five dollars a week, but I
don't save anything. My mother takes it all for the groceries.
<pb n="88"/>
I don't know what I'm going to do. Clerking is very hard
but I can't sew or I'd go and work in a necktie factory where
girls get ten dollars. Do house-work? No, I wouldn't like to
live out. I can't cook anyway. I could mind the children,
but nurse girls only get twelve dollars a month. Yes, I know
they have their board. No, not their washing. If you don't
help the kitchen girls whenever they tell you you have to do
your own washing, and I'd rather than have them bossing
me.</p>
<p>A mite of a cash girl who wore broken slippers, said she had
better shoes at home, but it was so hard running all day that
she couldn't wear them.</p>
<p>One of a cluster of girls from the grocery floor who were
earning $3 and $3.50 a week said: "People talk bad about
the B-store but it's as good as any of them. We needn't
be at the store till eight in the morning and they never fine us
if we're late. Lots of times when I have been sick the floor-
walker has told me to go out and walk round and if I didn't
feel better when I came back he let me go home. If it rains
Mr. N. lends us car-fare. He never said to pay him back but
I always did. We get 'p. ms.' too, and last week I made
eighty cents extra. At noon we can take forty minutes and
go where we like. We girls always go to Cooper &amp; Siegel's
and eat in the basement. At the Fair they give you a dinner
for twenty-five cents, and whenever we have a lot of 'p. ms.' 
we eat there."</p>
<p>"Why don't you eat up stairs in the lunch room?" I asked.</p>
<p>"Well, 'cause the benches havn't any backs, and it's nicer
to go out for a change."</p>
Like "the wards of Jarndyce,"<!-- RJP:10/25/15: reference to Bleak House, a novel by Charles Dickens --> caged up in this place of
abomination that the heavenly compassion of the proprietors
have provided for their hapless "ladies," I met hope, youth,
squalor, want, disease, despair, woe, cunning, innocence, rags,
beauty, bravery and industry variously personified in all
<pb n="89"/>
stages of miserable girlhood and womanhood. Much of the
talk I heard was coarse, indicative of ignorance and low
breeding, but I saw no evidence of depravity or viciousness.
One hears a great deal about the purchase of the shop-girl, but
the insinuations are as false as they are base. The skeptic has
only to look at the garb of these poor pale-faced, stoop-shouldered girls to admit their virtue. Vice is better dressed. I
spent an hour or more on the main floor watching the swarming customers joggle one another and haggle with the young
girls who waited on them. So many people in the densely-
stocked, over-crowded, ill-ventilated room polluted the atmosphere, making the strong weak and the weak sick. Every
available foot of space was utilized, some of the counters consisting of pine boxes on the side of which emaciated children
measured fringes, trimmings, ribbons, and cheap stuffs. One
of these troughs filled with Hamburg edging was placed
between the two elevators, and the little girls in charge were
knocked and pushed about by the hurrying crowd in a most
unseemly manner. I did not see any girl sitting down nor any
provision for a momentary rest. There was no mistaking the
poverty of the homes from which these hapless young creatures
came, for their garments were old and shabby and in many
cases unclean, unkept, and unsuitable. Worse than their
clothes was the unkept condition of the hair and person of
some young girls. As in the adjoining establishment, I saw
girls waiting on customers in their stocking feet. I saw the
floor-walker push and drag the young girls about and the
managers bully and drive both. One of these dignitaries, a
tall, argus-eyed blonde, with stooped shoulders and a drooping
head, was the right man in the right place. Everybody dispersed at his coming. His scowl was something terrorizing,
and had I been a subordinate and given the choice of the
lash and one of his glances of reproof, I should have taken the
former. There was another head, a tall, compactly-built
<pb n="90"/>
brunette, almost as formidable, who had a pair of eyes that
seemed to burn holes in everything and everybody contemplated.
The same sweltering crowd harassed the clerks on the second, third and fourth floors, and on the fifth the sight of so
many little drudges selling groceries or handling goods made
one feel ashamed of the civilization that fostered such a condition of woman. The younger girls in many instances wore
big check aprons to screen rather than save the worthless
little dresses beneath. It was harrowing to see these children,
boys of ten and twelve, and fragile girls of eleven, twelve,
thirteen, and fourteen, carrying boxes of soap, starch, and
candles, packages of buck-wheat, salt, and hominy, and cans
filled with oils, sirups, vinegars, and the like. The men in
charge had no hesitancy in commanding these transfers, calling
Maggie and Mary as often as John or Dick to make the
removal. I saw one little boy of slight build with a sweet but
very sad face, dragging a bag of coffee that would have been a
strain on the muscles of a strong man, and a little Swede girl
who said she was thirteen in March, had a box of canned
vegetables in her arms the weight of which made her black in
the face.
There is a ruin of youth and beauty which is more appalling
than age, and into such ruin has the youthful grace, vigorous
beauty and the charm of gladness and trust of these immature
lives fallen. There was no inclination to frolic, no merry bantering, and no semblance of childish glee among the little serfs.
A bridge of sighs spans the alley on the fifth floor, bringing
the two stores of Messrs. C. W. &amp; E. P. into communication.
Across this covered passage in the P. store proper, is a small
room in the rear of the floor which is used as a cafe by the
female help of the B. store. The furniture consists of two
narrow tables and three long benches extending the length of
the apartment. The benches had no rung or rest for the back,
<pb n="91"/>
and here the young women and check-girls sit at noon over
their lunch. On the wall is an expansive sheet of ecru paper
bearing this inscription:
"Female clerks and check-girls: You are requested not to
eat on the stairs or anywhere else. You will keep to the
right coming up, and to the left going down. You will not
talk on the way nor take hold of each other's hands, but walk
by yourselves. Anyone breaking this rule will be discharged.
Apropos of signs I forgot to say that in the basement where
the cloak-room is designated this notice appeared in bold relief:
The girl who took the silk umbrella
Saturday is known. If it is not returned at once she will have to take
the consequences.
Another less conspicuously placed sign read:
All female employes will be ready
for work at 7:45 A.M., under penalty.
Miss Gannon who has charge of the kitchen, is the good angel of the place. She is a plump, nice-looking person of splendid presence, with mild eyes, a firm face, sweet voice, and a
heart brimful of motherly tenderness. She makes tea and lemonade, which, with fresh milk is retailed at 3 cents a glass.
The tea has cream in it and the three lumps of sugar that go
with each cup are a gastronomical treat to the little ones who
drink the Japan first and save the sugar cubes for desert.
When I found Mr. H. he called his assistant, the lowering
brunette with the fiery eyes, who told me he had no opening—
told it, too, with a degree of positiveness that left no room for.
<pb n="92"/>
argument. With this summary dismissal after waiting nearly
two hours, I rode up to the top floor to see if I could not find
an opening in the grocery store. Mr. S. was hung up in a side
gallery midway between the ceiling and floor with a dozen or
more perspiring clerks. It did not take me long to discover
that I was being pursued, for I had not been engaged two minutes with the head of the mailing department, a most arbitrary,
red-haired, narrow-chested creature of 30 or so, before Messrs.
H. and N. sent him word to appear at once. Before leaving
Mr. S. said he would hire me if I had references that would
satisfy him as to my "honesty and respectability," but when
he returned from the one-minute interview with the managers
a great change had come over him.
"No, I can't hire you until I know something about you.
You are a stranger to me. I will want you to fill the country
orders and there will be plenty of chances for a dishonest girl
to steal gloves, handkerchiefs, jewelry, and other articles that
can be secreted in the pocket. I must have a letter from some
firm or corporation."
I offered to furnish a letter from a minister but it was declined as "no good." On the promise that I should be engaged
as soon as I produced the indorsement of a firm or corporation
I withdrew and returned in an hour with the following:
"Chicago, Aug. 3, 1888.—To whom it may concern: This is
to certify that the bearer is a young lady who has worked in our costume
department during the production of "The Crystal Slipper," and is thoroughly trustworthy and efficient and we can recommend her to any similar position.	Thomas W. Prior,
Business Manager and Treasurer Chicago Opera House."
After persuing it, Mr. S. called a little girl, and pinning my
letter to a note of his own, sent it to Mr. H. The dignitary
appeared, and in a very ambiguous style declined my services.
I learned afterward that A. E., the cloak manufacturer, had
<pb n="93"/>
"warded" the B. store, and while I was off getting my letter
that benevolent man had furnished a description.
It is a little singular that while the B. store refused to give
me a position as clerk, a most urgent invitation was sent to
The Times requesting that a reporter be sent to examine the
books and methods of the concern. By way of inducement a
voluminous account accompanied the invitation relative to salaries, rules, etc.</p><!-- each paragraph represented in the text will get its own <p> element -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>