<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title corresp="#CT002"><date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday Morning, July 31, 1888</date></title><sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor><sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Rebecca Parker</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName>Gregory Bondar</persName></respStmt><!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:<respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt>--></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-04">2015-11-04</date>. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor's degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head><title><name ref="#CT">Chicago Times</name> <date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday Morning, July 31, 1888</date></title></head><div type="headlines"><list><item>Further Details of the Factory Investigation Conducted by <hi rend="double"><name ref="#CT">The Times</name>'</hi> Lady Reporter.</item>
<item>A Cloak Concern Where Nothing but Fear of the Law Seems to Prevent the Use of Lash.</item>
<item>A Sickly Child of Fifteen Compelled to Work Nine and a Half Hours for Sixteen Cents.</item>
<item>The Unfortunate Insulted and Abused by Their Employer and Humiliated by the Forewoman.</item>
<item>Eighty Cents a Week for Laboring from 7:30 in the Morning Until 5:30 in the Evening.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p>I did not realize the ignominios position of respectable poverty till I went to <orgName ref="#Ellinger" type="exposedCompany">Ellinger's cloak factory</orgName>, <placeName ref="#Ellinger" type="address">282Madison street</placeName>, where labor is bondage, the laborer a slave, and flesh and blood cheaper than needles and thread. Corporations said to be without heart, but this concern is a commercial inquisition. It puts its help on the plane of slavery and nothing but civil law prevents the use of the lash.</p><p>The factory is on the third floor of the large brick building at the <placeName ref="#Ellinger" type="address">east end of Madison street bridge on the south side of the street</placeName>.</p><p>Elevator? Not much.</p><p>An elevator is a luxury and luxuries have no place at <orgName ref="#Ellinger" type="exposedCompany">Ellinger's</orgName>. You will be short of breath when you reach the top of the fourth flight, but in recovering you have time to take in the surroundings -- a great barn of a place, with the single charm of good light. There is plenty of vacant room, but the women are huddled together, elbows touching, along the line of machines. Beneath the west windows flows the river; at the south end of the room, not ten feet from the crowded table, is a tier of closets, and on hot days the combined odor of the two is shocking. <seg>Nobody in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">employ</w></phr> dare complain about smells, cold, heat, work, wages, or rules. But whoever heard of martyrs complaining?</seg></p><p>My experience began at 7:30 a.m. and lasted just three hours. When I climbed the dusty stairs I took a ten-minute rest at the top. <seg>Everybody was at work but a hungry-looking man about 27 years old, with skin the color of a Russia turnip and thin, peaked features. He was dressed in a pair of heelless slippers, a white shirt, and a pair of short pants that <orgName ref="#Willong" type="exposedCompany">Willonghby, Hill &amp; Co.</orgName> pay 18 cents for making. Neither collar, vest, coat, nor suspenders burdened <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> emaciated <w type="noun">form</w></phr>. He moved among the workers with a cat-like tread, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">shoulders</w></phr> drooping and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">knees</w></phr> opening and shutting with a sort of accordion movement at every step.</seg> <seg>He passed me several times as I stood at the desk and eyed me so unpleasantly that I turned <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">back</w></phr> to him.</seg></p><p>After waiting at the desk for three-quarters of an hour I asked the clerk, a sweet little girl of 16 years, with pretty red cheeks and dark eyelashes and hair, for work, and was told to wait till the forelady came round. A dozen girls were waiting, too, some with cloaks, others with check-books and tickets, and a few with hand-made fringe. The fringe-girl I spoke to. She told me she received 5 cents a yard for making an imitation of seal-ball fringe, such as winter cloaks are trimmed with. She had a piece three yards and a quarter long that had taken her all the previous day to make. Here was a child of 15 working nine and a half hours a day for a competence of 16cents. Will the <placeName type="locRef">Prairie avenue</placeName> woman who, at the suggestion of <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Ormison Chant</persName>, is trying to find one hundred girls who are earning less than 28 cents a days please enter <persName ref="#workingGirl">Maggie W&#8212;</persName> on the list, and will the women of the <orgName ref="#WPA">Protective agency</orgName>, who want a new field of inquiry, call and see this slim, snake-gaited, jaundice-faced creature who has charge of this human mill.</p><p><seg><phr><persName ref="#workingGirl">Maggie</persName><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">'s</w> <w type="noun">fringe</w></phr> being measured and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">book</w></phr> checked she was given another box of material and went off to weave it into tasel-trimming. The girl who took <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">place</w></phr> would not be interviewed.</seg> She <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">didn't know how much stitchers earned and wouldn't tell nobody how much a week she could make.</said> She was, possibly, 25 years old, with a deathly pale face, and looked as though she hadn't eaten any breakfast. Her successor was less reticent. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I'm here since May, but I don't like it; the boss is a horrid thing. Him and the forelady watches us all the time, and they don't give us hardly any work. I can only make one cloak a day: some pays 30 cents, some 40 cents, and some 50 cents. Yesterday I had only 60 cents coming to me for two days. Are you long here? Oh, you won't stay. <seg>They search <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">bag</w></phr> and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">pocket</w></phr> when you go home nights to see if you have any thread or pieces about you.</seg></said></p><p>Before I had a chance to talk with another unfortunate the little rosy-cheeked clerk told me <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">it's against the rules for new hands to stand here. You must go over by the stairs and wait till the forelady comes.</said> I smiled at the pretty child and she rewarded me by bringing a chair to me a few minutes later. All means of communication being cut off I amused myself making sketches of the shirted, slippered, sleuth-like creature as he passed.</p><p><seg>This pastime was interrupted by the appearance of a fat woman. She had on a black sateen suit that fitted <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> puffy <w type="noun">figure</w></phr> like the raiment of a well-boiled suet pudding. She carried herself like a drum-major on dress parade and by way of ornaments wore a gold watch with a double coil of gold chain at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">belt</w></phr>, gold earrings, a gold breast pin, gold cuff-buttons, and two gold rings. Bigger than bust or bustle was the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">woman's</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> I discovered when I asked</seg>:</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Are you the forewoman?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Forelady, yes. What do you want?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Work</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">What can you do?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Sew.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Where have you been working?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><orgName ref="#NRJC" type="exposedCompany">NeverRip company</orgName></said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Want to stitch?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">No, I would rather finish.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female"><seg>Give <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">name</w></phr> to the clerk.</seg></said></p><p><seg>I complied and was entered on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">his</w> <w type="noun">book</w></phr> as the resident of a vacant lot on <placeName type="locRef">Monroe street</placeName>.</seg> The forewoman selected a bundle as big as a Kainschatka baby from a mountain of bundles and said:</p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Here, go over there and wait till I come.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much do you pay for this class of work?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">I don't know. It seems to me you're mighty particular.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">If you don't know who does?</said> I asked.</p><p><seg><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">You make me dizzy,</said> she said, dropping the bundle and giving me a look of intense disgust. She took a small book from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">pocket</w></phr> containing the price-list and asked me what number.</seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">I don't know.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Look.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Where?</said></p><p><seg><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">You'll come down a peg or two before long,</said> and with a groan she bent over the bundle at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">feet</w></phr>, flushed apoplectically, and said <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">360.</said> Referring again to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">price-list</w></phr></seg>: <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Them's 65 cents,</said> and left me.</p><p><seg>I raised that 65-cent cluster and with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">arms</w></phr> folded about the fuzzy, ill-smelling thing, moved <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">down there</said>, as directed, and halted at the edge of a huge rag-box.</seg> Here I stood for twenty minutes, when the forewoman came aft and bade me <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">this way.</said> I pursued. There was a halt about the middle of the shop and I seized it for a <hi rend="double">scoop</hi>.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How many girls have you here?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Never counted them.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">What can experienced cloak hands earn a day?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Never asked them.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>How much of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">your</w> <w type="noun">salary</w></phr> is for politeness?</seg></said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">You can sit here,</said> pointing to a cane chair with half the seat gone. <said who="#foreperson" ana="female"><seg>That girl with the black dress will do <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">stitching</w></phr>, the one at the end of the second table will bind the seams, and <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> down there in the brown calico - she's fixing the machine now - will give you any help</seg>,</said> and she was off.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>I beg <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">your</w> <w type="noun">pardon</w></phr>, did I understand you to say I would get 65 cents for making this cloak?</seg></said> following her.</p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Now you're just a little too fresh. If you don't want the work, say so.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">I do want the work, but I want to know what it will pay first.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female"><seg>This is a 65-cent cloak. Do you get that through <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr>?</seg> The stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder gets 15 cents, and you get 30 cents for finishing if the work is right. If it isn't, you get out.</said></p><p>I thanked her and was alone. <seg>Here I thought lay <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">fortune</w></phr>. Thirty cents for making a long cloth cloak, after the seams were stitched.</seg> It had to be trimmed down the back gores, around the collar, cuffs, and pockets with mohair plush: the sleeves had to go in, eighteen buttons sewed on, eighteen holes worked, and all the seams and edges faced with black muslin. <seg>Thirty cents! To save <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">life</w></phr> I couldn't have finished the garment in ten hours.</seg> <seg>I was just reaching that conclusion when the forewoman appeared with a small book, two checks, and a piece of <phr><w type="poss">tailor's</w> <w type="noun">chalk</w></phr> as big as a dime.</seg></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Your number is 180: chalk it on all these pieces and if you lose any you will be fined.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">How much? You cheeky thing! <seg>The cost of the cloth and the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">cutter's</w> <w type="noun">time</w></phr>.</seg> That's how much. Give this check to the binder and that one to the stitcher.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Will you please tell me how this side gore goes?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Go to <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>. I ain't here to learn you how to sew.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">May I have a needle?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female"><seg>Furnish <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> own <w type="noun">needles</w></phr>.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">May I have basting cotton?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">There ain't any. You have to wait till it gets here.</said></p><p><seg>I gave a girl a penny for a needle and stole some thread from an <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">absentee's</w> <w type="noun">stock</w></phr>.</seg> Then I waited fifteen minutes while the binder got through and basted up the seams for the stitcher. That much done I got to work on the plush. The forewoman passed by and told me I was not <hi rend="double">showing</hi> enough fur. <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Go over to the sample and look at the work.</said></p><p>She sneered when I asked where the samples were, but a neighnor volunteered the information. <seg>There was no sample on the rack and I stepped over to inform the forewoman, who curtly told me it was none of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">affair</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Will you please tell me how wide to make this trimming?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Go to <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>.</said></p><p><seg>Poor <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> was doctoring a machine and said <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">in a minute.</said> On <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr> to me three stitchers implored her to look at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> miserable <w type="noun">implements</w></phr> and I waited patiently till I caught sight of the forewoman looking at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">bangs</w></phr> in a handglass.</seg> Apologizing for the intrusion I asked her if the sample had come yet.</p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">No.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">I wish you would kindly show me how wide to make this trimming.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Go to <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>, I told you.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> is too busy. She's mending machines.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Well, I won't be bothered with you?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">What's the reason you won't?</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Cause I won't.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Well you will. Tell me how wide you want this plush or I will see <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Ellinger</persName>.</said></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">See him. I don't care. There he is,</said> pointing to <seg>the snaky, half-starved creature whose shanks I had been sketching and on whom I had scornfully turned <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">back</w></phr></seg>. It was too much to ask of a free-born American woman to recognize the superiority of such a person. He came up to us in an instant. <seg>The forewoman was livid with rage and she began to talk as fast as <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> <w type="noun">tongue</w></phr> could move.</seg> Some fifty or more girls heard the tirade breathlessly. <seg>Before the half-dressed proprietor had a chance to get over <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">astonishment</w></phr> I threw the front of the cloak in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr>, the side body at the forewoman, and walked off to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> disabled <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> with <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Ellinger</persName> for a body guard.</seg> <seg>He was the color of a sanitatium babe when he reached <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> work <w type="noun">table</w></phr>.</seg> <seg>He had the two pieces of cloak in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">hand</w></phr> and when he raised <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">fist</w></phr> to strike me I worked up an <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">Indian-club</supplied></unclear> attitude and dared him.</seg></p><p><seg>He escorted me to the toilet-room, where I went for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hat</w> and <w type="noun">jacket</w></phr>, and before slamming the door in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> by way of a hint as to the privacy of the place I threw <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">needle</w> and <w type="noun">thread</w></phr> at him.</seg> <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Ellinger</persName> saw me across the shop and down the first flight of stairs. <seg>And there ended <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> first <w type="noun">experience</w></phr> in a cloak factory.</seg></p></div><div type="headline"><list>
<item>SIXTY CENTS A WEEK</item></list></div><div type="headlines"><list><item>For Working from 7:30 in the Morning Until 5:30 in the Evening</item><item>And Still the Poor Girls Complain the Prices Are Being Continually Cut Down</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p>I next made application for work at <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp"><orgName ref="#Wetherell" type="exposedCompany">Wetherell's</orgName></supplied></unclear>, on <placeName ref="#Wetherell" type="address">Wabash avenue</placeName>, where hundreds of girls are employed on corsets, bustles, skirts, jerseys and cloaks. Boarding the freight elevator I was drawn up to the top floor, where a pretty little Jewess informed me that <persName ref="#foreperson">Mr. <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">Saulsbery</supplied></unclear></persName> was engaged, but would see me in a little while. She showed me to a seat in the rear end of the store at the entrance to the shop-room, and for a single hour I listened to the drop, drop, drop of the heavy machinery and the snatches of song and merriment between the iron roar. Presently <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Wetherell</persName> came and sat by me.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Did you want work?</said> he asked.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Very much.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">What kind of work have you been doing?</said></p><p>I admitted I had never worked in a factory, but told him I could sew and was willing to do anything that would give me a living.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Well, you ought to have a chance - a good chance if you are willing to work - but it's dull just now and I don't see where we can put you. You say you can sew. Run the machine too? <seg>Well, we start <phr><w type="poss" ana="#Wetherell">our</w> skirt and cloak <w type="noun">rooms</w></phr> in a couple of weeks, and then we can try you.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">But I must have work</said>, I persisted, <said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">at once. I can't wait two weeks.</said></p><p><persName ref="#employer">Mr. Wetherell</persName> sighed a little and left me to see a customer who had just then entered. <seg>While I was fixing up a romance in case any inquiry was made as to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">age</w>, <w type="noun">name</w>, <w type="noun">residence</w> and <w type="noun">position in life</w></phr>, a sad-faced Irish mother came up the four stories with a sixteen-year-old daughter.</seg> They were as poorly dressed as myself, but considerably less happy. <seg>The <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">mother's</w> <w type="noun">hands</w></phr> were hard, thin and work-worn, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">her</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> seamed with care.</seg> She wore an old bonnet, a coarse black dress, poor shoes, an old shawl, and an expression of injury, despondency, and severity. <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> was a well-developed girl, with a good, wholesome face, red cheeks, bright, fun-loving eyes, big hands and feet, a most ungainly manner, and a nice figure. <seg>She had been crying, for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">her</w> <w type="noun">lashes</w></phr> were wet, and she seemed expectant that a crisis of some sort was near at hand. I soon learned that the mother missed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">her</w> <w type="noun">calling</w></phr> when she adopted maternal duties.</seg> The family lived in the region of <placeName type="locRef">Blue Island avenue</placeName> and consisted of the parents and growing children, two or three having married. <seg><persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> was the youngest and <said who="#messenger" ana="female">had todo something for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">grub</w></phr></said></seg>, as the mother said. For a long, time she worked in a box factory and made good wages, but the work was not steady, and last January she came to <orgName ref="#Wetherell" type="exposedCompany">Wetherell's</orgName>.</p><p>And what do you think she did?</p><p><seg>She earned 80 cents a week cutting dress reeds from 7:30 o'clock in the morning until 5:30 in the evening. <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> will be 17 years old in September. Here is <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">account</w></phr> of the work</seg>:</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Oh yes, I like it. They don't pay me much, but the forelady's good to me, and <persName ref="#foreperson">Mr. Saulsbery</persName> is awful kind. The girls is nice, too. The only thing I don't like is that they're always cuttin' me down. I can't make hardly nothing.</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female"><seg>Last week? Oh, last week I wasn't here. I staid home. It was so hot I didn't want to take the trouble to come down for 13 cents a day and walk and put up <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">lunch</w></phr>.</seg></said></p><p><seg>Thinking the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">girl's</w> <w type="noun">calculations</w></phr> were amiss I turned to the mother, who confirmed the statement, adding: <said who="#messenger" ana="female">It don't pay to feed that kid to work on the pay she's getting</said>.</seg></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">It's what all the girl's gets,</said> added <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>, beginning to cry. <seg>I played mother for a little while, told her she was a good girl to help <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">parents</w></phr> and not to mind, for there was plenty of work, and if she comes to <name ref="#CT">The Times</name> I'll help her get it.</seg></p><p><seg>After the Irish gray eyes had been dried with both corners of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> little black <w type="noun">shawl</w></phr> she gave me the prices at which she had been working.</seg> Here they are:</p><p>One cent a gross for cutting steels in eleven, fifteen and eighteen inch length. The work is done by machine, the operator using one foot and both hands constantly.</p><p>Four cents a gross for sewing buckles on bustles.</p><p>Three cents a dozen for basting bustles.</p><p>Four cents a dozen for springing bustles.</p><p>Seventy cents a dozen for putting elastics on reeds and boxing the same.</p><p>Wages in this department vary from 60 cents to $3 a week, $1.50 being a very fair average, and this too, for girls of 19 years and less.</p><p><seg>When the manager had dismissed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">guest</w></phr> he waited on <phr><persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">'s</w> <w type="noun">mother</w></phr>, who turned traitress, betraying <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">her</w> own <w type="noun">child</w></phr> to the enemy</seg> in this style:</p><p><said who="#messenger" ana="female">Can <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> come back, sir?</said> she asked.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Why, I guess so. What's been the matter?</said></p><p><seg><persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> rolled <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">finger</w></phr> up in black fringe, hung <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr>, and allowed the tears to stream down <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">cheeks</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#messenger" ana="female">Oh she's so sassy</said>, kindly volunteered the mother, <said who="#messenger" ana="female">and she comes home to me with a batch of stories every night about your cuttin' down the prices. Sure I can't believe a word she says.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Well, you come in the morning, <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>, and I'll see what we can do for you.</said> <seg>With this dismissal poor <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName> followed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">mother</w></phr>, who doubtless felt that she had done <phr><w type="poss" ana="#messenger">her</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">duty</w></phr> by the child.</seg></p><p><seg>I recited <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">piece</w></phr> to the low-voiced gentleman, who said there was plenty of work in the bustle department, but he guessed it wouldn't be pleasant for me, as the girls were only sixteen or so.</seg> I tried to assure him that I didn't care about the company, that I only wanted a chance to make a living for myself.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Well, I don't think you could earn enough to support yourself at machine work. Come in about Monday and I think we can give you something at $3 or so.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Three dollars a week?</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Yes.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">God have mercy on the girls,</said> I said reverently and departed.</p><p><persName ref="#nellNelson">NELL NELSON</persName></p></div></div></body></text>
</TEI>