<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title corresp="#CT006"><date when="1888-08-04">August 4, 1888</date></title><sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor><sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Rebecca Parker</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName>Gregory Bondar</persName></respStmt><!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:<respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt>--></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-04">2015-11-04</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor's degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head><title><name ref="#CT">Chicago Times</name> <date when="1888-08-04">Saturday Morning, August 4, 1888</date></title></head><!-- Check the title line!!! --><div type="headlines"><list><item><hi rend="double"><name ref="#CT">The Times</name></hi> Lady Reporter spends a Day in Goldsmith's Tailor Shop at 258 Rumsey Street.</item><item>And While Life shall Last She Will Not Forget the Misery, the Squalor, the Horrors of the Place.</item><item>Children 13 Years Old Working from Noon Till Night on Heavy Coats and Trousers.</item><item>Paying $3.50 a Week for Heavy Work Without Speaking and <hi rend="double">Pulled</hi> for Being Sick or Late.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p><seg>Never so long as reason reigns shall I forget the day I worked in <phr><orgName ref="#Goldsmith" type="exposedCompany"><persName ref="#employer">JL. Goldsmith</persName><w type="poss" ana="#Goldsmith">'s</w> <w type="noun">tailor-shop</w></orgName></phr>, and never when I pray shall I forget to add <hi rend="double">God help the shop girls</hi>.</seg></p><p> Thursday morning I stepped from an <placeName type="locRef">Ogden avenue</placeName> car and walked down <placeName type="locRef">Market street</placeName> in search of work. <seg>It was boiling hot and carried <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> brown <w type="noun">veil</w></phr> on the breeze, and a small pasteboard box containing a cracker and a lemon, a paper of needles, a thimble, and a pair of scissors.</seg> On the way I met two unhappy looking girls of whom I made labor inquiry. One had sewed carpet at $5 a week for the <orgName ref="#CCC">Chicago Carpet company</orgName> but was out of employment. <seg>The other said she earned $6 a week in <orgName ref="#WDbros"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#WDbros">W.D Brothers'</w> cravat <w type="noun">department</w></phr></orgName>.</seg> <seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Her</w> <w type="noun">kid</w></phr> was sick and the forewoman had <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">let her off for the day.</said></seg></p><p>The first clue I got to a place was a wooden sign with <hi rend="double">Sewing Girls Wanted</hi> that hung below the north window of <placeName type="address" ref="#HAM">155 Market street</placeName>, where <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#HAM">Messrs. Hart, Abt &amp; Marx</orgName> manufacture clothing. I read the sign and entered the main store-a nice, big, clean, cool place. <seg>A little girl sat the big type-writer making such clatter with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">letters</w></phr> that it was useless to try to call her.</seg> In the office were two gentlemen. One was the very prototype of <persName>Munkaesy</persName>'s <persName>Jesus Crist</persName> and he addressed for work. </p><p><said who="#employee" ana="male">The gentleman that attends to the work is not here just at present. Take a seat a moment.</said> I thanked him and looked at the vacant chair. It wouldn't do. It was too conspicuous. <seg>I knew the credit man in the building opposite and didn't care to be seen in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> factory <w type="noun">togs</w></phr>, so I went in a dark corner, where I stood, first on one foot and then on the other, for exactly forty minutes.</seg> Nobody came. Finally he with the Nazarene face appeared and said: <said who="#employer" ana="male">I'll go up and see if we want any more help.</said> Again I said <said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Thank you,</said> and watched him as he walked to the back of the store. </p><p>No, he didn't have a halo, but a monstrous pair of pedal extremities that curled up like an old-fashioned skate. </p><p><seg>When he got to the back of the store he simply retraced <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">steps</w></phr> and told me <said who="#employer" ana="male">We have all the girls we need.</said></seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Why don't you take the wooden sign in the window down?</said></p><p><seg>A sneer made <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> a hideous thing. I apologized to the Hungarian painter.</seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Supposing you take it in,</said> he said following me to the doorstep.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Why should I?</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">And for what purpose, please, should I take that sign in?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>For Christian charity, but Christian charity is not in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#HAM">your</w> <w type="noun">line</w></phr>.</seg></said> I then went over to <orgName ref="#SpitLand">Messrs. Spitz, Landaner &amp; Co.</orgName> There I encountered the manager of the work room and the most contemptuous treatment it was possible for a man to show a hapless woman. Suffice it to say <orgName ref="#HAM">Hart, Abt &amp; Marx</orgName> were avenged. </p><p>At <orgName ref="#Singer">A. L. Singer &amp; Co.'s</orgName> <placeName type="address" ref="#Singer">178 Market street</placeName>, I received the most courteous consideration. <seg>The manager took <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">name</w></phr>, or rather a name and address, and said he would give it to any of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#employer">patrons</w></phr> who needed help.</seg> Then he wrote me a letter of which the following is a copy:</p><p><persName ref="#employer">H. Goldsmith</persName> <placeName ref="#Goldsmith" type="address">258 Rumsey st</placeName>. - Sir: This girl wants work, <hi rend="single">I don't know what she can do, but I think you can use her.</hi>Respectfully,</p><p><orgName ref="#Singer">A. L. Singer</orgName> per <orgName ref="#Stein">Steins</orgName></p><p><placeName type="locRef">Rumsey street is two blocks west of Ashland avenue</placeName>. It begins at <placeName type="locRef">Division street</placeName> and runs south for a quarter of a mile or so over heaps of yellow clay, rubbish, and holes. The road is almost impassable for teams, and only the residents of the locality can take the upheavals and depressions of the sidewalk for a block without getting seasick. <seg>Filth of every description litters the ground, and following the line where a curbstone should be are garbage-boxes where the children mold mud pies during the day, where the men sit and smoke <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">pipes</w></phr> after the <phr><w type="poss">day's</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#employee">work</w></phr> is done, and where now and then old termagants backbite <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun" ana="#employee">neighbors</w></phr> and tear <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">each other's</w> <w type="noun">hair</w></phr>.</seg> Some of the cottages are so low that the chimneys barely reach above grade, and all swarm with children, pale, eager, dirty little creatures, that root about in the yellow clay and fresh dumping's like the dogs they play with. <seg>Poor children, it is not <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">mothers'</w> <w type="noun">fault</w></phr> that they are wild and unkempt for thelanguid parents give all <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">strength</w></phr> to the shop work in order to half feed and partly clothe them.</seg> I had only walked a few blocks in this deep rutted street in search of <persName ref="#employer">H. Goldsmith</persName> before being convinced that I was not in a district of protuberant optimists.</p><p>The first woman I made inquiry of was carrying a bucket of sawdust from a neighboring ale-house. She didn't know the name, but when I mentioned coats she grew loquacious.</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Oh, yes, the <hi rend="single">slave hole</hi> it's called; that's the sheeny tailor's! <seg>Don't you go to him, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#nellNelson">dear</w></phr>; he'll grind the marrow from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">bones</w></phr>. Go to service, girl, go to service.</seg> <seg>You can have a cot in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">room</w></phr> till you find a place.</seg> <seg>I was with him one fortnight and worked <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">eyes</w></phr> most blind and he paid me $1.75.</seg> No, I'm from England but I never had harder times in the old country than now. There I was paid 3 shilling for lodgings and here they cost me $4.</said> <seg>She told me she got the sawdust for sweeping out a corner dram-shop and used it to boil <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">tea kettle</w></phr> with.</seg> </p><p>The grandaunt of her quite overpowered me. Instead of a <hi rend="double">hole</hi> I found myself entering a large two-story red brick house still in process of construction. I ascended the front steps and after the maneuver of the celebrated king of France marched down again to the basement to the shop into the presence of <persName ref="#employer">H. Goldsmith</persName>, I handed him <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">letter</w></phr> and while he read it I took him in optically. He was unctuous little fellow, with kinky hair, cunning brown eyes, hatchet features and a small mustache the color of roasted coffee. He was attired in two shirts a neither one of chocolate flannel and a linen one a few shades lighter a pair of check pantaloons, carpet slippers, and a huge gold ring of masonic design. <seg>He read the letter with a cigar in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">mouth</w></phr>, the smell of which combined with the flavor of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">feet</w></phr> and the exhalations of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">toilet</w></phr> was something preponderant.</seg> </p><p><seg>He asked me what I had worked at and after a few gasps I gave him some of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">history</w></phr>, slightly distorted.</seg> </p><p><seg>I was told to take off <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hat</w></phr> and while doing so he stepped back out in the entry and vacated a hook among the factory girls wraps, but as I did not care to take the changes of tempting the gather snipes and going home bare-headed I declined <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">attention</w></phr> and hung them up in a corner on the floor.</seg> Already, sewing box in hand, I faced the gaping silent throng and was pointed to a chair at a long table about which ten girls were sewing with a speed and silence that was terrible to contemplate. They were cotton dresses of the poorest quality, some of them open at the neck, and nearly all rolled to the elbow. The youngest were four little girls of 13 one of whom was operating two basting and fourth finishing a blue cloth cloak. One large Irish hand, possibly 23 sat at the upper end of the table. Of the rest 13 years would be a fair average age. <seg>One poor girl, who was very lame, had a machine, and it make <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">heart</w></phr> ache to watch <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> pale <w type="noun">face</w></phr> and follow <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> thin little <w type="noun">hands</w></phr> guide coat after coat under the needle.</seg> <seg>All the girls were pale and haggard, some were very pretty, some few had color in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">cheeks</w></phr> but it was the heat flashes not the healthy glow of youth and physical strength.</seg></p><p><seg>In all there were twenty girls, eight men, and two boys-poor young fellows in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">teens</w></phr>, with mealy complexions, wild eyes, hollow cheeks, and sunken chests.</seg> Neither weighed a hundred pounds but both pressed goods with heavy feet and were called and pushed about by the boss and the assistant. <seg>The men worked in slippers and undershirt without straps or suspenders to keep <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">trousers</w></phr> in place and the girls wore heavy peg shoes.</seg> <seg>I noticed some of the machine hands worked the foot-plate in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> stocking <w type="noun">feet</w></phr>.</seg> </p><p><seg>I had taken all this in when the boss came near <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> and threw a plaid sack coat in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">lap</w></phr> and without a word walked away.</seg> <seg>There was a nice predicament I thought as I looked the garment over. I asked the little yellow haired Swede girl at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">right</w></phr> where to begin, but she looked at me and resumed her <hi rend="double">felling</hi> without a word of reply.</seg> <seg>Then I asked a big, yellow-haired, dough-faced German girl on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">left</w></phr> and received the same kind of response. Instantly I realized <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">position</w></phr>. Compulsory silence.</seg> </p><p><seg>I put twist in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">needle</w></phr>, squeezed on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">thimble</w></phr>, and selected the side-seam up the farmer satin lining, for if there is any one kind of needle work that I pride myself on it is <hi rend="double">felling</hi>.</seg> Well, I felled an hour, up one seam and down another, around the collar, and along the bottom of the coat. <seg>Then I stitched and tacked the tail pockets, took a deep breath, and settled back in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> to take a rest.</seg> I didn't take it long, though. <seg>Before I could reel off two lines of <phr><persName><w type="poss">Hood</w></persName>'s <hi rend="double"><w type="noun">Song of the Shirt</w></hi></phr> the boss was at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">elbow</w></phr> looking over <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr> with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> nasty smelly <w type="noun">cigar</w></phr> so near <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> that I was obliged to pull back to escape being burned.</seg> </p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Take smaller stitches,</said> he said. <said who="#employer" ana="male">Don't <hi rend="single">fell</hi> through. You haven't though. Now put in the sleeve-lining,</said> I did. <seg>In a great deal less I was told to rip it out. I put it in a second time did <persName ref="#workingGirl">Penelope</persName>'s work. The third time was not a charm and when <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> unction's <w type="noun">honor</w></phr>, who had been watching me all the time, neared <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> I politely asked him to show me how to arrange the fullness.</seg> <seg>He grabbed the coat, shook the <hi rend="double">muffy</hi> thing in my face dropped the stitches from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">two-for-a nickel</w></phr> to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hair</w></phr></seg>, and observed: <said who="#employer" ana="male">I don't think you'll do. I want experienced hands and pay $3.50 a week.</said></p><p><seg>Well, he showed me how tailors put in sleeve linings, and I showed the merits of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">teaching</w></phr>.</seg> <seg>In future I shall never let a coat-sleeve go about <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">waist</w></phr> without wanting <phr><w type="poss">its</w> <w type="noun">owner</w></phr> to unbutton and let me see where the lining is falled and how the top seam is felled.</seg></p><p>At noon we had forty minutes for I will not say dinner, because no one had anything that could be so designated unless it were <hi rend="double">Boss</hi> <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName>, and he went home. Most of the men had nothing to eat. I only saw two with a lunch. The girls had black bread and a can of cold coffee, which they consumed with evident relish. Not more than five minutes was spent over the repast. <seg>I devoured <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">crackers</w></phr> and gnawed at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">lemon</w></phr> by way of dessert.</seg> <seg>In a hurry to get at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr> as soon as possible to make up for lost time I threw the sucked Messina under the table and in a few moments saw a little stitcher pick it up and hide it in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">pocket</w></phr>.</seg> </p><p>By a series of questions I got the following information from a pretty Jewess who had been in the shop for three years and was getting $4.50 a week. She said regarding the salary. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Oh. I don't care, <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName> won't pay anymore. <seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">My</w> <w type="noun">mother</w></phr> has money and doesn't mind so long as I learn to sew.</seg> I am 15 in October. I've been here at 12 and don't know how much longer I will have to stay. <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName> thinks women are cows that must be driven. So he drives us. We have to be at work at 7 in the morning and stay till 6 in the evening.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Half-holiday Saturday?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Non</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">What if you are sick?</said></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">If you're sick pulls you. He pulled one for 20 cents for being late last week. He pulls if someone comes late, and he pulls if we talk.</said></p><p><seg>That's why I could not get <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">neighbors</w></phr> to tell me how to start <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><seg><persName ref="#workingGirl">Rosy</persName> told me she was 13, that <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">father</w></phr> peddled tests, and that she was the eldest of five sisters and two brothers.</seg> She had been in the shop two years and was getting $2.25 a week.</p><p>Another girl whom I dare not indicate said: <seg><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">These beggarly Jews and Swedes are robbing honest girls of a living. Most of them have homes and are willing to work for free. I live with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">mother</w> and <w type="noun">brother</w></phr> and can not make any more than enough to pay <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">our</w> <w type="noun">rent</w></phr> $10 a month. I would leave <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">family</w></phr> but <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">mother</w></phr> needs me</said>.</seg> <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName> is an awful hard man. <seg>He steals <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">hire</w></phr> from me and I spend for glitter and silk whenever I get a chance.</seg></p><p>During the noon hour the girls played in the front street and afterward amused themselves in the backyard with the men. At 12:13 o'clock we come back into the shop and <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="3"/>five minutes later<unclear><supplied resp="#KMW"> the place was noisy with </supplied></unclear><damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="4"/><unclear><supplied resp="#KMW">flying shuttles, clicking needles</supplied></unclear>, and the whizzing wheels of the spinning machinery. <seg>The young heads and pretty shoulders bent over coats and faces were so low that they almost touched the sewing in the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">owner's</w> <w type="noun">clothes</w></phr>.</seg> The clatter of the machinery was deafening and every now and then shop responded with the heavy hot iron wielded by <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName> in the back room. Nobody had any <unclear/> on hand the work instead <unclear/>instead <unclear/> the cutter there <unclear/> to the trimmer, who in turn threw it to the baster and so it moved from hand to machine going the bound of the thirty odd workers with suchrapidity that the air seemed filled with flying coats. The room was low and with every passage of coat tail muffy clouds of lint seemed floating about in space. <seg>Add to that poor light bad ventilation, the exhalations of so many people, the smell of due from the cloth, and the noxious odor of that ever-consuming cigar and you have materials for the make-up of <phr><orgName ref="#Goldsmith" type="exposedCompany"><persName ref="#employer">Mr. Goldsmith</persName><w type="poss" ana="#Goldsmith">'s</w> <w type="noun">coat-shop</w></orgName></phr>.</seg> All afternoon we serve sewed; sewed incessantly without uttering a syllable or resting a moment. <persName ref="#employer">Goldsmith</persName> was building the third story of the house, and every hour or so he left the shop in care to an assistant and went up to look after the carpenters. During these intermittent spells the girls took advantage of the substitute and hummed. They didn't sing, they hummed sounds and hymns, marches, and waltzes, and when the sub was not looking that actually whispered.</p><p>But the absentee possessed marvelous powers of ubiquitousness and very little time was wasted in this manner. There are some people you will always know were in the room without seeing them. <seg>This hard-headed, godless little Jew was a character of that sort. We could feel <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">presence</w></phr> and corresponding heaviness of atmosphere.</seg> <seg>Whenever he caught sight of a momentary idler he would glide up to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">elbow</w></phr> and mutter a single verb - work! She worked.</seg> </p><p>At 5 o'clock I was so tired I didn't know what to do with myself. <seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">My</w> <w type="noun">hair</w></phr> was matted with moisture and dusted with lint, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> throbbed with pain.</seg> </p><p><seg>I perspired at every pore, and the steels in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">corsets</w></phr> rusted all the front of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> nice <w type="noun">Hamburg</w></phr> under waist.</seg> I threw the big brown chinchilla overcoat. I had finished on the floor and for a period of three minutes fell into a state of voluptuous inertia. <seg>With <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> sixth <w type="noun">sense</w></phr> I saw the <hi rend="double">boss</hi> pick up the garment and another overcoat came flying across the table and dropped all over me.</seg> <seg>I threaded <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">needle</w></phr> preparatory to finishing <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> ninth <w type="noun">garment</w></phr>, began a light callisthenic movement of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> right <w type="noun">arm</w></phr> to scatter the pain and limber up <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">elbow</w></phr>.</seg> <seg>I went through perhaps seven motions, with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> tilted back by the way of stretching <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> lower <w type="noun">extremities</w></phr> when I was interrupted by the benevolent young tailor and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> incombustible <w type="noun">cigar</w></phr></seg>. </p><p><seg>Grabbing the frame of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> he jammed it down all fours and told me to <said who="#employer" ana="male">get to work.</said></seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much am I going to get for this work?</said> <seg>I inquire, after recovering from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">astonishment</w></phr> and the sudden shock of gravitation.</seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Do you want to know?</said> he asked with a contemptibly significant laugh.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">If you please.</said> </p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Well, just finish that coat and at 6 o'clock I'll tell you.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>I won't finish any more. There's <phr><w type="poss" ana="#Goldsmith">your</w> <w type="noun">coat</w></phr>. Pay me.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Pay you! For what?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">For seven hours' work. For finishing eight coats.</said></p><p><seg>Without further notice of me than an insolent sneer he picked up the coat, walked back to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">cutting-board</w></phr> and began to draft out collars. I went back to the cutting-board, too, and stood at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">side</w></phr> till commanded to <said who="#employer" ana="male">get out of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr>.</said> I stepped back enough to give him elbow room, but did not leave the table. </seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male"><seg>How long do you expect to annoy me by <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">presence</w></phr>?</seg></said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>I expect to remain where I am till you pay me for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> seven hours' <w type="noun">work</w></phr>.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male"><seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">Your</w> <w type="noun">day</w></phr> isn't up yet. We don't quit till 6 o'clock and its only ten minutes after 5.</seg></said></p><p><seg>I told him I did not want to work for him another minute and demanded <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">pay</w></phr>.</seg> </p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Well do you want to know what I'd pay you?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Yes.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">One dollar and fifty cents a week and you ain't worth 75 cents.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">You told me when I started that I would get $3 at least if I could sew.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">And you can't. <seg>All day you have been sitting up in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">shoulders</w></phr> straight and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> back as if you had a rocking-chair.</seg> There's what I value you at,</said> and he threw a 25 cent piece at me. At first I hesitated about touching the money, and, as <seg>I looked at him to see whether he was serious or not <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">eyes</w></phr> rested on the heavy gold ring he wore</seg>.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Oh, you're a <orgName ref="#BB">B'nai B'rith</orgName> man I see. <seg>Will you favor me with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">your</w> <w type="noun">card</w></phr>?</seg></said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">What for?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>I want to send this money to the society for the orphans which you represent with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">compliments</w></phr>.</seg></said> </p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Get out of this shop or I'll put you out.</said> Begging him not to go to that trouble I got. <seg>On <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr> out I took <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">box</w></phr> containing <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">sewing weapons</w></phr> from the table, and before I had gone two yards the humane proprietor of the establishment challenged me.</seg> </p><p><seg>I made a pert remark about scorning to take any of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">belongings</w></phr> that were not disinfected and proceeded toward the door, behind which I had stowed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hat</w> and <w type="noun">jacket</w></phr>.</seg> <seg>Debating whether I had better take in the vest cellar on the corner of Rumsey and Division streets or go back to the office and write <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">copy</w></phr> I stood at a machine table and tossed in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> day's <w type="noun">earnings</w></phr>.</seg> The first throw was heads, the second heads, and before I could reckon the third the angry boss informed me in an orotund quality of voice that <said who="#employer" ana="male">that's good American money and if you don't want just hand it back to me.</said> <seg>Not deigning to notice the man I pinned on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hat</w></phr>, and this worthy member of the slave-driving fraternity used the opportunity every low-lived wretch has to insult a friendless, helpless working-girl.</seg> <seg>It may gratify <persName ref="#employer">H. Goldsmith</persName> to know that <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">cowardice</w></phr> had the desired effect.</seg> <seg>But I told him he would hear from me again and I mean to keep <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">word</w></phr>.</seg> I know personally several members of <orgName ref="#BB">B'nai B'rith</orgName> and I am sure that they at least do not know the character of this man, if they know he is a member. </p><p><seg>Whatever opinions I may have entertained about the dignity of labor, respectable poverty, and the absurdity of fine feathers <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">experience</w></phr> as a factory hand has unfitted me for future service, since in no place I worked did I see any incentive to decency, honesty, or respectability, or any promise of success that did not carry with it the downfall of, blindly climbing hope.</seg> </p><p>-	Nell Nelson</p></div></div></body></text>
</TEI>