<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title corresp="#CT004"><date when="1888-08-02">Thursday Morning, August 2,1888</date></title><sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfireserver</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">PittsburghSupercomputing Center</ref></sponsor><sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref>server</sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Rebecca Parker</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription by</resp><persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University ofPittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName>Gregory Bondar</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2015-12-03">2015-12-03</date>. Codedby</resp><persName ref="#ras">Rob Spadafore</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-04">2015-11-04</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->.This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'sin-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History basedSocial Sciences Bachelor's degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh atGreensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the projectbegain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title level="s">City Slave Girls</title><author>Nelson, Nell</author><editor>Chapin, Charles</editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Newspaper Print</edition></editionStmt><extent>21-part series: Front-page placement</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Chicago Times</publisher><pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace><date>1888</date><publisher>New York University Digital Library Technology Services(DLTS)</publisher><availability><p><ref target="http://dlib.nyu.edu/undercover/city-slave-girls-nell-nelson-chicago-times-aka-white-slave-girls-new-york-world">www.dlib.nyu.edu</ref></p></availability></publicationStmt></biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split atthe end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text.Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as tomake a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, theinformation portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with theoriginal. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of thedocument we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combinationto provide our best interpretation of the text.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head><title><name ref="#CT">Chicago Times</name><date when="1888-08-02">Thursday Morning, August 2,1888</date></title></head><div type="headlines"><list><item><hi rend="double"><name ref="#CT">The Times</name></hi> Lady Reporter, in the Guise of a Factory Bondwoman, IsInsulted by a Scoundrel.</item><item>Accosted by a Well-Dressed Brute Who Tries to Thrust His BlightingFriendship on Her.</item><item>Human Monsters Who Lure from Virtue's Path the Half-Starved Victims ofMan's Cupidity.</item><item>Manufacturers Who Pay Their Serfs the Miserly Sum of Eighty Cents forMaking a Dozen Shirts.</item><item>A Big Collar and Cad Maker of Troy N.Y Astonished at the State ofAffairs in Chicago.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p><seg>On Thursdaymorning when I started to renew <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w>factory<w type="noun">life</w></phr> I discovered after getting on a South-sidecar that I did not have a cent in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">pocket</w></phr>. In putting on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w>shop-girl<w type="noun">disguise</w></phr> I had left <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">purse</w></phr> at home.</seg> When the conductor asked for the fair I had none to give him. It was very hot, the clouds threatened rain, and the shop was at so great a distance that I did not feel as if I couldwalk. <seg>I concluded to throw myself on the generosity ofthe conductor and told him I had forgotten <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">purse</w></phr>. He looked ugly and told me to get off.Just as he placed <phr><w type="poss">his</w><w type="noun">whistle</w></phr> to <phr><w type="poss">his</w><w type="noun">lips</w></phr> to signal the gripmanto stop a distinguished, well-dressedman paid <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">fare</w></phr>.</seg> <seg>I thanked him for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">courtesy</w></phr> and told him if he would give me<phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">card</w></phr> I would send him the money he had so kindly paid.</seg></p><p>He smiled and said: <said who="#benefactor" ana="male">A merebagatellemiss, and not worth mentioning.</said></p><p><seg>At <placeName type="locRef">Eighteenth street</placeName> I left the car to go to a <phr><orgName ref="#VestMaker1"><w type="poss" ana="#employer">vestmaker's</w><w type="noun">place</w></orgName></phr> at <placeName ref="#VestMaker1" type="address" >2155 Archeravenue</placeName>.</seg> <seg>I was crossing <placeName type="locRef">the threepoints where State and Nineteenth streets intersect</placeName> when whoshould come abreast but <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun" ana="#benefactor">benefactor</w></phr>. Instead ofraising <phr><w type="poss">his</w><w type="noun">hat</w></phr> he jauntily cocked <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w>left<w type="noun">eye</w></phr> and came so close to me that the sleeve of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <hi rend="double">never-rip</hi> <w type="noun">jersey</w></phr> was pressed againstthe waist-line of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w>light-gray<w type="noun">suit</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Aha, here we areagain!</said></p><p><seg>Although I distinctly heard everyword of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">remark</w></phr> I said: <said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">I beg <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">your</w><w type="noun">pardon</w></phr></said>, with as much of the<placeName type="locRef">Newport</placeName>chill as I could affect.</seg></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Come, come, now,</said> he said withincreasedgayety, <seg>moving <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">waistband</w></phr> still closer to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">jersey</w></phr></seg>.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>Oh, you are the gentleman to whom I am indebted for car-fare. You want <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">your</w><w type="noun">money</w></phr> I suppose; if you will give me<phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">your</w><w type="noun">card</w></phr> I will write you an order.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Do you work in this neighborhood?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">No sir.</said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Where, then?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Noplace.</said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Where are you going?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">For work.</said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">What kind?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Anykind. <seg>May I have <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">your</w><w type="noun">card</w></phr></seg>? I am in somethingof a hurry.</said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Mayn't I have yours?</said> heasked.</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>Certainly; I haven't <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">case</w></phr>, but if you will lend me a pencil I will write you one.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male"><seg>With pleasure, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">my</w><w type="noun">dear</w></phr>.</seg></said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><seg>You are mistaken, sir. That is not<phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">name</w></phr>.</seg></said></p><p><seg><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Ha, ha, ha! I see you are a littlemischievous, but for all that you are <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">my</w><w type="noun">dear</w></phr></said>, producing threeinches of Faber.</seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">A cardplease?</said></p><p><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Bless me, I had forgotten</said>, andthe natty-sack-coat was ransacked for a suitablecard.</p><p><seg><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Ah, here-this will do, I hope, in lieu ofsomethingmoreconventional</said>, carefully placing on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">sewing-box</w></phr> a smallcard with the address down.</seg>I reversed the pasteboard and read on the back:</p><p><persName ref="#promMen">DR. Charles Gilman Smith.</persName></p><p>Office Hours___________</p><p>Residence___________</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female"><persName ref="#promMen">Dr. Smith</persName>! I knowhim quite well.</said></p><p><seg><said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Oh, you do, eh?</said> in a tone thatleft no doubt that <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w> <w type="noun">stock</w></phr> in me had dropped.</seg> I wrote:</p><p>Reporter.</p><p><name ref="#CT">The Times</name>.</p><p>and <seg>handed it to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#benefactor">companion</w></phr></seg>, who read it with eyes that seemed to have been wired open. <seg>While he crushed the<phr><w type="poss" ana="#promMen">doctor's</w><w type="noun">card</w></phr> in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w>left<w type="noun">hand</w></phr><phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">right</w></phr> pulled out a splendidgoldwatch</seg>, and with a most abrupt <said who="#benefactor" ana="male">Didn't think it wasso late, have an engagement at 9:45</said>, was offwith more alacrity than is conducive to grace. <seg>I looked after him, admiringthe cut of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">coat</w></phr>, the swing of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">trousers</w></phr>, the polish of<phr><w type="poss" ana="#benefactor">his</w><w type="noun">shoes</w></phr>, and the magnificentcarriage of head and shoulders</seg>, and thought:</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">May the lord deliverus workinggirls.</said> <seg>I also thought that I shouldlike to meet <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w>car<w type="noun">friend</w></phr> when I had <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> suffocating<w type="noun">veil</w></phr> off and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> good<w type="noun">clothes</w></phr> on.</seg> <seg>Won't <persName ref="#promMen">Dr.Smith</persName> inveigle him to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#promMen">his</w> <placeName type="locRef">Statestreet</placeName><w type="noun">office</w></phr> and present me? I was to give him back <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w><w type="noun">nickel</w> and lead<w type="noun">pencil</w></phr>.</seg></p><p>When I reached the shop at <placeName type="address" ref="#VestMaker1">2155Archer avenue</placeName> the tailor told me he onlywanted onevestmaker and had hired her twohours ago, <seg>I then went over on <placeName type="locRef">Cottage Grove avenue</placeName>, borrowed 25cents from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">dressmaker</w></phr> and rode down to <placeName type="locRef">Lake street</placeName> to get work ina feather dusterfactory.</seg> There may have been work, but there was noelevator and I was toohot and tired to go up fiveflights of stairs to lookfor it. I chose a <orgName ref="#CigarFactory1" type="exposedCompany">cigar factory</orgName><placeName ref="#CigarFactory1" type="address">on Randolph near Dearborn street</placeName> withbut threepairs of stairs to climb andlearned in the salesroom that they had all the help they needed. <seg>I tried <persName ref="#employer">Gomez</persName>across the street, who had nowork, but enoughgoodness of heart to give mea chair and a letter to twocigarmakers of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w><w type="noun">nationality</w></phr>.</seg> I went to see <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#CigarFactory2"><persName ref="#employer">F.Garcia</persName></orgName> at <placeName type="address" ref="#CigarFactory2">20th Clark street</placeName>. He asked me if Icould <hi rend="double">strip</hi> and I told him I could. When he wanted to know where I hadworked I owned up that I didn't know anything at allabout the business but was anxious to learn and get work. He didn't know <said who="#employer" ana="male">how a sewinggirl would do at the <hi rend="single">fillers</hi> but you might go and talk with someof the help, for you may not be satisfied to try even.</said></p><p>He showed me the way across the hall toan emptyroom. The floor was litteredwith rags and paper and the dust was heavy on the walls and wood-work and in onecorner was a good-sizedash-pile. <seg><persName ref="#employer">Garcia</persName> rappedfor entrance, but there was so much noise within that the door remained fast. Whenthe Spaniard left me I turned the knob and came upon a bigboy who was tickling <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w><w type="noun">laborers</w></phr>. The girls were flying around the emptyroom and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w><w type="noun">pursuer</w></phr> had both screeching.</seg> The fun came to a stop the momentI went in and the youngpeople gladly told me all I cared to know aboutthe business. All they did was to <hi rend="double">strip</hi> – just pull thestem or mid-rib from the leaf and put it in a <hi rend="double">book-filler</hi>. <seg>Icould get $4 a week and steadywork and the nextyear$5. <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">My</w><w type="noun">informant</w></phr>, a littlegirl of 15years, has been in the shoptwoyears and earned $5.30 a week.</seg> Shetold me she was the oldesthand in the shop: that shecould <hi rend="double">strip</hi> as fast as a man, and put the ribbonbands about the cigarsbefore they were boxed.</p><p>At 12:15 o'clock I went into the shop and was given a chair in front of a barrel filled with inches of tobacco called <hi rend="double">hands</hi> and lined with gunny-cloth.<seg>There was a littletinpail of brownwater for wetting I don't know what near<phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">chair</w></phr>, and on the otherside a pineboardthree feet long and sixteen inches wide.</seg> When the tobaccoleaves were stripped and laid on the board itwas thubbed a <hi rend="double">book-filler</hi> and carried off to the next room. In the shopwith this were some eighteen men or more rolling the <hi rend="double">fillers</hi>, putting onthe wrappers, shaping the cigars with a broadknife and seeming the ends.<seg>Along the tablessome of the men were smoking and others chewing, some with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w><w type="noun">hats</w></phr> on and all in theshirt-sleeves.</seg> There were negroes, Swedes, a Chinaman, Germans, and Spaniards, whose influence on the lives of the younggirls, while not reallyharmful, could hardly be called beneficial. I stripped leaves enough to enable me to take the socialcondition of the inmates,the badlight, impureatmosphere, the chokingsmell of the tobacco, andthe photographs and prints cut fromsensationalpapers that were tacked on the smoke-stainedwalls.</p><p>From the cigarfactory I went to the <orgName ref="#EUC" type="exposedCompany">Excelsior Underwear Company</orgName>, <placeName ref="#EUC" type="address">199 and 201 Fifth avenue</placeName> and satfor half an hour while the forewomanscolded a pale-facedgirl who wore mourning. Shehad brought back a dozen chemises for which the house paid $2, but the work was soiled in the making-machine oil havingwet the cotton – and the forewoman refused to take it.</p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">What shall I do?</said> <seg>She asked the woman, with a voice as sad as<phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w><w type="noun">face</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">What does anybody dowith dirty things? You will have to pay for laundering the garments of the greasy sewing and clean thethread.</said></p><p>Then the girl was left alone by the manager, who went up to the other end of the counter to get trimmings for six dozen chemises thata tall young Swede girl was waiting for. <seg>The forewoman wore a blue dress of plaid design with a Marseilles vest buttoned in it, and of seven rings on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w> left <w type="noun">hand</w></phr> six were set with whatappeared to be diamonds.</seg> <seg>She had jewels at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w><w type="noun">chin</w></phr> and in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w><w type="noun">ears</w></phr> and hair.</seg> She measured off the lace edgings and the tape insertion andgave minute directions about the fullness and the finish. <seg>The six dozen garments were bundled up by <persName ref="#employer">Mr.Hyman</persName>, the proprietor, and the elevator carried her and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#foreperson">her</w><w type="noun">load</w></phr> to the pavement below.</seg><seg>The seamstress told me she lived at home and with the help of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w><w type="noun">mother</w></phr> made $12 a week.</seg></p><p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">It is very hard work though</said>, she said <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">We sew day and night. I had rather do itthan work down in a shop for I have more self-respect. <seg>All the girls are not good, and very few are in a position to go with respectable people. They go with bad company and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w><w type="noun">language</w></phr> is bad.</seg> Sometimes in the winter they dance till daylightand go from the hall to the shop.I don't blame them. <seg>The life of a girl who had nothing todepend on but <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w><w type="noun">needle</w></phr> is a best a hard one.</seg> Still I don't like to be with a crowdof factory girls if I can help it.The manager and superintendent obliged to be strict, but very seldom make anydistinction in the treatmentof a nice girl and one who is not so nice. I don't think I cantell you how many ways there are to insult a girl. <seg>I have had a foreman just give me a lookas I passed in to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w><w type="noun">machine</w></phr> or handed in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w><w type="noun">sewing</w></phr> that made me wish I was dead.</seg> Thenthere are the spiteful things the girls say about you and the cutting remarks of the forewoman that make you feel like fainting. <seg>The cashier may have a grudge andif he doesn't hold <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w><w type="noun">wages</w></phr> back till all the other hands are paid hell will throw itat you, make you take ragged bills, or give – you a<phr><w type="poss">week's</w> <w type="noun">pay</w></phr> in change.</seg> <seg>A cashier in a <placeName type="locRef">Jackson street</placeName> cravat factory once rubbed <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">his</w><w type="noun">hand</w></phr> across <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w><w type="noun">chin</w></phr> to feel <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w><w type="noun">whiskers</w></phr>, he said, and because I got angryand said I would report him he saved up all the silver that had holes and plugs and made me take it.</seg> <seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">My</w> <w type="noun">salary</w></phr> was $3.25 that week, and some of the silver couldn't pass. I took it to a bankand the cashier was kind enough togive me good money for it.</seg> Plenty of times the forewoman hashad me discharged for being <hi rend="double">stuck up</hi>.</said></p><p><seg>Prices here range from 20 cents to $2 a dozen. It depends on the material. <phr><w type="poss">Children's</w> <w type="noun">drawers</w></phr> pay 20cents a dozen, but there are nobutton holes to work.</seg> Some shirts are$2 some$4 and some$1.70 but most of them only pay 20 cents. Everything is done by machine including button holes and gussets. The bosoms and bands are ready to go in. Corset-covers pay 40 cents and 20 cents each, but they have to be trimmed and the holes worked by hand. This is a mean shop, so far as prices go, but theyare all alike in that particular. <seg>You have to find <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">your</w> own <w type="noun">thread</w></phr> and you are constantly being suspected of keepingback short ends of trimmings.</seg></p><p>I asked the forewoman for stitching and was given shirts at 80 cents a dozen to do. I had to pay 50cents for the use of the machineand 25 cents for a spindle of thread. <seg>I told the forewoman I had left <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w><w type="noun">purse</w></phr> at home, but she saidit was <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">alright you can have it takenout of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">your</w> <w type="noun">wages</w></phr>.</said></seg> I asked her what the machine cost, but she doesn't know, and when I venturedthat the expiration of the patient hadreduced the old place$15 to about $12 she told me she<said who="#foreperson" ana="female">reckoned I didn't know what I wastalking about.</said> The room where we worked wasabout eighteen feet wide and ten feetdeep with toilet closets built out from the walls. The machines encircled thethree walls and in the middle of thefloor were the boxes of work. One girl wasstitching wrist-bands, another had button-hole machine and was getting 50 cents a hundred. A thirdwas making tucked drawers at 20 centsa dozen and I had a shirt at 60 cents which I failed to finish all three hours, being unable to manage a machine.</p><p>-<persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName>.</p></div></div></body></text>
</TEI>
