<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Parker_NellNelsonProject_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <div type="preface">
    <subtitle>AUTHOR’S PREFACE.</subtitle>
    <p>IN the following pages will be found a record which, in many places, amounts to an indictment
        of our whole system and our whole civilization. <desc of="workingClass">The position of the <ref
            to="newspaperSeries">White Slaves</ref> in our factories is something which can only
        be described as disgraceful.</desc> In going on as we are going -- in not stopping the abuses to
        which female labor is subjected here at our very doors, we are doing what is at once a
        foolish and a dangerous thing. We are sowing what we must reap; and as long as what is
        called the dangerous element in this community can point out <desc of="womensLabor">the rank injustice to which we
        subject female labor</desc>, so long will they have in their hands an argument which we cannot
        meet. These things can be made straight and just and fair. We can with little effort do
        justice, and it is the purpose of these pages to excite those who can do right; to do
        it.</p> <p>With the facts in the case spread before a candid world there should be little
    question about what should be done. <desc of="womensLabor">It is not an issue as to what women should be paid for their
    work. Until they themselves learn how to organize, they must expect bad treatment in that
    direction. Nobody can say that an employer must pay a dollar for that which is offered to him at
    fifty cents. But we can demand that proper care, proper sanitation and proper treatment shall be
    accorded to every working woman.</desc></p> <p>As far as the rest of the matter goes, <desc of="womensLabor">female labor must
        organize if it wishes to do anything. Organized labor is the end to which the industry of
        the civilized world is tending, and every year the movement becomes more and more certain of
        ultimate success.</desc> There have been checks and drawbacks, but the force which impels the
        workingman forward to a general union with all of his fellows has been constant and
        irresistible.</p>
    <p>As we have endeavored to show in the following pages, there is a necessity for general labor
        organization, such as has been never before known in the world. The age is one of
        combination, both of the <pb n="IV"/> working class and the employing class. Unless either
        side unites in a strong, well-disciplined union, it must go to the wall. The proper reply to
        the corporation, the pool and the trust is the trades-union, the trade federation, and some
        society which shall bind into one homogeneous, one-ideaed and perfectly-disciplined mass the
        whole of the working element in the <placeName type="country">United States</placeName>.</p>
    <p>To this end experiments have been made and will be made. <orgName>The Trades Union Congress
            of England</orgName>; <orgName>the Knights of Labor of America</orgName>; similar
        societies on the Continent, -- are all evidences of the necessities for organization and the
        attempts which men are making in that direction. But all of these social forces are new and
        their leaders inexperienced. Often the right road can not be found until after all the wrong
        ones have been tried. We find society provided with a new weapon, but it is only out of many
        mistakes, out of much loss and suffering, that we will arrive at the knowledge of its proper
        use and its correct purpose. We have nearly settled the question of what the trades-union
        can do, and what it cannot do -- we have surveyed it,weighed it, appraised it. It occupies a
        definite place in our calculations. It is no longer an unknown quantity in the problem. But
        the force, the defensive and the offensive powers of thoroughly organized national labor are
        not known, nor will they be in this century.</p>
    <p>One great society after another will arise, and take up the work which its predecessor laid
        down. Each will avoid the rocks upon which the earlier ones went to pieces; the unknown seas
        of organization are being charted surely, if slowly, and the people are coming to know where
        the dangers lie. It is part of the history of human effort that moves in wave -- now coming
        in with a high tide, and again ebbing out so that it seems that almost all the advance has
        been lost. This is, however, seeming rather than reality. With <persName>Tennyson</persName>
        we <quote speaker="Tennyson">"-- Know that through the ages one increasing purpose runs And the thoughts of men
            are widened with the process of the suns."</quote> Even if the men of the present day do
        not find themselves able to mobilize, equip and maintain the army of labor, doubt it not
        that their sons and their daughters will.</p>
    <pb n="V"/>
    <p>There are elements of strength which have not even been touched by the present leaders,
        although of course they have been recognized, and efforts toward getting them have been
        made. Take the elections, for instance. There were in the <placeName type="country">United
            States</placeName>, in <date year="1880">1880</date>, 17,392,099 people engaged in all kinds of
        occupations. The voting population was, white and black, 12,830,349 for the <date
            year="1880">same year</date>; and the President, <persName>James A. Garfield</persName>,
        was elected by the ballots of 4,449,053 citizens. <persName>Cleveland</persName>
        <date year="1884">four years later</date> was chosen by the votes of 4,911,017 men; and
            <!--rjp: look up the date of publication.. pretty sure it 1888--><date year="1888">this
            year</date> a President will be made by the votes of not more than 5,500,000 persons.
        Now can any person believe that there are not in <placeName type="country">America</placeName> much more
        than 6,000,000 or 7,000,000 of citizens who would be willing to come together on a labor
        platform and for labor candidates, if they could have confidence in the integrity of the men
        and the honesty of the measures. <orgName>The George movement</orgName> in
            <placeName type="state">New York</placeName> proved at once the strength and the weakness of the
        laborers and the friends of labor. They were able to do a great deal even with their
        imperfect machinery of organization, and the disappearance of this vote in a subsequent
        election showed that there was nothing permanent in the methods by which it had been called
        out. It was a flash in the pan, but it proved something that labor should not willingly
        forget.</p>
    <p>The road to power in this country lies but in one direction -- through the ballot box. That
        is our final tribunal of appeal, and its decisions we must accept heartily, willingly,
        loyally. When organized labor raises its voice in this court, the world will listen with
        respect. But until that time comes, the workingman’s duty is still clear. Neither
            <placeName type="city">Rome</placeName> nor organized labor were, or will be, built in a day. The
        movement must be pushed firmly and guided wisely. There must be statesmanship and diplomacy,
        as well as sacrifice and loyalty. Labor and capital must both listen to the voice of public
        opinion in <placeName type="country">America</placeName>, for both are weak, and properly weak, before it.
        It is our ruler, whether we are rich or poor, eminent or humble; and it is a wise ruler,
        whose commands are born of truth and justice and carried out in strictness and mercy. When
        public opinion is with labor organization and its methods, then, and not until then, will
        the labor problem be solved.</p>
        </div>
</root>
