<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title level="a" xml:id="CT005"><!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each article --><!-- RJP: each article will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and article number (add  2 zeros in front of early articles so we have consistent format with articles that will be double and even triple digits). For example: the first article in the series published in the Chicago Times will be xml:id="CT001" --><date when="1888-08-03">Friday Morning, August 3, 1888<!-- RJP: this is the actual text of the title of each article: generally the date hence why it is surrounded by a date element --></date><!-- RJP: I put the xx notation here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the date is changed according to the date on each article  --></title>
                <title level="m">"City Slave Girls"</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --> 
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-04">2015-11-04</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">"City Slave Girls"</title>
                        <author>Nelson, Nell</author><!-- RJP: note to self: make sure add Helen Cusack as an alternative name for Nell Nelson in the site index -->
                        <editor>Chapin, Charles</editor><!-- RJP: note to self: check this information and spelling of last name!!-->
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Newspaper Print</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>21-part series: Front-page placement</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Chicago Times</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date>1888</date>
                        <publisher>New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS)</publisher>
                        <availability>
                            <p><ref target="http://dlib.nyu.edu/undercover/city-slave-girls-nell-nelson-chicago-times-aka-white-slave-girls-new-york-world">www.dlib.nyu.edu</ref>
                            </p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><title><ref type="newspaperSeries">Chicago Times</ref> <date when="1888-08-03">Friday Morning, August 3, 1888</date></title></head>
            <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>While Among Chicago’s Weak Serfs The Times’ Lady Reporter Finds Mr. Goss’ “Good Jew.”</item>
                        <item>Holding Her Nose, She Gazes Upon All Kinds of Soul-and-Body Starving Wretchedness.</item>
                        <item>In a Small, Dirty Room Filled with A Crowd of Women Life Seems Like a Hideous Dream.</item>
                        <item>To Save Space, These Unshackled Servants of Greed Are Compelled to Take Short Stitches.</item>
                        <item>Even Pins Are Not Given to the Employee and the Girls Have to Use Their Underclothing for Towels.</item>
                    </list>
            </div>
                <div type="articleBody">
                    <p>Two weeks ago <persName>Rev. Mr. Gross</persName> preached a sermon relative to the morals and progress of the working woman. <rs type="wageDesc" ref="#ras">Among other things he referred to a “good Jew” who, having the comfort of the hundred odd girls in his cloak factory at heart, “provided every day for 1 cent a substantial lunch.”</rs> I sent the reverend gentleman a note, inclosing a stamp for the address of the “good Jew” and in reply came the name of <persName>H. Zimmerman</persName>, <placeName type="address">233 Monroe street</placeName>. On went poverty’s respectable rags, and off I posted for shop-work and a penny spread.</p>
        <p><rs type="workEnvir" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">The elevator carried me to the top of the building where every week thousands of jackets, sacques, circulars, dolmans, and cloaks are turned out to supply the country trade of the northwest. Here in a crowded room, with low ceiling and dingy walls, poorly ventilated and insufficiently lighted, sit between eighty and 150 young girls surrounded from Monday morning until Saturday noon by the ceaseless clatter of the sewing-machines in an atmosphere so thick that it can be cut with a knife.  The machines are run by steam, and notwithstanding the great buckram fans overhead that revolve with a crackling noise the ceiling is so low and the air so hot as to be positively stifling to the initiated. There is the smell of dye from brown, blue, and black cloaks coupled with the still more offensive odor from the “English plaids”; along the pressing-table are the gas stoves where irons are heated and where the girls sponge and press collars and seams, each operation attended with a little cloud of steam and a stuffy, scorching smell that blows about and around the whizzing fans; clouds of lint from the textures in hand covers everything it constantly being inhaled by the sewers. Then, too, there is the smell of rancid machine oil; the overpowering exhalations from so many perspiring and unkempt persons and an occasional whiff from the six or seven toilets closets, all powerful facts of one might smell that must be smelled to be appreciated. The “good Jew” had all the windows open, but the place was so strong I almost fainted.</rs></p>
        <p>I have a seat in the middle of the room and a 35 cent Norfolk to make. <rs type="workEnvir" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">It is so dark that I can hardly see my stitches as I thread to sleeve hole with black muslin.</rs> The forewoman can’t see either till she takes the work over to the window to examine it, and returns with a gratifying, “<said who="forewoman" ana="female">Guess that it will do.</said>”</p>
        <p><rs type="workEnvir" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">We are so crowded along the line of tables that the girls are told to “take short threads,” and I duck my head every time the pale-faced, hollow-eyed girl at my left pulls her needle out, to escape being hit. She has only been able to make three 50 cent long cloaks in five days and says:</rs></p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">You won’t mind my taking long threads; will you, if I don’t hit you?</said>”</p>
        <p>I tell her to pull away and offer to fell the bottom hem on her cloak to which she agrees. <rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">She has on a cheap jersey waist, a calico skirt, and the little but of underwear that shows at her neck where she has opened her collar is as black almost as her jersey. Her shoes are broken and one of the uppers is mended with black thread. She lives with her folks and has “a lot of little brothers and sisters, but the ‘Q’ strikes have put them all out” so that she hasn’t bought anything for herself this year except a hat at the Fair.</rs></p>
        <p>“<said who="nellNelson" ana="female">Do you go to church?</said>” I ask.</p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">What’d I go to church for?</said>”</p>
        <p>“<said who="nellNeslon" ana="female">For the music and the sermon.</said>”</p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">I want a seat, though, and I’d rather ride down to the shop and back than pay 10 cents to get in the pew.</said>”</p>
        <p><rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">A poor little creature, bony and grimy, and wild-eyed as the “marchioness” goes down on her hands and knees and turns out the dust in the cracks of the floor with the eye of her needle.</rs></p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">I’m huntin’ for pins,</said>” she says, “<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">to fix on the braid.</said>”</p>
        <p>“<said who="nellNelson" ana="female">Doesn’t <persName>Zimmerman</persName> provide you with pins?</said>”</p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female">Indeed he doesn’t; nor with nothin’ else but fannin’ and what’s the good of fans in an oven?</said>”</p>
        <p>The child turns up the pins some of them bent, and puts them first in her mouth to straighten them and then in the bosom of her dress humming to herself, “Rock of Ages.” At the expiration of the hunt a new difficulty befalls her. The needle’s eye is stuffed as she says and in an effort to remove the filling off goes the head optic and all. Nobody has another to lend and I give her mine. <rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">She says she is <persName>Pat</persName> and the daughter of a Twelfth street teamster. Her mother is living and she and her brother “help the family along.”</rs></p>
        <p>“<said who="workingGirl" ana="female"><rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">Yes, I went to school and learned numbers and geography, but I can’t sew very well. The forelady says that’s why I don’t make more. I got $2.75 one week, but I don’t know how much I’ll earn this week. I used to be in the Fair and they gave me $2 runnin’—checks I didn’t like it there, because I never got home till 8 at night and the boys was guyin’ us all the time.</rs></said>”</p>
        <p>At noon time the girls crowded into the wash-room and those unable to reach the already wrining-wet towel that hung near the sink dried on their dresses. <rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">I saw a tall young German woman wash her arms and neck and shake off the water as well as she could with the palms of her hands before putting on her dress waist again.</rs> <rs type="wgDesc" ref="#ras">Another, a girl of 14, who wore a plaid skirt and an old velvet jacket, dried her hands on her underclothing.</rs> <rs type="workEnvir" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">The lunch the “good Jew” served consisted of a cup of black coffee that was neither nutritious nor fragrant, and minus cream and sugar, for which the girls paid 2 cents a cup. Then there were cuts of pie at 5 centseach, which delicacy, architecturally speaking, had two stories, substantially built, with a water-proof inner lining of fruit mucilage. The top crust had bubbled up in the baking till it was a warty as tripe, and tenacity of the under dough would have sufficed for hinging a cellar door. This is certainly not the lunch <persName>Rev. Mr. Gross</persName> referred to in his sermon, but it’s the only one the girls in the <orgName type="exposedCompany">Zimmerman factory</orgName> knew anything about.</rs></p>
        <p><rs type="workDesc" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">However profitable the menu may have been to the firm it was anguish to many of the hungry toilers unable to procure it. We girls who had no money to invest in the appetizing viands sat by, begging with our eyes and following with melting mouths every morsel on its way down the throats of our neighbors. One of us, a mite of a girl, wan-faced and hectic, who had been watching the mastication of a well-fed machine-hand, waited till the leathery strangle of peach-paste had almost disappeared and then asked to consumer to “give her the crust.”</rs></p>
        <p>When the well-fed party said “naw” the child called her a “dirty beggar” and laid her little head on her arm for a nap. I went out to buy a needle and some day when it rains and the wind is never weary I shall send in a bill for the 20 cents <persName>H. Zimmerman</persName> owes me on a cotton-back Norfolk. <rs type="livingCond" subtype="negative" ref="#ras">Only a half hour was allowed for the noon rest during which the girls washed and combed, trimmed their finger-nails with scissors, and talked, or went to sleep.</rs></p>
                    <p><rs type="workDesc" subtype="positive" ref="#ras">All hands were on deck at 7:30 in the morning, in which manner and the 5:30 hour of closing the Saturday half-hour was made good to the firm. Many of the girls told me they made ten cloaks a week which averaged 30 cents apiece. Work was good, the season covering 10 months of the year.</rs> A number of men at work on the long cloaks had chairs at the side of the girls and knew well enough personally I did not polish them for they were saturated with tobacco fumes and smelled a foul, sweaty, sickening odor.</p>
        <p>-<persName>Nell Nelson</persName></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
        
        