<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Section 3</title>
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago.</title>
                <author>
                    NELSON, Nell, pseud.
                </author>
                <editor>Rebecca Parker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Chicago, Barkley Pub. Co., <date when="1888">1888</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>139 p. 19 cm.
                            Microfilm. New Haven, Conn. : Research Publications, 
                            No. 3519    Inc.,1976 -- 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
<div type="section" n="3">
<head><list><item>A HARD DAY'S WORK FOR FORTY-ONE CENTS.</item> 
<item>LESS FORTUNATE WORKERS WHO EARNED ONLY ELEVEN CENTS</item>
<item>A SICK GIRL'S SAD STORY.</item>
<item>THE HOPELESS MISS WHO LONGED TO BE MARRIED.</item></list></head>
<p>At the N-R- Jersey Company I was told to apply at
the factory on West Washington street.
"Work is given out at 7:30 A.M.," the clerk informed me,
"and if you have any snap about you you can make a good
living." By way of getting the required snap I went home, ate
my dinner, and was in bed at 8 o'clock.
The next morning I resumed the rags of poverty and at 7
o'clock made my debut as a factory hand. I was one of 120
women, ranging in age from 15 to 60. The factory where the
jerseys are made is at the corner of W-- and U-- streets,
with elevator entrance in the rear and work-room on the fifth
story.
The girls began to arrive at 7 o'clock, and at every trip of
the elevator some twenty or more were carried up-stairs. I
took a chair in one of the machine rows, and for an hour did
nothing but watch the preparations for work in that human
hive. The room was 50 x 138, with an open unfinished roof,
and brick walls calcimined. Light was admitted from rear and
side windows. The pressmen had their boards and furnaces
at the south end of the room, where all the work was pressed
prior to being boxed and ticketed for the trade. At the ex-
<pb n="15"/>
treme opposite end was the cutting room, fenced in from the
rest, and between the two were the work-tables where the hundred odd girls stitched and finished the jerseys.
Along the brick wall were nails irregularly driven, on which
the girls hung their hats and wraps, dresses and collars.
Nearly every one took off their dress and waist, turned it inside
out, put it on a nail and put on a calico or old stuff shop suit.
A few took off their corsets and nearly all the machine hands
changed their shoes before work. On the stroke of 7:30 a bell
rang, the power was turned on, the machines began to buzz
like little saw-mills and the day's work had commenced.
Heads of brown, black, yellow and gray bent so nearr the flying shuttles that every minute I expected the bangs and fluffy
crimps would get caught in the machinery. The faces were
sad and so very, very pale that I shall never look at a jersey
again without seeing them. The average age may have been
23, but not less. There were girls of 17 and 18 and some
world-weary women past 50, all working for little more than
enough to keep body and soul together. The work circulated
in baskets - long chip hampers with stout handles - that held
a dozen, with room for five times that quantity. A great deal
of time was lost by the workers in getting the contents of the
basket examined, checked off on the ticket and the ticket
stamped. If it had been the last chance for life I don't believe
the girls would have worked any harder for salvation. Scarcely
a head was raised from machine or lap. Shoulders were bent
down, chests hollowed in, and faces drooped so low that I could
not begin to make a study of the "windows of the souls" before
me. At 8:40 the proprietor of the chair I was in asked me to
vacate, and I walked down through the narrow isles of sewing
women to the "forelady" and asked for work.
She asked me if I wanted to take a machine, but I expressed
a preference for finishing. I was given a number, a basket
with five jerseys to finish, and a chair beside a girl named
<pb n="16"/>
Hannah, who, being engaged by the day, was told to "show
me." Hannah had blond hair and talked with the brogue.
She gave me a needle as long as my engagement finger, and
the most meager instruction compatible with obedience. Fortunately I had my thimble, and crossing my knees I threaded
the gimlet-like needle with silk and proceeded to hook-and-eye
a jersey. Rembering the treachery of any shop clothes I ever
wore I filled the two hooks and eyes with sewing and after
testing them proceded to face the collar. I made poor work of
the bias band, for my needle was so coarse that it split the
satin. I told Hannah about my misery but she wisely said it
was no fault of hers, and went on with a $3-a-dozen lot she had
been doing two days and a-half. Thinking it would be a good
way to get acquainted with my neighbors I asked several for a
fine needle and at last exchanged the crow-bar Hannah had
given me for a fine cambric article. It worked better, and at
the end of two hours I had bound the arm-holes, faced the collar, tacked the front facings and the bustle piece, and put two
pairs of hooks and eyes in a black jersey. The dye was not
fast, neither was the wool, for my throat, ears, and nostrils
were tufted with black lint. I was African from the finger-
nails to the wrists. The front facings had to be trimmed off.
I had no scissors. Hannah was ungenerous with hers, and I
lost about fifteen cents worth of time borrowing the weapons.
At noon I had finished four jerseys and was so sore about the
neck and back that I could scarcely rise from the chair. I
began to scent hot tea, and looking about saw a big girl called
Emma brewing three pots of Japan over one of the press
furnaces. She had her front hair in curl papers and was
whistling "In the Sweet Bye and Bye." About thirty girls
went to her, each with her own cup, for a supply of tea. I
remarked to one passing my chair that her tea looked awfully
nice and asked where she got it.
"From Em. She makes it and we each pay two cents a week."
<pb n="17"/>
On the stroke of twelve the machine stopped and 120 tired
women stopped too for thirty minutes' rest, and the food that
could hardly be called refreshing. In the main it consisted of
brown bread and butter. In some parcels there was cold meat
and cake ; others had pie ; a few a bottle or canteen of milk,
cold tea or coffee, but I did not see a particle of fruit. One
little girl who had been stretching jerseys at two cents apiece
made a lunch on three Graham crackers and a piece of custard
pie, which she ate reading a paper-covered book. I counted
thirty-seven girls with a lunch of dry bread, fifteen with sandwiches, and ten who ate cold pancakes. Twenty-three girls
were without any luncheon whatever. During the intermission
the elevator stopped running and no one left the building but
myself. Less than ten minutes was spent over the wretched
meal. At one side of the west wall separated by a ten foot
pine partition, was the toilet room, containing an iron sink
with one faucet of running water. Here the girls crowded
like so many cattle, each with her bit of soap and grimy cotton
towel, to wash. Dress waists were loosened and neck, faces,
arms and hands lathered with soap and rinsed as the chance
permitted. There were three closets, unflushed, untidy, and
unwholesome. Set up against the wall in this enclosure, with
the faucet run through the partition, was a barrel of ice water
inscribed in big letters: "Two cents will be collected every
Saturday for ice water." Besides this luxury every hand pays
twelve cents a week for the use of the machine.
At one o'clock I finished my basket which I dragged to Tom
the book-keeper, who took my name and credited me with five
garments. No price had been put on the jerseys as they were
sampled goods, but the forelady thought they would go at
sixty cents a dozen, which meant twenty-five cents to my
credit.
I didn't get any more work till two o'clock, because the forelady was in the toilet-room having her bangs done up in paper.
<pb n="18"/>
She was a pretty woman, by the way, with a good face and a
shock of beautiful auburn hair. She had been in her position
for six years and was drawing a salary of $35 a week. The
girls had a good word for her generally, but she struck me as
being a woman without heart. At her appearance I was given
a basketful of jerseys to finish button-holes. I worked like a
Trojan for an hour, at the end of which I won the heart of a
little girl who sat at the end of my table facing the wall. She
had been sitting still so long that I called out and asked if she
were ill.
"No. I haven't any work."
Tired almost to exhaustion and as hot as a newly-built mustard plaster I was only too glad of a chance to transfer my
interests, but she declined. It was too hot to work; she was
going away soon, she said, and didn't care to do any more.
"When did I begin? Today. I worked in a box-factory,
but it was so dull I could not earn 16 cents a day. My mother
wants me to pay her $2.50 a week board, but how could I with
96 cents. This is no better. I came at 8 this morning, and I
have only made 11 cents. I am 21. Beaux? Yes, some.
I have one steady fellow, but I don't know if he will marry
me. I hope he will."
She told me he earned $75 a month as telegraph operator on
the board of trade ; that he was "steady as a steeple, and the
only fellow she ever loved."
I told her how to go about catching the prosperous telegrapher
and rehashed a recipe given me by no less a personage than
Mrs. John M. Sherwood, which I had never tried. She was
going to a picnic at Garfield park at 6 o'clock, and brought
over a 25-cent chocolate cake to show me. Then she loaned
me her scissors, told me good-by, and went home to dress , for
the fete.
Nothing of any importance occurred till someone passed the
news that a girl was sleeping in the closet. Half a dozen left
<pb n="19"/>
their machines to look at her, Hannah, my mentor, among
them.
"Oh, you just ought to see her fast asleep with her mouth
open." It was more than I could stand. I threw my button-holes in the basket and went to the toilet-room. Sure enough
there was the poor girl sitting in the dirty place, her head
resting against a folded apron, breathing in the foul air that
reeked with filth and disease. The walls of the closet were
black with pencil marks, the floor was strewn with lint and
thread, and the pale face of the sleeper looked ghastly in the
darkness. She had tied one end of a string to the latch and
the other to the drop chain.
"My dear child, you musn't sleep here. Are you sick?"
"Oh I am so sick."
Instantly there were a dozen willing hands to help her out
to a window where a chair was placed for her. We rubbed
her temples, chafed her hands, bathed her head, and got her
some lemons. After making her toilet she came over to my
table, and as I sewed away at my button-holes she told me
her story.
"Rose and I are only six months in this country. We came
from England with our brother and live on Carpenter street.
The climate doesn't agree with me and I am sick all the time.
At first we worked in Marshall Field's, and Rose and I made
fringe. We got $7 a week and were so happy. It was awful
nice there. We didn't have to pay for drinking water or anything ; there were lots of towels, whole cakes of soap, and oh,
it was so clean. We had a foreman over us, and he was as
good as a brother to us. Sometimes we let our money lay
and drew it in a pile; oh, such a lot it was! We put away
very much of it. But I got sick and all we 'ad saved went
for doctor and medicine. Then the work stopped. They
took our names though and promised to send for us in the fall.
For a while we worked in the box factory, but liked to starve.
<pb n="20"/>
Then we went to Ellinger's and made cloaks at 30 cents each, but it was so hard, and we couldn't please them no matter how we tried. We came here today, but its only a fit place to starve in. All the work they gave me was a dozen jersbys to button ; that's 11 cents a row; had two dozen holes to finish at 16 cents. Twenty-seven cents for the two of us! How canwe live on that?" and the child began to cry again.
By way of comforting her I took her name, promised to help her, and gave her my check for forty-one cents. She didn't think it would be honored, so I took it to the cashier myself and demanded pay as I was not coming back in the morning. "No ma'am," said Tom, "you don't get it. Come around on the 20th and I hunt you up." 
At 5:30 work ceased. Each girl had to sweep out her place, clean and oil the machine, and return her basket and check. I paid a nickel to have my corner swept, and finding it impossible to wash up sans towel and soap I got under my veil and rang the elevator. The pressers laughed and told me to try the stairs—five flights. Down I went. At the second I went into the salesroom to buy a jersey. One of the firm waited on me. His magnanimity was sublime. The identical black jersey that I had received 5 cents for finishing was offered to me at $2. I declined. By way of interest one hundred dozen garments are turned out of the factory every day in the year. As near as I could learn the salaries average $4 a week, but plenty of grown women are not allowed to earn over 28 cents a day.
Work begins at 7:30 A.M. and 12:30 P.M. Anyone five minutes late working on time is fined an hour's pay, and for the loss of an hour the pay of half a day is knocked off. Piece-workers who are late are kept idle from one to three hours. A girl who loses her ticket forfeits pay for the entire lot, not withstanding the entry is on the books of the firm.
</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>



