<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:id="WSGC15">Section 15</title><!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each book chapter --><!-- RJP: each section will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and section number (add  a zero in front of early sections so we have consistent format with sections that will be double digits). For example: the first section in the Barkley text will be xml:id="WSGC01" -->
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --> 
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-06">2015-11-06</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                        <author>NELSON, Nell, pseud.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Barkley Pub. Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                        <publisher>Research Publications No. 3519 Inc.</publisher>
                        <date when="1976">1976</date>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
                        <availability>
                            <p>139 p. 19 cm. Microfilm. 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>PLACES WHERE VIRTUE COUNTS FOR NOTHING AND IS NOT TOLERATED BY THE EMPLOYER.</item>
                        <item>BODY AND SOUL MUST BE GIVEN UP TO THE SCOUNDRELS, OR THE EMPLOYE LOSES HER SITUATION.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="sectionBody">
                    <pb n="100"/>
                    <p>"Do you want to visit a manufacturing establishment, generally held in high repute, where a girl's tenure of place depends
                        upon the degrading concessions she may be induced to make
                        to her employer?"
                        The question was put to a reporter for the Times by Inspector
                        G. R. of the health department. They had just formed a
                        temporary copartnership under the name and style of "we"
                        to make a thorough examination of the hells and holes where
                        human beings hive, delve, and thrive or die under the guise of
                        "employes."
                        "Well, I'll tell you the story and I know it to be true, and
                        so does my wife. A girl of good development and modest
                        demeanor had for some time been employed in book-bindery
                        and had become fairly well skilled. One afternoon she turned
                        in, as the result of her day's work, four books. The foreman
                        complained that the work was imperfect - in fact, that the
                        books were spoiled, and told the girl she must pay for them.
                        She asked for particulars but could get little satisfaction. She
                        became indignant and was thrust aside. Remembering that
                        other mouths than hers were awaiting the food her scanty
                        earnings must purchase she pleaded first for justice and then
                        for mercy.
                        "'You quit work with the rest at 6 o'clock,' said the foreman. 'Come back fifteen minutes later and perhaps I may
                        <pb n="101"/>
                        straighten out your account so that you will lose nothing'
                        The girl, hesitating between hope and fear, crossed the bridge
                        as if to go homeward, and then returned to the office. The
                        foreman was at the door, welcomed her within, and turned the
                        key. He assured her he had helped many of the girls in the
                        employ of the firm to balance their accounts after business
                        hours. Be that as it may, he had made a grave miscalculation
                        in this case, and in less seconds than it takes to tell it he was
                        glad he hadn't lost the key to the door. The girl came directly
                        to my house, told her story, and never returned to the tiger's
                        lair. Her case is but one of many, and if she adheres to her
                        present decision it will be the particular one of the many before the firm and the foreman hear the last of it. Now come
                        with me and we'll take a trip through the binderies and printing establishments, and before we get through I'll show you
                        the fiend who endeavored to ruin this young girl."
                        Our first visit of inspection was made to the five-story and
                        basement building, on Monroe street, occupied by the J. M.
                        company, printers, binders and lithographers. On the main
                        floor the superintendent gave us yellow tickets, each guaranteeing a single ride in a freight elevator at the rear to the fifth
                        floor. "You must walk down," he added, encouragingly.
                        To the fifth floor we went, and to all appearance arrived unannounced as the foreman was frank. A girl acknowledged she
                        was but 14 years old and worked ten hours a day, and the
                        closets were in bad condition. Groping our way down a dark
                        and narrow stairway, we learned that the foreman had been
                        called to the office.
                        "How old are you?" asked the inspector of a boy feeding a press.
                        "Seventeen," he replied, winking at a companion when the
                        inspector's back was turned, as much as to say he knew his
                        business. Apparently he was about 13, and probably that was
                        his age, as it was admitted that four boys and two girls under
                        legal age were regularly employed.
                        <pb n="102"/>
                        Save as to ill-kept closets on the three upper floors and a
                        scarcity even of that undesirable kind, the sanitary condition
                        of the premises is fair, light and ventilation being abundant.
                        Of the 305 employes 220 are males and eighty-five are females.
                        The wages of the latter range from $3 to $10 a week, averaging about $5, and the male average is $12.50.
                        "Aren't you from The Times?" asked one of the forewomen in a quizzical way.
                        "Do I look like a woman?"
                        "You might be 'Nell Nelson' disguised in pants for all I
                        know. But I don't care if you are; I'll tell you all I know."
                        "Facilis descensus avemi" doesn't apply to going downstairs in this factory, because it isn't easy to get down, and the
                        lower you get - that is to say, the nearer you approach the
                        manager's desk - the more heavenly the situation. Ceilings
                        rise in gradation and stairways expand until Mr. M's handsome office is reached.
                        "The health department claims that there should be one
                        closet for every twenty employes," said the inspector.
                        "But ours are only for use in case of emergency," replied
                        Mr. M. "We didn't put them in for the accommodation of
                        our help, and they are not expected to visit them during working hours; their time belongs to us. It is work that we want
                        from them."
                        This was said partly in self-defense and partly in repartee,
                        but even with apologetic explanation it grates harshly on the
                        ear. By an expenditure of a few hundred dollars, the health,
                        safety and comfort of 300 persons employed by a firm having
                        hundreds of thousands of dollars invested could be assured.
                        And at the same time it must be admitted that this is one of
                        the very best regulated establishments of the kind in Chicago.
                        The story told by the inspector did not relate to the J. M.
                        company.</p><!-- each paragraph represented in the text will get its own <p> element -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>    
