<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Section 2</title>
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago.</title>
                <author>
                    NELSON, Nell, pseud.
                </author>
                <editor>Rebecca Parker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Chicago, Barkley Pub. Co., <date when="1888">1888</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>139 p. 19 cm.
                            Microfilm. New Haven, Conn. : Research Publications, 
                            No. 3519    Inc.,1976 -- 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
<div type="section" n="2">
<head><list><item>PUT THROUGH AN IMPUDENT CROSS-EXAMINATION TO GET TO SEW CLOAKS AT FIFTY CENTS EACH.</item> 
<item>MAKING PANTS AND SHIRTS AT SEVENTY-FIVE CENTS A DOZEN AND FIND YOUR OWN THREAD.</item></list></head>
<p>At R--- &amp; Co’s and R--- Bros. I applied for work and
was told to report in the morning to sew on cloaks.
The manager in S’s on Market street wanted hands and
offered to engage me at once. I was most impudently catechised, some seven inquiries requiring as many false statements.
What was my name, place of residence, last position, amount
of wages received, state of my health, nativity, married or
<pb n="13"/>
single - to which I answered "neither." Here was a dilemma.
"Oh, yes, widow? " and an inordinate ha! ha!
"Yes."
"Grass widow, eh?" with a sneer.
"How much do you pay for cloaks", I asked, tired of the ordeal.
"Fifty c«nts each."
It was enough and I left the creature still anxious to solve
the widow question.
By the time I reached L’s on Market street, I was in a reckless frame of mind.
"Is there any work for a good sewer?" I asked the girl in
the office.
"Yes, plenty. John give her some pants."
John had eyes the color of calico, and a complexion like an
immature tomato. He led the way to the cottonades, which
were cut, trimmed, and tied up in bundles of a dozen garments
each.
"Here’s a sample," holding up a pair of overalls of brown
cottonade. " The work is cut out, but you will have to do
everything yourself. I want you to make the fly extra strong
and press the bottoms. We pay 75 cents a dozen and you find
your own thread. * ’
"Seventy-five cents for a dozen of these pants and find my
own thread?"
"Yes, or I’ll give you 80 cents a dozen and give you linen
thread if you sew the buttons on fast.
"No, I guess, I won’t take the pants. What other work
have you?"
"Here are cheviot shirts, if you'd rather. Gusset the tail
here and the sleeves, stay the bosom and arm-holes, and make
the collar and wristbands extra strong. These pay 75 cents a
dozen." He offered to give me three on trial. The thread
cost 5 cents, car-fare 10 cents, and I should have left 3 cents
after the job.
<pb n="14"/>
John said: "That’s so, but I can’t help it. If the work is
satisfactory you can have a six-dozen lot."
It was very good for John to sympathize with me, but I
thanked him and said I would look a little further.</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
