<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:id="WSGC19">Section 19</title><!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each book chapter --><!-- RJP: each section will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and section number (add  a zero in front of early sections so we have consistent format with sections that will be double digits). For example: the first section in the Barkley text will be xml:id="WSGC01" -->
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --> 
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-06">2015-11-06</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                        <author>NELSON, Nell, pseud.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Barkley Pub. Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                        <publisher>Research Publications No. 3519 Inc.</publisher>
                        <date when="1976">1976</date>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
                        <availability>
                            <p>139 p. 19 cm. Microfilm. 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>EATING POOR CRACKERS AND WORKING FOR TWO MONTHS IN ORDER TO GET A PAIR OF SHOES.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="sectionBody">
                    <pb n="31"/>
                    <p>One of the chance acquaintances I made at the jersey factory worked three days for J--- S---- &amp; C, Market street,
                        receiving 65 cents for her labors about ten days after leaving.
                        One-third of 65 cents is 21 2/3 cents.
                        That is the way S---- &amp; Co. solve the problem; but the
                        question is one that capital, Christianity, and civilization are
                        invited to analyze.
                        "Don't never go to S----'s," the little girl said, "it's an awful
                        place."
                        On Saturday I tumbled out of bed at 6 A.M. and donned
                        my factory clothes. On the way down-town the street-car met
                        with an eight-minute obstruction in the shape of a load of
                        bricks, and when I reached the manufacturing establishment of
                        J--- S---- &amp; C it was 8:32 o'clock. The elevator took me
                        up one story and I was told to "get out." I told the boy at
                        the rope that I wished to go up to the work room.
                        "You're too late," he said. "Have to take the freight ele-
                        vator down at the back of the store."
                        Down I walked as directed past long tables, that towered
                        with long cloaks, dolmans, ulsters, jackets, and short wraps;
                        past two or three busy unobserving clerks, past a pair of forbidding-gooking men who glared at me from under their black
                        hats and blacker brows; past an earthen-gray-stringy crash
                        towel that waved at half-mast over a dirty wash-basin, past a
                        tier of closets that emitted a stifling odor, and on down to the
                        packing-room. I waited for a big lusty packer to finish pummelling the mischievous little Swede who ran the elevator and
                        <pb n="32"/>
                        was carried up to the top floor with a box of cloth. When the
                        car landed I found myself at the extreme end of a room 50x80
                        feet, in an enclosure of wire-fence, packing-boxes, and cutting-
                        boards - beyond and between which I could see perhaps two
                        hundred persons, mostly women, bent over machines, and
                        working as only slaves ever work. The thundering noise made
                        by the machinery deadened every other sound, even that made
                        by the cutters as they ran their heavy shears through the satin
                        and muslin trimmings. Sixteen persons passed me - men in
                        undershirts, trousers and slippers, with work in their hands;
                        men in business suits with work in their brains; girls of 13 in
                        rags and death-like pallor, with work in their arms; older and
                        paler girls and still older and paler women, some with white
                        hair and spectacles, carrying work to be pressed, examined,
                        altered or checked. Nobody noticing me, I asked a pretty
                        little girl who was cutting a bolt of satin into cuff-lining to
                        direct me to the forewoman and was told to go and sit down
                        till she came. I had hardly arranged myself on an empty box
                        when a playful young man capsized my throne and spilled
                        me in a heap of unmade cloaks. My first impulse was for revenge, but remembering that I was a poor girl looking for work
                        I contented myself by petting my damaged left knee and right
                        elbow. While mentally photographing the miserable, little,
                        bullet-headed sapling who caused my trouble, a young woman
                        brought me a chair and placed it in a corner, which convenient
                        spot happened to be off a narrow passage leading to the work-
                        room proper. My nose was not long in seeing a row of closets
                        that walled the south side of the passageway. Overhead was
                        a pasteboard sign with "No admission to the work-room"
                        printed in large, black letters. There was no place beyond
                        where I could sit or stand without being in the way unless
                        I went back into the freight elevator, so I resolved to stick it
                        out.
                        For almost two hours I sat in the dark, filthly place with a
                        <pb n="33"/>
                        handkerchief over my mouth and nose waiting for the fore-
                        woman to come and admit me to the shop. I watched the poor
                        girls pass and repass, their broken shoes slipping up and down
                        with every step, and their ragged skirts often catching new
                        gaps from the nails of the packing boxes. Just as I was 
                        beginning to get myself in a state of passivity, as prescribed by
                        Mrs. Eddy, and was combatting the foul smell of the closets
                        with the wholesome healthy atmosphere of South Park, something in my head seemed to give way, and the whole factory
                        turned into a colossal whirligig. The big goose of the presser
                        and the little irons of the press girls began to play tag, and
                        machines, operators, finishers, wire-forms, cutters, examiners,
                        messengers, models, forewomen, teachers and firm, all joined
                        in the merry go round. To escape being knocked in the head
                        by a two-story press-board I clutched a little stitcher who said:
                        "You an't sick, is you?"
                        I guessed I was. Bringing me a tin cup full of water, she
                        departed saying: "She'd be docked if she didn't go."
                        An old man with grey hair and glasses showed me to the
                        freight elevator and I was let down to the second story. When
                        I reached the staircase I sat down on the top step to recover.
                        A portly man with a straw hat, full beard, broad shoulders,
                        and a suit of mixed goods, mistaking me for a tramp, came
                        out from the stock and informed me that "no peddlers are
                        allowed on the premises. Move off."
                        I moved off determined to return another day.
                    </p><!-- each paragraph represented in the text will get its own <p> element -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>      