<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" xml:id="WSGC19">Section 19</title><!-- RJP: I am keeping these quotes empty here so that oXygen fires an error reminding editors to make sure the xml:id is changed according to each book chapter --><!-- RJP: each section will have its own identifier and this is where it is being defined... the identifier should include the source and section number (add  a zero in front of early sections so we have consistent format with sections that will be double digits). For example: the first section in the Barkley text will be xml:id="WSGC01" -->
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --> 
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:
               <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-11-06">2015-11-06</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="s">The White Slave Girls of Chicago</title>
                        <author>NELSON, Nell, pseud.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Barkley Pub. Co.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                        <publisher>Research Publications No. 3519 Inc.</publisher>
                        <date when="1976">1976</date>
                        <pubPlace>New Haven, Connecticut</pubPlace>
                        <availability>
                            <p>139 p. 19 cm. Microfilm. 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>A YOUNG WIDOW ATTEMPTS TO SUPPORT HERSELF AND CHILD BY MAKING OVERALLS.</item>
                        <item>STARVATION STARING HER IN THE FACE, SHE SOLD HER HONOR RATHER THAN PART FROM HER BABY.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="sectionBody">
                    <p>One of the white slaves of Chicago stood in the prisoner's
                        dock at the armory police court yesterday, moaning piteously.
                        She was young and her face was pretty. The big policeman
                        who stood at her side said he had arrested her for soliciting
                        men upon the street. She was booked as Kitty Kelly. The
                        frail, unfortunate girl brushed away her tears and told a story
                        that went straight to the heart of every man in the crowded
                        court-room. She was a white slave and might have worn
                        away her frail life sewing that her character should remain
                        pure and unsullied, but the grinning skeleton of starvation
                        haunted her by day and night, and in desperation she sold herself to the tempter. She w'as pale and thin and fierce hunger
                        had left marks upon her young face.
                        "Oh, judge, I never did such a thing before! I never did
                        it before! For God's sake have pity on me!" and she wrung
                        her hands in agony and sobbed convulsively.
                        "Nonsense," said the justice, trying to be stern. "You all
                        say that."
                        "My baby! my baby! Oh what will become of her? For
                        mercy's sake don't fine me! I have no money, not a cent.
                        Oh have mercy. I never was out before, surely I never was!"
                        The big justice looked inquiringly at the big officer and the
                        big officer with a touch of emotion in his voice, said:
                        <pb n="118"/>
                        "I never saw her before, your honor."
                        "Will you promise to keep off the street?"
                        "I can't, no I can't promise you that. God knows I would
                        if I could. But when I see my baby starving and there is no
                        other way to find food for her, what else can I do?" and the
                        wretched little woman sobbed as if her heart was breaking.
                        The justice looked stern.
                        "Oh sir," she sobbed, "if you only knew the misery and
                        sorrow, the despair and degradation to which I have been
                        humiliated, you might pity me. I was young when I
                        was married. For a while I was so happy. Then my
                        husband sickened and died. That was but little more
                        than a year ago. Soon after my baby was born. I had
                        no friends and no money. I was alone in this great city and
                        no one to help me or even to give me a bit of advice. Vainly
                        I sought for work. I could not go into service and take my
                        baby with me, and I could not bear the thought of parting
                        from it. At last I found employment in a factory. There I
                        made overalls and toiled from morning until night, week in
                        and week out. But work as hard as I could, I could only
                        earn four dollars a week. Baby took sick and I had to pay
                        for a doctor and medicine and it cost more than I could make."
                        Starvation or a life of shame, she said, were the only two
                        courses she could see, and for the baby's sake she chose shame.
                        But such a life was full of horror for her, and, disgusted and
                        ashamed, she went back to the old grinding toil. Striving
                        with all her power to earn an honest livelihood she again saw
                        that the struggle was too much, and two weeks ago she saw
                        that her baby must starve unless she found something else.
                        She went upon the street and was placed in the station. She
                        was moaning and sobbing, and though imprisonment seemed
                        probable, she only thought of her little girl.
                        "It was all because of my baby. She is my all and I can't
                        send her to the Home for the Friendless. I worked hard for
                        <pb n="119"/>
                        her but we could not live with only four dollars a week.
                        What could I do? I could not beg enough for both. Oh, I
                        was driven to it, and after I had sunk once, I could get nothing
                        else than the factory because I had no one who would give me
                        a letter of recommendation. It was starvation for my baby,
                        or shame."
                        "But many I know manage to live on less than four dollars
                        a week," said the magistrate.
                        "Yes, one person might; but I can't feed, clothe, and shelter my baby and myself for that. Must I lose my baby
                        because a woman cannot earn more than enough in Chicago
                        to give herself black bread and a garret?"
                        She claimed that she was not on the downward path of her
                        own volition, and that if she could support herself and child
                        she would leave her life of shame. She was fined twenty-five
                        dollars, but execution was staid during good behavior. If
                        arrested again she will be given fifty days at the bridewell.
                        She left the court-room weeping and moaning.
                        "What will become of my baby," she cried, "if I am
                        brought here and have to be imprisoned for so long?"</p><!-- each paragraph represented in the text will get its own <p> element -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


