<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a">Section 23</title>
                <title level="m">The White Slave Girls of Chicago.</title>
                <author>
                    NELSON, Nell, pseud.
                </author>
                <editor>Rebecca Parker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Chicago, Barkley Pub. Co., <date when="1888">1888</date>.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>139 p. 19 cm.
                            Microfilm. New Haven, Conn. : Research Publications, 
                            No. 3519    Inc.,1976 -- 35mm -- (History of Women ; 3519)</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
<div type="section" n="23">
<pb n="134"/>
<head><list><item>A PROPOSITION OF MARRIAGE TO A PRETTY AND BRAINY SEAMSTRESS IS TAKEN UNDER CONSIDERATION.</item>
<item>CORRECTING AN ERRONEOUS IMPRESSION THAT NELL NELSON'S ARTICLES ARE NOT FOUNDED ON
FACT.</item></list></head>
<p>Nothing short of a Philadelphia lawyer, a Chicago health
officer, a proprietor or a "devil-chaser" that hits the spot once
in a thousand times could, without a guide, explore the labyrinth that is known as H. S. &amp; Co.'s paper-box manufactory,
on R--- street. It occupies only the three upper floors of a
four-story building, but the stairways are so dark and narrow
that one must grope his way from somewhere to a suppositious somewhere else, which resembles nowhere when he gets
there, because the rooms are so overcrowded with material that
one employe cannot in many instances see her nearest neighbor
two yards away.
Of the 120 employes, ten are mere girls, who get from $2 to
$3 a week, while the others receive from $5 to $7.50. Each
girl keeps her own account-book, and at the request of the
proprietor submitted it to inspection. It showed the exact
amount the owner had been paid each week for many weeks.
One advantage of working in this stuffy place is that there is
work the year around.
Mr. S. had the usual explanation to make as to the employment of young boys and girls and no doubt made it truthfully.
Their parents needed their assistance and would sign any
<pb n="135"/>
sort of certificate as to age, and supplement it with personal
solicitation asking employment as a charity. In extreme cases
he negotiated a compromise with his judgment, as most manufacturers do, and gave the child employment
"What kind of work do you do?" A group of five boys
was asked at the noon hour.	
"All but him binds packages; he glues."
"How old are you?"
"We's pretty old and gettin' older all de time."
The closets are separate and fairly decent.
The ventilation is bad.
"I am a man of few words and you have no time to lose, so
I will proceed direct to business. Do you want to get married?"
The proposition was made by a Times reporter to an attractive young woman employed as a seamstress in a custom shop
on the fourth floor of S. N's building on the southwest corner
of W. and H. streets on the North side.
The reporter had seen the young woman but once before,
and after that meeting the following paragraph was printed in
The Times on August 13:
"An intelligent trio, evidently good friends, gathered in a
corner, and between bites talked freely. One was a thorough
American, lived on May street, and walked back and forth
from her work, the round distance being fully three miles. Another, whose yellow hair bespoke an ancestry from the region
of the midnight sun, walked about the same distance. Many an
avenue belle would give half her inheritance, for the form, face
and figure, to say nothing of the brains of this every-day sewing girl, wearing out her young life for $6 a week. But she
made no complaints. Independence more than compensated
her for the hardships of the weary day."
Usually "popping the question" is a trying ordeal to a man,
even when none but the two parties most interested are present.
<pb n="136"/>
What must it have been in this case when half a score of pairs
of bright eyes were gazing in astonishment and as many ears
were trained to catch every syllable? Usually, too, the woman
addressed is very much embarrassed, or seems to be. This one
was not. With a musical laugh followed by an interrogation
point, she awaited further developments, Emma, the American
girl, rallying her good-naturedly the while
"You know you want to get married," said Emma. "Why
don't you say yes?"
Not wishing to prolong the agony beyond the proper limit
the reporter produced the following letter:
Chicago, Aug. 13. - To the Editor: One who reads your articles
with more than passing interest, and who deeply sympathizes with the
cause of honest labor, has sufficient romance in his "make-up" to perform his part in assisting the young lady of brains referred to, and if
honesty of purpose, good bringing up, etc., accompany the brains, the
lady can find at the head of an honest, temperate, working-man's home
a peace and comfort not found in "wearing out her young life" in pursuit of a mere existence. This is in good faith, and any acknowledgment
of it will call forth - confidentially, of course - the name and address of
the writer.
It was interesting to watch the play of the girl's features as
she read the letter. At first curiosity was uppermost; then
came an expression of sadness as the passages expressing sympathy for honest labor were reached, and finally a slight flush
and a smile as she read the offering clause.
"Will you accept?"
"Don't you do it at once," said Emma, tantalizingly.
"Keep him waiting for a while till he gets real anxious."
"Who is the writer?" asked the girl to whom the letter referred. " He must live where girls are scarce."
"The letter is dated and postmarked 'Chicago.'"
"Well, I should like to see the writer. It takes something
more than temperance and honesty to make a man. I shall
not embrace the present opportunity to answer."
<pb n="137"/>
"Nor the man either?"
"Nor the man either," she said with a merry laugh as she
caught the gentler force of the play upon the words.
"Will you answer the letter?"
"I will take it under advisement, as politicians say"
"If you don't accept turn the letter over to me," chimed in
Emma. And then noticing the grounds in her coffee she
added: "Can you tell fortunes?"
Everybody on the Times tells fortunes, and of course the
visitor could. "This man is a blonde, tall, somewhat portly,
and a widower with three children," he began.
"Can't you make it five? She just dotes on children. If
she won't take him I'll be No. 2 and run the chance. Can't
you induce him to call here? We are tailoresses here, but
when we appear upon the street we are ---"
"Well, what are we then?" asked the girl with the light
hair.
"Why, then - then we are ourselves. What time is it?"
"Seventeen minutes to 1 o'clock."
"Then we have just two minutes to live," and the trio
began preparations for renewing their toil after the forty-five
minutes allowed for lunch. The author of the letter might
wait a long time before finding a brighter or better head for
his household than this girl whose ancestors worshipped Thor
and Woden.
"Nell Nelson," in a recent article in the Times, described
the trousers manufactory of K. B. O., on S. street near Division,
as a two-story and basement frame, the stories being used for girls
and the basement for horses. This is true as to the girls, and
only the qualifying expression "in part" is needed to make it
fit the basement, the rear portion of it being used for stabling,
with all that the word implies. Miss Nelson, it will be remembered, worked an afternoon at this place, making a pair of
trousers for 5 cents, and after relating her experience quoted
<pb n="138"/>
the words of a young woman who sat at the same table and
who complained that the shop was cold.
Of course the girl had no idea that her language was to
appear in print and spoke carelessly. But Mr. O. was displeased
and the girl was promptly discharged from his employ. The
Knights of Labor were promptly notified and so was the Times.
Yesterday a reporter was instructed to investigate the case and
if the facts were as reported to assure the girl, whose name is
Mary Kane, that the Times would secure for her another and
better position.
Mr. O. was found on the upper floor of his shop and pretty
mad yet, though he had had a week to cool off in. But he
soon quieted down, led the way to the office in the basement,
and sent for Foreman M. Then the Times article was read
and liberally commented on, M. doing most of the talking
because he could turn sharp corners in English a trifle more
skillfully than O.
"Mary Kane has left, but she wasn't exactly discharged,"
said O. "If the rooms are cold in winter why didn't she complain to me instead of 'Nell Nelson?' I know they are cold
at times, but not for half a day. I frequently feel chilly myself in the early morning. I know the house is not a model;
It was built directly after the fire and needs many improvements. Why didn't Mary Kane complain to me?"
"She preferred no charges against you. In a casual way
she stated to a table-mate that the shop was cold in winter as
you now acknowledge. The situation is this: If you have
discharged Mary Kane because of a chance word, The Times
will see to it that she immediately secures a situation in some
other shop."
After a few moments Mr. O. said the girl was one of the best
in his employ, that nothing could be said against her work or
her character, and he would be willing to take her back.
"You may tell Mary K. she may come back to work if she
<pb n="139"/>
wishes to. I don't want to do anybody any injustice. All I
had against her in all the years she worked for me was that
remark about my shop being cold."
"But I may not see her, as she is away from home"
"Well, just go over and tell her mother that it's all right
and Mary can go to work when she likes."
It was the work of an hour, but no bull-dozing or pleading was
used. The case was squarely discussed on its merits, and if
Mary K., whom all the neighbors, including O. himself, say is
a steady, industrious, and thoroughly deserving girl, walks into
the shop to-day she can have her old seat and at the same time
the consciousness that she has not compromised herself or been
compromised in the least. Both O. and M. will be glad to
welcome her back, which is much to their credit.</p>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
