<div type="section" n="8">
<head><list><item>"THE TIMES'" LADY REPORTER, IN THE GUISE OF A FACTORY BONDWOMAN, IS INSULTED BY A SCOUNDREL.</item>
<item>ACCOSTED BY A WELL-DRESSED BRUTE WHO TRIES TO THRUST HIS BLIGHTING FRIENDSHIP ON HER.</item></list></head>
On Thursday morning when I started to renew my factory
life I discovered after getting on a South-side car that I did
not have a cent in my pocket. In putting on my shop-girl
disguise I had left my purse at home. When the conductor
asked for the fare I had none to give him. It was very hot,
<pb n="45"/>
the clouds threatened rain, and the shop was at so great a
distance that I did not feel as if I could walk. I concluded to
throw myself on the generosity of the conductor, and I told
him I had forgotten my purse. He looked ugly and told me
to get off. Just as he placed his whistle to his lips to signal
the gripman to stop a distinguished, well-dressed man paid
my fare. I thanked him for his courtesy and told him if he
would give me his card I would send him the money he had
so kindly paid.
He smiled and said: "A mere bagatelle, miss, and not
worth mentioning."
At Eighteenth street I left the car to go to a vestmaker's
place at 2155 Archer avenue. I was crossing the three points
where State and Nineteenth streets intersect, when who should
come abreast but my benefactor. Instead of raising his hat,
he jauntily cocked his left eye and came so close to me that
the sleeve of my "never rip" jersey was pressed against the
waist-line of his light grey suit.
"Aha, here we are again!"
Although I distinctly heard every word of his remark, I
said: I beg your pardon," with as much of the Newport
chill as I could affect.
"Come, come, now," he said with increasing gayety, moving
his waist-band still closer to my jersey.
"Oh, you are the gentleman to whom I am indebted for
car-fare. You want your money I suppose; if you will give me
your card I will write you an order."
"Do you work in this neighborhood?"
"No sir."
"Where, then?"
"No place." 
"Where are you going?"
"For work."
"What kind?"
<pb n="46"/>
"Any kind. May I have your card? I am in something of
a hurry."
"Mayn't I have yours?" he asked.
"Certainly; I haven't my case, but if you will lend me a
pencil I will write you one."
"With pleasure, my dear."
"You are mistaken, sir. That is not my name."
"Ha, ha, ha! I see you are a little mischievous, but for all
that you are my dear, producing three inches of Faber.
"A card, please."
"Bless me, I had forgotten," and the natty sack-coat was
ransacked for a suitable card.
"Ah, here - this will do, I hope, in lieu of something more
conventional," carefully placing on my sewing box a small
card with the address down. I reversed the pasteboard and
read on the back:
Dr. Charles G— S—.
Office hours—
Residence— 
"Dr. Smith ! I know him quite well."
Oh, you do, eh?" in a tone that left no doubt that his
stock in me had dropped. I wrote:
Reporter.
THE TIMES.
and handed it to my companion who read it with eyes that
<pb n="47"/>
seemed to have been wired open. While he crushed the doctor's card in his left hand, his right pulled out a splendid gold
watch, and with a most abrupt "didn't think it was so late,
have an engagement at 9:45," was off with more alacrity than
is conducive to grace. I looked after him admiring the cut of
his coat, the swing of his trousers, the polish of his shoes, and
the magnificent carriage of head and shoulders, and thought:
"May the Lord deliver us working girls."
I also thought that I should like to meet my car friend when
I had my suffocating veil off and my good clothes on. Won't
Dr. S. inveigle him to his State street office and present me?
I want to give him back his nickel and lead pencil.
When I reached the shop at 2155 Archer avenue the tailor
told me he only wanted one vestmaker and had hired her two
hours ago. I then went over on Cottage Grove avenue, borrowed twenty-five cents from my dressmaker, and rode down
to Lake street to get work in a feather-duster factory. There
may have been work, but there was no elevator and I was too
hot and tired to go up five flights of stairs to look for it. I
chose a cigar factory on Randolph, near Dearborn street, with
but three pairs of stairs to climb, and learned in the salesroom
that they had all the help they needed. I tried G., across the
street, who had no work, but enough goodness of heart to give
me a chair and a letter to two cigarmakers of his nationality.
I went to see F. G. on Clark street. He asked me if I could
"strip" and I told him I could. When he wanted to know
where I had worked I owned up that I didn't know anything
at all about the business, but was anxious to learn and get
work. He didn't know "how a sewing-girl would do at
'fillers,' but you might go and talk with some of the help,
for you may not be satisfied to try even."
He showed me the way across the hall to an empty room.
The floor was littered with rags and paper and the dust was
heavy on the walls and wood-work, and in one corner was a
<pb n="48"/>
good-sized ash-pile. G. rapped for entrance, but there was so
much noise within that the door remained fast. When the
Spaniard left me I turned the knob and came upon a big boy
who was tickling his colaborers. The girls were flying around
the empty room and their pursuer had both screeching. The
fun came to a stop the moment I went in, and the young people gladly told me all I cared to know about the business.
All they did was to "strip" - just pull the stem or mid-rib
from the leaf and put it in a "book-filler.'' I could get $4 a
week and steady work and the next year $6. My informant,
a little girl of fifteen years, has been in the shop two years and
earned $6.50 a week. She told me she was the oldest hand in
the shop; that she could "strip" as fast as a man, and put
the ribbon bands about the box before they were boxed.
At 12:45 o'clock I went into the shop and was given a chair
in front of a barrel filled with bunches of tobacco called
"hands" and lined with gunny-cloth. There was a little tin
pail of brown water for wetting I don't know what near my
chair, and on the other side a pine board three feet long and
sixteen inches wide. When the tobacco leaves were stripped
and laid on the board it was dubbed a "book filler" and carried off to the next room. In the shop with us were some
eighteen men or more rolling the "fillers," putting on the
wrappers, shaping the cigars with a broad knife, and securing
the ends. Along the table some of the men were smoking
and others chewing some with their hats on, and all in their
shirt-sleeves. They were negroes, Swedes, a Chinaman,
Germans, and Spaniards, whose influence on the lives of the
young girls, while not really harmful, could hardly be called
beneficial. I stripped leaves enough to enable me to take in
the social condition of the inmates, the bad light, impure
atmosphere, the choking smell of tobacco, and the photographs
and prints cut from sensational papers that were tacked on the
smoke-stained walls.
<pb n="49"/>
From the cigar factory I went to the E. U. Co. on Fifth
avenue, and sat for half an hour while the forewoman scolded
a pale-faced girl who wore mourning. She had brought back
a dozen chemises for which the house paid two dollars, but the
work was soiled in the making - machine oil having wet the
cotton - and the forewoman refused to take it.
"What shall I do?" she asked the woman, with a voice as
sad as her face.
‘‘What does anybody do with dirty things? You will
either have to pay for laundering the garments or rip out the
greasy sewing and stitch with clean thread."
Then the girl was left alone by the manager, who went up
to the other end of the counter to get trimmings for six dozen
chemises that a tall young Swede girl was waiting for. The
forewoman wore a blue dress of plaid design, with a Marseilles
vest buttoned in it, and of seven rings on her left hand six
were set with what appeared to be diamonds. She had jewels
at her chin and in her ears and hair. She measured off the
lace edging and the tape and insertion and gave minute directions about fullness and the finish. The six dozen garments
were bundled up by Mr. H., the proprietor, and the elevator
carried her and her load to the pavement below. The seamstress told me she lived at home, and with the help of her
mother made twelve dollars a week.
"It is very hard work though," she said, for we sew day
and night. I had rather do it than work down in a shop, for
I have more self-respect. All the girls are not good and very
few are in a position to go with respectable people. They go
with bad company and their language is bad. Sometimes in
the winter they dance till daylight and go from the hall to the
shop. I don't blame them. The life of a girl wbo has nothing to depend on but her needle is at best a hard one. Still I
don't like to be with a crowd of factory girls if I can help it.
The manager and superintendent are obliged to be strict, but
<pb n="50"/>
very seldom make any distinction in the treatment of a nice
girl and one who is not so nice. I don't think I can tell you
how many ways there are to insult a girl. I have had a fore-
man just give me a look as I passed in to my machine or
handed in my sewing that made me wish I was dead. Then
there are the spiteful things the girls say about you and the
cutting remarks of the forewomen that make you feel like fainting. The cashier may have a grudge, and if he doesn't hold
your wages back till all the other hands are paid, he will throw
it at you, make you take ragged bills or give you a week's pay
in small change. A cashier in a Jackson street cravat factory
once rubbed his hand across my chin "to feel my whiskers,"
he said, and because I got angry and said I would report him
he saved up all the silver that had holes and plugs and made
me take it. My salary was $5.25 that week and some of it I
couldn't pass. I took it to a bank and the cashier was kind
enough to give me good money for it. Plenty of times the
forewoman has had me discharged because I was 'stuck up.'
"Prices here range from 20 cents to $2 a dozen. It depends
on the material. Children's drawers pay 20 cents a dozen, but
there are no button-holes to work. Some shirts are $2, some
$41 and some $1.50, but most of them only pay 80 cents.
Everything is done by machine, including buttonholes and
gussets. The bosoms and bands are all ready to go in. Corset covers pay 40 cents and chemises 20 cents each, but they
have to be trimmed and the holes worked by hand. This is a
mean shop so far as prices go, but they are all alike in that
particular. You have to find your own thread and you are
constantly being suspected of keeping back short ends of lace."
I asked the forewoman for stitching and was given shirts at
80 cents a dozen to do. I had to pay 50 cents for the use of
the machine, a No. 8 Wheeler &amp; Wilson, and 35 cents for a
spool of thread. I told the forewoman I had left my purse at
home, but she said it was "all right, you can have it taken
<pb n="51"/>
out of your wages." I asked her what the machine cost but
she didn't know, and when I ventured the information that the
expiration of the patent had reduced the old price of $65 to
about $12 she told me she "reckoned I didn't know what I
was talking about." The room where we worked was about
eighteen feet wide and ten feet deep, with toilet closets built
out from the walls. The machines encircled the three walls
and in the middle of the floor were the boxes of work. One
girl was stitching wrist-bands, another had a button-hole machine and was getting 50 cents a hundred. A third was making tucked drawers at 20 cents a dozen, and I had a shirt at
6 2/3 cents, which I failed to finish in three hours, being unable
to manage the machine.
In Tuesday's paper reference was made to the firm of W---
H--- &amp; Co., as paying 18 cents a pair for making trousers. It
was a typographical error and did unintentional injustice to
the firm. The lowest prices on their list is 45 cents, and that is
for making boys' trousers.
</div>