<xml><!--ebb: If you'd like to convert this to TEI, we can work on a standard header: you could follow what we're using the Digital Mitford or Pacific projects if you like; look at some of our sample headers. For now, I'm just wrapping a lot of this opening matter in a general <header> element.-->
<header>
INTERIOR OF SN EAST£Rtt WOOLEN WILL,
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
INTERIOR OF SN EAST£Rtt WOOLEN WILL,
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
THE
SLAVES OF
A
MERICA
BUNG AN ACCOUNT OF THE
SUFFERINGS, PRIVATIONS AND HARDSHIPS
OP THB
WEARY TOILERS IN OUR GREAT CITIES
I
As RECENTLY EXPOSED BY NELL N
of the CHICAGO TIMES.
FXXALX LABOR, CHILD LABOR, CONTRACT LABOR AND PRISON
LABOR—AM ARRAIGNMENT or CORPORATIONS, POOLS AND
TrVSTS. AND AM APPIAL FOR INDUSTRIAL EMANCIPATION.
Author of The Story of Manual Labor in All Lands and Ages,
WITH SPECIAL CONTRIBUTIONS BY
JUDGE T. M. COOLEY, T. V. POWDERLY AND OTHERS

OHIOAQO :
. S. peale &amp; Company.
MDCCCLX XXVIIL

HARVARD
UNIVERSITY
UBRARY
1943

COPTfUOBT,
3T R. 8, PIAIJ 
</header>

<text> <div type="preface">AUTHOR’S PREFACE.
IN the following pages will be found a record which, in many places, amonnts to an indictmeut of oar whole system and our whole
civilization. The position of the White Slaves in our factories is
something which can only be described as disgraceful. In going on as
we are going—in not stopping the abuses to which female labor is subjected here at our very doors, we are doing what is at once a foolish and a dangerous thing. We are sowing what we must reap; and as long as what is called the dangerous element in this community can point out the rank injustice to which we subject female labor, so long will
they hare in their hands an argument which we cannot meet. These
things can be made
effort do justice, and it is the purpose of these pages to excite those
who can do right; to do it.
   With the facts in the case spread before a candid world* there should be little question about what should be done. It is not an issue as to what women should be paid for their work. Until they
themselves learn how to organize, they must expect bad treatment in
that direction. Nobody can say that an employer must pay a dollar for that which is offered to him at fifty cents. But we can demand
that proper care, proper sanitation and proper treatment shall be accorded to every working woman.
   As far as the rest of the matter goes, female labor must organize if it wishes to do anything. Organized labor is the end to which the industry of the civilized world is tending, and every year the movement becomes more and more certain of ultimate success. There have been checks and drawbacks, but the force which impels the workingman forward to a general union with all of his fellows has been constant and irresistible.
   As we haye endeavored to show in the following pages, there is a necessity for general labor organization, such as has been never before
known in the world. The age is one of combination, both of the
iii
straight and just and fair. We can with little
IT
<!--ebb: Something's obviously missing here!-->
working class and the employing class. Unless either side unites in a
strong, well-disciplined union, it mnst go to the wall. The proper reply to the corporation, the pool and the trust is the trades-union, the trade federation, and some society which shall bind into one homogeneous, one-ideaed and perfectly-disciplined mass the whole of the working element in the United States.
   To this end experiments haYe been made and will be made. The
Trades Union Congress of England; the Knights of Labor of America;
similar societies on the Continent, —are all evidences of the necessities for organization and the attempts which men are making in that direc-
*
tion. But all of these social forces are new and their leaders inexperienced. Often the right road can not be found until after all the wrong ones have been tried. We find society provided with a new weapon, but it is only out of many mistakes, out of much loss and suffering, that we will arrive at the knowledge of its proper use and its
correct purpose. We have nearly settled the question of what the
trades-union can do, and what it cannot do—we have surveyed it,
weighed it, appraised it. It occupies a definite place in our calculations.
is no longer an unknown quantity in the problem. But the force, the defensive and the offensive powers of thoroughly organized national labor are not known, nor will they be in this century.
   One great society after another will arise, and take up the work which its predecessor laid down. Each will avoid the rocks upon which the earlier ones went to pieces; the unknown seas of organization
are being charted surely, if slowly, and the people are coming to know
where the dangers lie. It is part of the history of human effort that moves in waves—now coming in with a high tide, and again ebbing out so that it seems that almost all the advance has been lost. This is, however, seeming rather than reality. With Tennyson we
i
Know that through the ages one increasing purpose runs
And the thoughts of men are widened with the process of the suns
99
   Even if the men of the present day do not find themselves able to mobilize, equip and maintain the army of labor, doubt it not that
their sons and their daughters will.

   There are elements of strength which have not even been touched bj the present leaders, although of course they have been recognized, and efforts toward getting them have been made. Take the elections, for instance. There were in the United States, in 1880, 17,392,099 people engaged in all kinds of occupations. The voting population was, white and black, 12,830,349 for the same year; and the
President, James A. Garfield, was elected by the ballots of 4,449,053
citizens. Cleveland four years later was chosen by the votes of 4,911,017 men; and this year a President will be made by the votes of
not more than 5,500,000 persons. Now can any person believe that I
there are not in America much more than 6,000,000 or 7,000,000 of cit- I izens who would be willing to come together on a labor jriatform and
for labor candidates, if they could have confidence in the integrity of
the men and the honesty of the measures. The George movement in New York proved at once the strength and the weakness of the laborers and the friends of labor. They were able to do a great deal even with their imperfect machinery of organization, and the disappearance of ] this vote in a subsequent election showed that there was nothing per- I manent in the methods by which it had been called out. It was a flash I in the pan, but it proved something that labor should not willingly {
forget.
   The road to power in this country lies but in one direction—through I the ballot box. That is our final tribunal of appeal, and its decisions we must accept heartily, willingly, loyally. When organized labor
raises its voice in this court, the world will listen with respect. But
until that time comes, the workingman’s duty is still clear. Neither
Bome nor organized labor were, or will be, built in a day. The movement must be pushed firmly and guided wisely. There must be statesmanship and diplomacy, as well as sacrifice and loyalty. Labor and capital must both listen to the voice of public opinion in America, for both are weak, and properly weak, before it. It is our ruler, whether we are rich or poor, eminent or humble; and it is a wise ruler, whose commands are bora of truth and justice and carried out in strictness and mercy. When public opinion is with labor organization and its
methods, then, and not until then, will the labor problem be solved.
 </div>   <div type="toc">
<head>TABLE OF CONTENTS.</head>
<list><item>CHAPTER I.—FEMALE LABOR.

lists of Trades In Which F emale Labor Is Used—Peculiar Female Ability-
Average Wages—Pay and Privileges of Household Work—Pitiable Condition of Working Women at Home and Abroad—Statements from London, New York and Chicago—Foul Factories and Filthy Tenements—A Week's Salary Gone in Fines—The One Door of Escape—The Actual Experience of a Newspaper Investigator in the Guise of a Shop-girl	 13</item>
<item>CHAPTER II.—CITY SLAVE GIRLS.
J
A Day in a Chicago Tailor Shop—Misery, Squalor and Ceaseless Toil—Children Thirteen Years Old Working from Morn till Night on Heavy Coats and Trowsers— $8.50 a Week for Toil that Grinds the Marrow from the Bones and Kills Morality—Compelled by a Hard Master to Work Without Speaking and “ Pulled'* for being Sick or Late	 20</item>
<item>CHAPTER IV.—A MODERN SLAVE-PEN.
A Day’s Experience in a Chicago Cloak Factory—Left in a Foul and Filthy
Corner of the Work-Room Until Outraged Nature Succumbs— After Hours of Drudgery the Bosses Refuse to advance Car-fare to a Needy Serf—Vile Air, Brutality and the Privileges of Earning Barely Enough to Keep Soul and Body Together—Eating Poor Crackers and Workmg for Two Months in Order to Get aPair of Shoes	 82</item>
<item>CHAPTER V.—CHILDREN DOOMED TO DRUDGERY.
Girls of Tender Years Wasting Away their Lives in a So-Called Modern Dry
Goods Emporium—Ill-Fed, Wan-Faced Children Working from 7:45 to 6:80 for Miserly Compensation	 	 84</item>
<item>CHAPTER VI.—SHOE-SHOP SLAVES.
Little Heroines who work for Three Meals, a Roof at Night and Their Car-Fare—
Dirt and Work	No Time for Church or for Reading—How the Laws
Concerning Child Labor are Openly Evaded	 50</item>
<item>CHAPTER VII.—THE SLATES OP “ LITTLE HELL.”
A Day Among the Serfs sod Bond-Women in the Slop-Shops of Chicago—Six
Cents for Foor Hours of Unceasing Toil in a Dirty, Crowded Tailor’s Room— Children Who Waste Their Lives for $1 a Week—Hen who Grow Rich at the • Expense of Human Life—Factories from which the Miserable, Helpless Drudges Could Never Escape in Case of Fire—Task-Masters who Can Not
Speak English Holding American Laborers in Grinding Bondage	 65</item>
<item>CHAPTER VIII.—CHILDHOOD IN BONDAGE.
Boys Who Work in Box Factories for Three Cents an Hour—The Sash and
Door Making Concerns and Their Child Slaves—A Trip Through a Mattress Factory—What Becomes of the Loathsome Rags Picked Up by Scavengers—A “ Good Jew ”—A Modern Slave Driver Who Compels Unshack- eled Slaves to Take Short Stitches in Order to Save Space	 00</item>
<item>CHAPTER IX.—THE SLUMS OF A ORE AT Cm.
Among the Hovels of the Poor—Work and Workers in a “ Slop-Shop”—No Rest
for the Wretched Women and Children This Side the Grave—A Day Among the Butcher-Shops and Canned-Meat Factories—The Lesson to be Learned—
The Remedy	 07</item>
<item>CHAPTER X.—THE HOMES OF WORKERS.
The Tenements of New York—Squalid Misery Among the Working Wome)
Stifling and Fetid Rooms in which People Work and 81eep—Suicidal Sewage
Systems—Official Facts, Figures and Illustrations—The Overcrowded Metropolis—Scenes in the Italian Quarters—American Pauperization—A Frightful Indictment.	 74</item>
<item>CHAPTER XI.—CONTRACT LABOR.
The Evils of Over-Immigration—The Contract System—How the Pauper Laborers Live—Wooden Shoes and Filth—The Brass Check System—The Wholesale Importation of Immigrant Labor a Menace to Society		 82</item>
<item>CHAPTER XII.—THE FIELD OF THB TRADES UNION.
Insincere Arguments against Trades-Unions—The Real Reason for the Hostility
to Labor Organizations—Communism «. Anarchy—The Fault on Both Sides—Labor as Merchandise—The Workingman’s Limitations—The Goad
of Want—The Truck System—Employment for the Trades-Union—The Black List—The Iron-Clad Oath			 80</item>
<item>CHAPTER XIII.—STRIKES IN THEORY AND PRACTICE.
The Wage 8ystem a Relic of Feudalism—Compromise the Ultimate Law of
Nature—The Trades-Union the Emancipator of Labor—The Ethics of the Labor Question—A Self-Ad justing Apportionment of Profits to be Substituted for the Illogical System Now in Vogue—An Appeal for Industrial
Emancipation</item>			
<item>CHAPTER XIV.—THE EIYALS OF AMERICAN LABOR.
PACQL
Immigrant Competition—The Products of American Labor Protected, but no
Protection for American Labor Itself—Connection Between Immigration
and Bankruptcy—Convict Competition—The Whole Domain of National Industry Affected by Criminal Labor—Mechanical Competition—The Effect of Machinery on Manual Labor.	100</item>
<item>CHAPTER XV.—THE ARMY OF THE DISCONTENTED.
BY T. V. POWDBRLY.
The Number of the Unemployed—The Downward Tendency of Wages—The
“ Law of Supply and Demand ”—Relation of Wages to the Cost of Production—Child Labor—The Plea for Shorter Hours—Effect of Labor-Saving
Machinery-The Eight-Hour System—“ The Sin of Cheapness’*—“Too
much Wheat/' yet Millions of Men and Women in Want of Bread	116
Strikes and Arbitration— (By T. V. Powderly)			124
Co-operation—(Letter from Judge T. M. Cooley)	129</item></list>   </div> 
   <title>WHITE SLAVES.</title>CHAPTER I.—FEMALE LABOR.

LIST OF TRADES m WHICH FEMALE LABOR IS USED—PECULIAR FEMALE ABILITY
—AVERAGE WAGES—PAY AND PRIVILEGES OF HOUSEHOLD WORK—PITIABLE CONDITION OF WORKING WOMEN AT HOME AND ABROAD—STATEMENTS FROM LONDON, NEW YORK AND CHICAGO—FOUL FACTORIES AND FILTHY TENEMENTS—A WEEK’S SALARY CONE IN FINES—THE ONE DOOR OF ESCAPE—
THE ACTUAL EXPERIENCE OF A NEWSPAPER INVESTIGATOR IN THE GUISE OF A SHOP-GIRL.
EVERY year the scope of female labor is becoming broader, the number of laborers larger, the skill and the effectiveness of the working-women greater, but, unfortunately the condition of the women who
win their bread has not improved. They are for the most part badly housed, insufficiently fed, shabbily clothed and poorly paid. The trades and the callings requiring skilled labor in which women are now employed in this country are mainly in the production of the following articles: Artificial flowers, awnings, bedding supplies, blank books, paper boxes, collars and cuffs, clothing, brushes, buttons, canned goods,
caps, cards, carpets, cases for jewelry, cigars and cigarettes, cloaks and
suits, confectionery, cords and fringes, corsets, dresses, embroidery, envelopes, essences and extracts, fancy boxes and fans, feathers, flannels, flags, furs, gimps, gloves, gold-leaf, handkerchiefs, hats, hat- sweats and hat trimmings, labels, laces, lead pencils, underwear,
mats, mattresses* medicine, morocco goods, millinery, neckties, paper
bags, parasols, perfumeries, pocket books, pearl work, preserves, quilts,
ribbons, shirts, shoes, skirts, silk, soap, slippers, straw goods, spices, suspended tags, tassels, tickings, tobacco, toys, trimmings, twines, umbrellas, upholstery, watch-cases, wax-works, wigs, willow ware,
window-shades, woolen goods, wrappers, worsted yams. In the making
13
of each of these articles the reader will perceive that the demand has brought about the supply. There was need in each case for the mannal dexterity, the light and caref nl tonch and the patient and tireless application which we recognize as the chief advantages of women’s work.
For this peculiar ability, however, it is nnfortnnately true that the
women are the worst paid laborers in America. They receive shamefully low wages, and the conditions under which they work are disgraceful to our boasted civilization. For instance, braid-makers average
$5.50 a week; vest-makers, $6.00; button-hole makers, $4.30; candy- makers, $4.75; cap-makers, $5.50;tobacco-strippers, $5.50; cigar-makers, $5.00; dressmakers, $5.00; hatters, $6.00; ladies’hat makers, $4.00;paper- makers, $5.00; rag-sorters, $3.50; shirt-makers, $6.00. These figures, however, come from first-class establishments, which are not afraid to
expose their methods of working to the light of day; establishments which, unfortunately, are in a helpless minority among the employers of female labor. The writer believes, from a careful study of all the facts to which he could get access, that the average wage for female
skilled labor in this country, throughout, is somewhere between $4.50
and $5.00 a week, and the average time worked is something more than ten hours a day. The reason is plain: female labor is not organized, it is perfectly helpless, and the weakest, under the beneficent and kindly law of nature, goes to the wall.
   There are classes of work done by women whose conditions can not in justice be criticised as can the so-called skilled labor, and which are, if not too well paid, at least comfortable, healthy, and proper; chief among these is domestic service, in which, in 1888, more than 1,200,000
females are employed. Their wages run between $10 and $14 a month
some, of course, ranging as high as $25 and $30, and few falling below
$10, so that $12 is a conservative general average. To this is of course to be added board and lodging and perquisites, easily worth $20 a month more. The domestic servant is, as a rule, well fed, cleanly and com* fortably lodged, and fairly treated; but the idea of household work is so repugnant to many women that they prefer the starvation wages of the trades and the unwholesome crowding of the tenements. Laundresses and hotel servants have also surroundings and lives better for than anything to be found in the factories, but here, too, the objection of “ menial service ” applies, and most American-born women will have
none of it.
   Up to within the past few years there was practically no recourse for
an educated woman who had her own living to make save teaching. This
t
list has also been extended, and type-writing, which pays about $10 a
week, stenography at an average of $12, and different kinds of clerical work in stores, keeping books, cash, etc., and selling goods, which are paid for at the rate of from $5.50 to $10, and sometimes $15 a week, have been added to the list. So that on the whole there are now in America about one hundred separate callings bidding for female labor, out of* which the woman who must win her bread may take her choice. That the theater for her endeavor has thus been widened is by itself a good thing. The chance for self-help, the possibility of independence, lifts the sex up, and as the years come on we can expect to see the sphere of woman’s action broadening until it at last will include all of these industries, where tactual skill, delicate manipulation, and careful work are needed rather than strength. But before we congratulate ourselves
too much upon the high civilization which this indicates, let, us look at
the reverse of the picture.
   It is a fact that female labor the world over is in a most pitiable condition; women are weak in every way, weak individually and weak in their lack of organization, and there are men ready at all times to take
   advantage of their weakness. In London the average wage of the whole body of women workers is, according to official figures, less than seven shillings ($1.75) a week, and out of this sum the worker must find food for herself, rags to cover her, and a place to stay when she is not struggling for these few paltry bits of silver. As to the effect, hear what the English factory inspector says as late as the 1st of July, 1888:
   “ Domestic workshops, as now extended, are a great evil. Instead * of large factories and legally constituted workshops we have thousand s of domestic workshops, dark, dirty and overcrowded, and which can not be improved by factory legislation, for at the time of the passing of the act the present state of things could not have been contemplated. Let not keen competition bear the whole of the blame, but rather let the truth be spoken, to the credit of greediness, and an unconcern for the welfare of unskilled operatives. Our female population are losing self-respect, for they have no hope of improvement, being unskilled operatives; they rush into extremes of the gratification of the
senses, they frequent places where drink is supplied, and where utterances are set to music provocative, enticing and subtle, a luxurious yet sensuous gratification of untrained minds, unrestrained when their small earnings are*paid; but in the end they are most assuredly the victims of
the voluptas empta dolore.”
And in the factories the conditions are such that the most callous
reader must stand appalled at the details. In 424 factories where women were employed in the east end of London, sewer gas was present in
dangerous quantities, and the sexes were huddled together without
any attempt at decency. The places are described as foul and filthy.
Among 600 lost women who answered the questions put to them by the inspector, 511 had been factory operatives. The only wonder is that the
proportion is not greater.
   But we are accustomed to look on London as a place in another world. How is it at home? Here is the condition in New York tabulated so that it may be seen at a glance :
SANITARY CONDITION OF WORKSHOPS AND FACTORIES.
1
2
3
5
7
9
9
2
4
5
a Is there free circulation of air through and about the
building in which you work ?
b Are there offensive odors in the rooms occupied by
ploy
then
es; if so, from what causes?
e Are there facilities for washing?
Are seats provided, as prescribed by law?	
d Are employes furnished with pure drinking water ?
Does the work require the employes to stoop over?
   proper and separate facilities for cnai dress by males and females ?	
e Are there
/ A re there separate water-closets for males and females
Are there stairways from the windows outside ?
4
S
Are the rooms supplied with water pipes?
Are there hose attachments?	
h Are employes compelled to stand or sit at their work ?
Are there water tanks and buckets on each floor?	
Yes.
No.
468
249
342
233
480
124
320
192
627
102
587
116
354
221
609
g 128
350
818
286
885
224
375
Sit.
Stand.
469
175
Yes.
No.
236
387
Blank. Optional.
285
226
296
181
107
235
175
148
166
218
• *
Blank.
198
87
   a One says where she is employed there are 100 women and small girls who work in a cellar without ventilation, and gas and electric lights burning all day.
   b Eighty-one from water-closets and seventy-three from various other causes.
' yes, but if caught washing d in some cases where they have ice water in the summer the employes are
c Fourteen answered
are fined.
or
made to pay a stated sum per season.
   e A number answer that they change in the water-closet.
   / Yes, but very poor and not pleasant to enter.
   g In sight of male employer, and another case not fit to use, and a breeding-plaoe ofdis-
i Some are fined if caught sitting, and in some instances must furnish their own seats.
These are official figures, and the New York Labor Commissioner says
officially of them
It is not only proven that the sanitary condition
such as to cause alarm, but that, in an equally great proportion of the same buildings, means for prevention and escape in case of fire are alarmingly deficient. And this is not all, nor is it, from certain standpoints, a fact calculated to arouse public sentiment and indignation to so great an extent, as the utter lack of proper facilities for change of dress and the use of separate water closets, as established by overwhelming testimony “
In Chicago, according to the statements given with names and places
by the Times newspaper, the conditions are as bad. In many places
where women work there is not even a pretense of cleanliness. It is proven that in one factory the women are locked in without any possibility of leaving the room for any purpose. When the knitting girls
struck in St. Louis, it was shown that in some cases prostitution was one of the conditions of getting and keeping work, and that many girls could not make enough money to buy bread and fuel without resorting to the streets. It is the general custom in almost all places to discipline women workers by fining them for an infraction of the rules, and there are many instances on record where the fines have taken up the whole of the week's wages, although the employer got the whole of the week’s
work. Can anyone wonder that out of 2,000 women of the town in
New York, 1,820 had been working girls before they took to,the streets? Can anyone wonder why Madison street, in Chicago, is nightly crowded with unfortunates?
   But it will be well to give here in detail some of the results of the Times9 investigations of the conditions surrounding female labor in Chicago. They have additional value from the fact that they were made for a responsible newspaper by a woman who shows in every line of her
work her fitness for the task. It has not been deemed advisable here to
*
give the names of the firms and corporations, but those sufficiently
interested may peruse the files of the Chicago Times, beginning with
July 30, 1888, and there read the articles, under the heading “ City Slave Girls,” which should make the nom deplume of the writer, “ Nell Nelson,” forever dear to all toiling womankind :
   Tuesday, July 10, according to instructions, I made up for the role of shop-girl, and with a list of factories in one hand, and gentle peace in the other, sailed down town under a brown baize veil as impenetrable as an iron mask.
   I did not realize the ignominious position of respectable poverty till I reached a cloak factory on Madison street, where labor is bondage, the laborer a slave, and flesh and blood cheaper than needles and thread.
Corporations are said to be without heart, but this concern is a commercial inquisition. It puts its help on the plane of slavery, and nothing but civil law prevents the use of the lash.
   The factory is on the third floor of a large brick building.
Elevator? No, indeed. An elevator is a luxury, and luxuries have no place here. You will be short of breath when you reach the top of
the fourth flight, but in recovering you have time to take in the
surroundings—a great barn of a place, with the single charm of good
light. There is plenty of vacant room, but the women are huddled together, elbows touching, along the line of machines. Into the west windows pours the odor of Chicago’s famous sewer river; at the south
end of the room, not ten feet from the crowded table, is a tier of closets,
and on hot days the combined odor of the two is shocking. Nobody dare complain about smells, cold, heat, work, wages or rules. But whoever heard of martyrs complaining?
My experience began at 7:50 a.m. and lasted just three hours. When
1 climbed the dusty stairs I took a ten-minute rest at the top. Everybody was at work but a hungry-looking man about twenty-seven years
old, with skin the color of a Russia turnip, and thin, peaked features.
He was dressed in a pair of heelless slippers, a white shirt, and a pair of
shop pants that some poor slave had received eighteen cents for making.
Neither collar, vest, coat, nor suspenders burdened his emaciated form.
He moved among the workers with a cat-like tread, his shoulders
drooping and his knees opening and shutting with a sort of accordion movement at every step. He passed me several times as 1 stood at the
desk, and eyed me so unpleasantly that I turned my back to him.
After waiting at the desk for three-quarters of an hour, I asked the
clerk, a sweet little girl of sixteen years, with pretty red cheeks and dark
eyelashes and hair, for work, and was told to wait till the forelady came round. A dozen girls were waiting, too, some with cloaks, others with
check-books and tickets, and a few with hand-made fringe. The fringe.
girl I spoke to. She told me she received 5 cents a yard for making
an imitation of seal-ball fringe, such as winter cloaks are trimmed with. She had a piece three yards and a quarter long that had taken her all the previous day to make. Here was a child of fifteen working nine and a half hours a day for a competence of 16± cents. Will the Prairie Avenue woman who, at the suggestion of Mrs. Ormison Chant, is trying
to find a hundred girls who are earning less than 28 cents a day, please
enter Maggie W	on the list, and will the women of the Protective
Agency who want a new field of inquiry, call and see the slim, snake-
gaited, jaundice-faced creature who has charge of this human mill?
Maggie’s fringe being measured and her book checked, she was given
another box of material, and went off to weave it into tassel-trimming. The girl who took her place would not be interviewed. She “ didn’t
know how much stitchers earned, and wouldn’t tell nobody how much a
week she could make/’ She was, possibly, twenty-five years old, with a
deathly pale face, and looked as though she hadn’t eaten any breakfast.
Her successor was less reticent. “Pm here since May, bnt I don’t like
it. The boss is a horrid thing. Him and the forelady watches us all
the time, and they don’t give us hardly any work. I can only make one
cloak a day; some pays 30 cents, some 40 cents, and some 50 cents. Yesterday I had 60 cents coming to me for two days. Are you long here? Oh, you won’t stay. They search your bag and your pockets when
you go home nights to see if you have any thread or pieces about you.”
   After waiting an hour the disguised investigator was properly enrolled among the toilers of this particular cloak factory, assigned to a place in
the work-room, and given a good-sized bundle of material, which was to
be made into a garment.
   “ This is a 65-cent cloak,” said the hard-featured spinster who acted as forelady. “ The stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder 15 cents, and you get 30 cents for finishing, if the work is right.” Here was£ indeed, a fortune! Thirty cents for making a long cloth cloak after the seams
were stitched. It had to be trimmed down the back gores, around the
collar, cuffs and pockets with mohair plush; the sleeves had to go in—
   eighteen button-holes to be worked and a corresponding number of buttons sewed on, and the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty . cents, in other words, for a good day’s work of ten hours!
I
/
CHAPTER II.—CITY SLATE GIRLS.
A DAT IN A CHICAGO TAILOR-SHOF—MISERY, SQUALOR AND CEASELESS TOIL—CHILDREN THIRTEEN YEARS OLD WORKING FROM MORN TILL NIGHT ON HEAVY COATS AND TROUSERS—$8.50 X WEEK FOR TOIL THAT GRINDS THE MARROW FROM THE BONES AND KILLS MORALITY—COMPELLED BY A HARD MASTER TO WORK WITHOUT SPEAKING AND “ PULLED ” FOR BEING SICK OR LATE.
NEVER, so long as reason reigns, writes Kell Nelson, shall I forget the day I worked in a Market-street tailor-shop, and never when I pray shall I forget to add “ God help the shop girls.
   Thursday morning I stepped from an Ogden avenue car and walked down Market street in search of work. It was boiling hot, and I carried my brown veil on the breeze, and a small pasteboard box containing a
cracker and a lemon, a paper of needles, a thimble, and a pair of scissors.
   The first woman I made inquiry of was carrying a bucket of sawdust from a neighboring ale-house. She didn’t know by name the shop I was looking for, but when I mentioned coats, she grew loquacious.
   Oh, yes, the ‘ slave hole ’ it’s called; that’s the sheeny tailor’s! Dont you go to him, my dear; he’ll grind the marrow from your bones. Go to service, girl, go to service. Tou can have a cot in my room till
yon find a place. I was with him one fortnight and worked my eyes 'most blind, and be paid me $1.75. No, I'm from England, but I never
had harder times in the old country than now. There I paid 5*. for
lodgings, and here they cost me $4.” She told me she got the sawdust
for sweeping out a corner dram-shop, and used it to boil her tea-kettle with.
   Instead of a “hole”1 found myself entering a large two-story red brick house still in process of construction. I ascended the front steps, and, after the maneuver of the celebrated king of France, marched down again to the basement—to the shop—into the presence of the proprietor.
I handed him my letter, and while he read it I took him in—optically. He was an unctnous little fellow, with kinky hair, cunning brown eyes, hatchet features, and a small mustache the color of roasted coffee. He was attired in two shirts—a nether one of chocolate flannel and a linen one a few shades lighter—a pair of check pantaloons, carpet slippers, and
a huge gold ring of Masonic design. He read the letter with a cigar in
20
his month, the smell of which, combined with the flavor of his feet and
the exhalations of his toilet, was something preponderant.
He asked me what I had worked at, and, after a few gasps, I gave
him some of my history, slightly distorted.
   I was told to take off my hat, and while doing so he stepped back ont in the entry and vacated a hook among the factory girls' wraps, but, as I did not care to take the chances of tempting the gutter snipes and going home bare-headed, I declined his attention and hung them up in a corner on the floor. All ready, sewing-box in hand, I faced the gaping, silent throng, and was pointed to a chair at a long table, about which ten girls were sewing with a speed and a silence that was terrible
to contemplate. They wore cotton dresses of the poorest quality, some
of them open at the neck, and nearly all rolled to the elbow. The
youngest were four little girls of thirteen, one of whom was operating,
two basting, and the fourth finishing a blue cloth cloak. One large
Irish hand, possibly twenty-five, sat at the upper end of the table. Of
the rest fifteen years would be a fair average age. One poor girl, who
was very lame, had a machine, and it made my heart ache to watch her pale face and follow her thin little hands guide coat after coat under the needle. All the girls were pale and haggard, some were very pretty, some few had color in their cheeks, but it was the hectic flush, not the healthy glow of youth and physical strength.
   In all we were twenty girls, eight men, and two boys—poor young fellows in their teens, with mealy complexions, wild eyes, hollow cheeks, and sunken chests. Neither weighed a hundred pounds, but both
pressed goods with heavy irons, and were cuffed and pushed about by
the boss and his assistant. The men worked in slippers and undershirts, without straps or suspenders to keep their trousers in place, and the
girls wore heavy peg shoes. I noticed some of'the machine hands worked the foot-plate in their stocking feet.
I had taken all this in when the boss came near my chair and threw a plaid sack coat in my lap and without a word walked away. Here
was a nice predicament, I thought, as I looked the garment over. I asked the lit tie yellow-haired Swede girl at my right where to begin, but she looked at me and resumed her “felling” without a word of
reply. Then I asked a big, yellow-haired, dough-faced German girl on
my left, and received the same kind of response. Instantly I realized their position. Compulsory silence.
I put twist in my needle, squeezed on my timble, and selected the
si de-seam in the farmer satin lining, for if there is any one kind of
needle work that I pride myself on it is “felling,” Well, I felled an
hour, up one seam and down another, around the collar, and along the
bottom of the coat* Then I stitched and tacked the tail pockets, took a deep breath, and settled back in my chair to take a rest. I didn’t take it long, though. Before I could reel off two lines of Hood’s “Song
of the Shirt,” the boss was at my elbow looking oyer my work with his nasty-smelling cigar so near my face that I was obliged to pull back to
escape being burned.
   “Take smaller stitches,” he said. “Don’t ifell’ through. You haven’t, though. Now put in the sleeve-lining,” and he left me muttering inwardly, “Put in the sleeve-lining.” I did. In a great
deal less time I was told to rip it out. I put it in a second time, and a second time did Penelope’s work. The third time was not a charm, and when his unctuous honor, who had been watching me all the time, neared my chair I politely asked him to show me how to arrange the fullness. He grabbed the coat, shook the “ muffy ” thing in my face, dropped the ashes from his two-for-a-nickel in my hair, and observed: “ I don’t think you'll do. I want experienced hands,” and although mute I thought—“ You monster, to talk about experienced hands, and
pay 13.50 a week!”
   Well, he showed me how tailors put in sleeve linings, and I showed the merits of his teaching. In future I shall never let a coat-sleeve go about my waist without wanting its owner to unbutton and let me see where the lining is fulled and how the top seam is felled.
   At noon we had forty minutes, for—I will not say dinner, because no one had anything that could be so designated. Most of the men
had nothing to eat. I only saw two with a lunch. The girls had black bread and a can of cold coffee, which they consumed with evident relish. Not more than five minutes were spent over the repast. I devoured my crackers and gnawed at my lemon by way of desert. In a hurry to get at my work as soon as possible, to make up for lost time, I threw the sucked Messina under the table, and in a few moments saw a little stitcher pick it up and hide it in her pocket.
   By a series of questions I got the following information from a pretty Jewess who had been in the shop for three years and was getting $3.50 a week. She said, regarding the salary: “ Oh, I don’t care. The boss won’t pay any more. My mother has money and doesn’t mind
so long as I learn to sew. I am fifteen in October. I came here at twelve, and don’t know how much longer I will have to stay. The boss thinks women are cows, that they must be driven. So he drives us.
We have to be at work at seven in the morning and stay till six in the
evening."
   “Half holiday Saturday?”
   “Nix.”
   “ What if you are sick?”
   “ If you’re sick he * pulls’ you. He ‘ pulled’ me for twenty cents for being late last week. He * pulls’ all the hands when they come late, and he ‘pulls’ if we talk.”
   That’s why I could not get my neighbors to tell me how to start my work.
   Rosy told me she was thirteen, that her father peddled fish, and that she was the eldest of five sisters and two brothers. She had been in the shop two years, and was getting $2.25 a week.
   Another girl, whom I dare not indicate, said: “ These beggarly
Jews and Swedes are robbing honest girls of a living. Most of them
have homes and are willing to work for nothing. I live with my mother and brother, and can not make any more than enough to pay our rent, $10 a month. I would go in a family, but my mother needs
me; she is sick. The boss is an awful hard man to work for. He steals my hire from me, and I steal his cotton and silk whenever I get a
chance. ”
   During the noon hour the girls played in the front street, and afterwards amused themselves in the back yard with the men. At 12:45 o’clock the “ boss ” came into the shop, and five minutes later the place was noisy with flying shuttles, clicking needles, and the whizzing wheels of the roaring machinery. Fair young heads and pretty shoulders bent over heavy coats, and faces were so low that they almost touched the sewing in their owners’ laps. The clatter of the machines was deafening, and every now and then the shop resounded with the heavy hot irons wielded by the pressers in the back room. Nobody had any time to hand the work, instead of which the cutter threw it to the trimmer, who in turn threw it to the baster, and so it moved from hand to machine, going the round of the thirty odd workers with such rapidity that the air seemed filled with flying coats. The room was low,
and with every passage of coat-tail muffy clouds of lint seemed floating about in space. Add to that poor light, bad ventilation, the exhalations of so many people, the smell of dye from the cloth, and the noxious odor of that ever-consuming cigar, and you have material for the makeup of this particular coat-shop. All afternoon we sewed; sewed incessantly, without uttering a syllable or resting a moment. The “boss”
was building the third story of the house, and every hour or so he would leave the shop in care of an assistant and go up to look after the carpenters. During these intermittent spells the girls took advantage of the substitute and hummed. They didn’t sing; they hummed songs and hymns, marches and waltzes, and when the sub was not looking they actually whispered.
   But the absentee possessed marvelous powers of ubiquitousness, and very little time was wasted in this manner. There are some people you would always know were in the room without seeing them. This hardheaded, godless little Jew was a character of that sort. We could feel his presence and a corresponding heaviness of atmosphere. Whenever he caught sight of a momentary idler he would glide up to her elbow and mutter a single word—work! She worked.
   At 5 o’clock I was so tired I didn’t know what to do with myself. My hair was matted with moisture and dusted with lint, and my head throbbed with pain.
   I perspired at every pore, and the steel in my corsets rusted all the front of my nice Hamburg underwaist. I threw the big brown chinchilla overcoat I had finished on the floor, and for a period of three minutes fell into a state of voluptuous inertia. With my sixth sense I saw the “boss” pick up the garment, and the next moment another overcoat came flying across the table and dropped all over me. I threaded my needle preparatory to finishing my ninth garment, and began a light calisthenic movement of my right arm to scatter the pain and limber
up my elbow. I went through perhaps seven motions, with my chair tilted back by way of stretching my lower extremities, when I was interrupted by the benevolent young tailor and his incombustible cigar.
   Grabbing the frame of my chair, he jammed it down on all fours, and told me to “get to work.”
     44 How much am I going to get for this work ?” I inquired, after recovering from my astonishment and the sudden shock of gravitation.
   “ Do you want to know ?” he asked, with a contemptibly significant laugh.
   “ If you please.”
   “ Well, just finish that coat, and at 6 o’clock I’ll tell you.”
   “ I won’t finish any more. There’s your coat. Pay me.”
     44Pay you! For what ?”
   “ For seven hours’ work ; for finishing eight coats.”
   “ Without further notice of me than an insolent sneer, he picked up the coat, walked back to his cutting-board and began to draft
out collars. I went back to the cutting-board, too, and stood at his side till commanded to “get out of his way.” I stepped back enough to give him elbow room, but did not leave the table.
   “ How long do you expect to annoy me by your presence ? ”
   “ I expect to remain where I am till you pay me for my seven hours’ work.”
   “ Your day isn’t up yet. We don’t quit till 6 o’clock, and it’s only
ten minutes after 5.”
   I told him I did not want to work for him another minute, and demanded my pay.
   “ Well, do you want to know what I’d pay you ? ”
   “ Yes.”
   “ One dollar and fifty cents a week, and you aint worth 75 cents.”
   “ You told me when I started that I would get $3v at least if I could sew.”
   “ And you can’t. All day you have been sitting up in your chair with your shoulders straight and your chair back as if you had a rocking-chair. There’s what I value you at,” and he threw a 25-cent piece
at me. At first I hesitated about touching the money, and, as I looked
at him to see whether he was serious or not, my eyes rested on the heavy gold ring he wore •
   “Oh, you’re a B’nai Brith man, I see. Will you favor me with your card ? ”
   “ What for ? ”
   “ I want to send this money to the society for the orphans which you represent, with my compliments.”
   “ Get out of this shop or I’ll put you out.” Begging him not to go
to that trouble, I got.
   Whatever opinions I may have entertained about the dignity of labor, respectable poverty and the absurdity of fine feathers, my experience as a factory hand has unfitted me for future service, since in no place that I worked did 1 see any incentive to decency, honesty, or respectability, or any promise of success that did not carry with it the downfall of blindly climbing hope.
*
A HARD DAY’S WORK FOR 41 CENTS—LESS FORTUNATE WORKERS WHO Barred
ORLY 11 CENTS—A SICK GIRL’S SAD STORY—THE HOPELESS MISS WHO
LONGED TO BE MARRIED.
THE next institution looked into was a jersey factory. A day’s experience there furnishes the material for a chapter which ought to
prove exceedingly interesting, if not startling, to those who rely upon their imagination for ideas of factory life:
   “ Work is given out at 7:30 a. m.,” the clerk of the manufacturing company informed me, “and if you have any snap about you, you can make a good living." By way of getting the required snap I went
home, ate my dinner, and was in bed at 8 o’clock.
The next morning I resumed the rags of poverty, and at 7 o’clock made my dibut asa factory hand. I was one of 120 women, ranging in
ages from fifteen to sixty, who began to arrive at 7 o’clock. At every trip of the elevator some twenty or more were carried up stairs. I took a chair in one of the machine rows, and for an hour did nothing but watch the preparations for work in that human hive. The room was
50x138, with an open, unfinished roof, and brick walls calcimined.
Light was admitted from rear and side windows. The pressmen had their boards and furnaces at the south end of the room, where all the work was pressed prior to being boxed and ticketed for the trade. At the extreme opposite end was the cutting-room, fenced in from the rest, and between the two were the work-tables, where the hundred odd girls stitched and finished the jerseys.
Along the brick walls were nails, irregularly driven, on which the girls hung their hats and wraps, dresses and collars. Nearly every one
took off her dress and waist, turned it inside out, put it on a nail and
put on a calico or old stuff shop suit. A few took off their corsets, and
nearly all the machine hands changed their shoes before work. On the stroke of 7:30 a bell rang, the power was turned on, the machines
began to buzz like little saw-mills, and the day’s work had commenced.
Heads of brown, black, yellow and gray bent so near the flying shuttles that every minute I expected the bangs and fluffy crimps would get caught in the machinery. The faces were sad and so very, very pale
C'-QAX yAKEKS AT YORK. From s Photograph
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
that I shall never look at a jersey again without seeing them. The average age may have been twenty-three, but not less. There were girls of seventeen and eighteen and some world-weary women past fifty, all working for little more than enough to keep body and soul together. The work circulated in baskets—long chip hampers with stout handles—
that held a dozen, with room for five times that quantity. A great deal of time was lost by the workers in getting the contents of the baskets examined, checked off on the ticket and the ticket stamped. If it had been the last chance of life, I don’t believe the girls would have
worked any harder for salvation. Scarcely a head was raised from
machine or lap. Shoulders were bent down, chests hollowed in, and
faces drooped so low that I could not begin to make a study of the “ windows of the souls ” before me. At 8:40 the proprietor of the chair I was in asked me to vacate, and I walked down through^ the narrow aisles of sewing-women to the “forelady” and asked for work.
   She asked me if I wanted to take a machine, but I expressed a preference for finishing. I was given a number, a basket with five jerseys to finish, and a chair beside a girl named Hannah, who, being engaged
by the day, was told to “ show me.” Hannah had blonde hair, and talked with the brogue. She gave me a needle as long as my engagement finger, and the most meager instruction compatible with obedience. Fortunately I had my thimble, and crossing my knees I threaded
the gimlet-like needle with silk and proceeded to hook-and-eye a jersey.
Bemembering the treachery of any shop clothes I ever wore, I filled the two hooks and eyes with sewing, and after testing them proceeded to face the collar. I made poor work of the bias band, for my needle was
so coarse that it split the satin. I told Hannah about my misery, but
she wisely said it was no fault of hers, and went on with a $3-a-dozen lot she had been doing two days and a half. Thinking it would be a
good way to get acquainted with my neighbors, I asked several for
a fine needle, and at last exchanged the crow-bar Hannah had given me for a fine cambric article. It worked better, and at the end of two
hours I had bound the arm-holes, faced the collar, tacked the front facings and bustle piece, and put two pairs of hooks and eyes in a black
jersey. The dye was not fast, neither was the woo], for my throat, ears, and nostrils were tufted with black lint. I was African from the
'finger-nails to the wrists. The front facings had to be trimmed off. I
had no scissors. Hannah was ungenerous with hers, and I lost about fifteen cents’ worth of time borrowing the weapons. At noon I had finished four jerseys, and was so sore about the neck and back that I
conld scarcely rise from the chair. I began to scent hot tea, and looking about saw a big girl called Emma brewing three pots of Japan over
one of the press furnaces. She had her front hair in carl papers, and was whistling “ In the Sweet Bye-and-By. ” About thirty girls went to her, each with her own cup, for a supply of tea. I remarked to one passing my chair that her tea looked awfully nice, and asked where she got it.
“ From Em. She makes it, and we each pay two cents a week."
On the stroke of twelve the machines stopped and 120 tired women stopped too, for thirty minutes’ rest, and food that could hardly be called
9
refreshing. In the main it consisted of brown bread and batter. In
some parcels there were cold meat and cake; others had pie; a few a bottle or canteen of milk, cold tea or coffee, bat I did not see a particle of frnit. One little girl who had been stretching jerseys at two cents each, made a lunch on three graham crackers and a piece of cnstard pie
which she ate while reading a paper-covered book. I counted thirty-seven
girls with a lunch of dry bread, fifteen with sandwiches, and ten who ate cold pancakes. Twenty-three girls were without any luncheon whatever. During the intermission the elevator stopped running, and no
one left the building but myself. Less than ten minutes were spent over the wretched meal. At one side of the west wall, separated by a
ten-foot pine partition, was the toilet-room, containing an iron sink
with one faucet of running water. Here the girls crowded like so many cattle, each with her bit of soap and grimy cotton towel, to wash.
Dress waists were loosened and necks, faces, arms and hands lathered
with soap and rinsed as the chance permitted. There were three closets, unflushed, untidy and unwholesome. Set up against the wall in this
enclosure, with the faucet run through the partition, was a barrel
of ice water inscribed in big letters: “ Two cents will be collected
every Saturday for ice water.” Besides this luxury every hand pays
twelve cents a week for the use of the machine.
At one o’clock I finished my basket, which I dragged to the bookkeeper, who took my name and credited me with five garments. No
price had been put on the jerseys, as they were sampled goods, but the
forelady thought they would go at 60 cents a dozen, which meant 25
cents to my credit.
I didn’t get any more work till two o’clock, because the forelady was
in the toilet-room having her bangs done up in paper. She was a pretty
woman, by the way. with a good face and a shock of beautiful auburn
hair. She had been in her position for six years, and was drawing a
salary of 135 a week. The girls had a good word for her generally, but she struck me as being a woman without heart. At her appearance I was given a basketful of jerseys to finish button-holes. I worked like a Trojan for an hour, at the end of which I won the heart of a little girl who sat at the end of my table facing the wall. She had been sitting still so long that I called out and asked if she were ill.
   “ No. I haven't any work."
   Tired almost to exhaustion, and as hot as a newly-built mustard plaster, I was only too glad of a chance to transfer my interests, but she declined. It was too hot to work; she was going away soon, she said,
and didn’t care to do any more.
   “When did I begin? To-day. I worked in a box factory, but it was so dull I could only earn 16 cents a day. My mother wants me to pay her $2.50 a week board, but how could I with 96 cents.  This is no
better. I came at eight this morning, and I have only made 11 cents. I
am 21. Beaus? Yes, some. I have one steady fellow, but I don't know
if he will marry me. I hope he will.”
   She told me he earned $75 a month as telegraph operator on the Board of Trade; that he was “ steady as a steeple, and the only fellow she ever loved.”
   I told her how to go about catching the prosperous telegrapher, and rehashed a recipe given me by no less a personage than Mrs. John M. Sherwood, which I had never tried. She was going to a picnic at Garfield Park at six o’clock, and brought over a 25-cent chocolate cake to show me. Then she loaned me her scissors, told me good-by, and went
home to dress for the fSte.
   Nothing of any importance occurred till some one passed the news
that a girl was asleep in the closet. Half a dozen left their machines to look at her, Hannah, my mentor, among them. '
“Oh, you just ought to see her, fast asleep, with her mouth wide open." It was more than I could stand. I threw my button-holes into
the basket and went to the toilet-room. Sure enough, there was the poor girl sitting in the dirty place, her head resting against a folded apron, breathing in the foul air that reeked with filth and disease. The walls of the closet were black with pencil marks, the floor was strewn with lint and threads, and the pale face of the sleeper looked ghastly in the darkness. She had tied one end of a string to the latch and the other to the
drop chain.
“ My dear child, you mustn’t sleep here. Are you sick ? ”
“ Oh, I am so sick."
   Instantly there were a dozen willing hands to help her out to a window, where a chair was placed for her. We rubbed her temples, chafed her hand8, bathed her head, and got her some lemons. After making her toilet she came over to my table, and as I sewed away at my buttonholes she told me her story:
   “ Rose and I are only six months in this country. We came from
England with our brother, and live on Carpenter street. The climate
doesn’t agree with me, and I am sick all the time. At first we worked
in Marshall Field’s, and Rose and I made fringe. We got $7 a week, and were so happy. It was awful nice there. We didn’t have to pay for drinking-water or anything; there were lots of towels, whole cakes of soap, and, oh, it was so clean. We had a foreman over us, and he was
as good as a brother to us. Sometimes we let our money lay and drew
it in a pile;* oh, such a lot as it was! We put away very much of it. But I got sick and all we ’ad saved went for doctor and medicine. Then
the work stopped. They took our names, though, and promised to send
for us in the fall. For a while we worked in the box factory, but nearly to starve. Then we went to Ellinger’s and made cloaks at 30 cents each, but it was so hard, and we couldn’t please them, no matter how we tried.
We came here to-day, but it’s only a fit place to starve in. All the work
they gave me was a dozen jerseys to button; that’s 11 cents a row; had
two dozen holes to finish at 16 cents. Twenty-seven cents for the two of us! How can we live on it ? ” And the child began to cry again.
   By way of comforting her I took her name, promised to help her,
• and gave her my check for 41 cents. She didn’t think it would be honored, so I took it to the cashier myself and demanded pay, as I was
not coming back in the morning. “ No, ma’am,” said that functionary, “you don’t get it. Gome round on the 20th, and I’ll hunt you
   n
up.
   At 5:30 work ceased. Each girl had to sweep out her place, clean
and oil the machine, and return her basket and check. I paid a nickel
to have my corner swept, and, finding it impossible to wash up sans
towel and soap, I got under my veil and rang the elevator. The press- er8 laughed and told me to try the stairs—five flights. Down I went. At the second I went into the salesroom to buy a jersey. One of the
firm waited on me; his magnanimity was sublime. The identical black jersey that I had received 5 cents for finishing was offered to me at $2; I declined. By way of interest, one hundred dozen garments are turned out of the factory every day in the year. As near as I could learn, the salaries average $4 a week, but plenty of grown women are
not allowed to earn over 28 cents a day.
Work begins at 7:30 a. m. and 12:30 p. m. Any one five minutes
late, working on time, is fined an hour's pay, and for the loss of an hour the pay of half a day is knocked off. Piece-workers who are late are
kept idle from one to three hours. A girl who loses her ticket forfeits
pay for the entire work, notwithstanding the entry is on the books of
the firm.
CHAPTER IY.—A MODERN SLAVE-PEX.
A DAY'S EXPERIENCE IN A CHICAGO CLOAK FACTORY—LEFT IN A FOUL AND FILTHY
CORKER OF THE WORK-ROOM UNTIL OUTRAGED NATURE SUCCUMBS—AFTER HOURS OF DRUDGERY THE BOSSES REFUSE TO ADVANCE CAR-FARE TO A NEEDY SERF—TILE AIR, BRUTALITY AND THE PRIVILEGES OF EARNING BARELY ENOUGH TO KEEP SOUL AND BODY TOGETHER—EATING POOR CRACKERS AND WORKING FOR TWO MONTHS IN ORDER TO GET A PAIR OF SHOES.
ONE of the chance acquaintances I made at the jersey factory, reports Miss Nelson, had worked three days for a. firm whom we will here call Grinder &amp; Co., on Market street, and received 65 cents
for her labors about ten days after leaving. One-third of 65 cents is 21} cents.
   That is the way Grinder &amp; Co. solve the problem; but the question is one that capital, Christianity and civilization are invited to analyze.
   “ Don't never go to Grinder's,” the little girl said, “ it's an awful
place. ”
   On Saturday I tumbled out of bed at 6 a. m. and donned my factory clothes. On the way down town the street-car met with an eight-minute
obstruction in the shape of a load of bricks, and when I reached the manufacturing establishment of Grinder &amp; Co. it was 8:32 o’clock. The
elevator took me up one story and I was told to “get out.” I told the
boy at the rope that I wished to go up to the work-room.
   “ You're too late,” he s&amp;id. “ Have to take the freight elevator down at the back of the store.99
   Down I walked, as directed, past long tables that towered with long cloak 8, dolmans, ulsters, jackets and short wraps ; past two or three busy, unobserving clerks; past a pair of forbidding-looking men, who glared at me from under their black hats and blacker brows; past an
earthen-gray stringy crash towel that waved at half-mast above a dirty
wash-basin; past a tier of closets that emitted a stifling odor, and on down to the packing-room. I waited for a big, lusty packer to finish
pummeling the mischievous little Swede who ran the elevator, and was carried up to the top floor with a box of cloth. When the car landed I found myself at the extreme end of a room 50x180 feet, in an inclosure of wire-fence, packing-boxes and cutting-boards—beyond and between
82
which I could see perhaps two hundred persons, mostly women, bent
oyer machines, and working as only slaves ever work. The thundering
noise made by the machinery deadened every other sound, even that
made by the cutters as they ran their heavy shears through the satin and muslin trimmings. Sixteen persons passed me—men in undershirts, trousers and slippers, with work in their hands; men in business suits, with work in their brains; girls of thirteen in rags and death-like pallor, with work in their arms; older and paler girls and still older and paler women, some with white hair and spectacles, carrying work to be pressed, examined, altered, or checked. Nobody noticing me, I asked a pretty little girl who was cutting a bolt of satin into
cuff-lining to direct me to the forewoman, and was told to go and sit down till she came. I had hardly arranged myself on an empty box when a playful young man capsized my throne and spilled me/ in a heap of unmade cloaks. My first impulse was for revenge, but, remembering that I was a poor girl looking for work, I contented myself by petting my damaged left knee and right elbow. While mentally photographing the miserable, little, bullet-headed sapling who had caused my trouble, a young woman brought me a chair and placed it in a corner, which convenient spot happened to be off a narrow passage leading to the work-room proper. My nose was not long in scenting a row of closets that walled the south side of the passage-way. Overhead was a pasteboard sign with “ No Admission to the Work-Room,” printed in large, black letters. There was no place beyond where I could sit or stand without being in the way, unless I went back into the freight elevator, so I resolved to stick it out.
   For almost two hours I sat in the dark, filthy place with a handkerchief over my mouth and nose, waiting for the forewoman to come and admit me to the shop. I watched the poor girls pass and repass, their broken shoes slipping up and down with every step, and their ragged skirts often catching new gaps from the nails of the packing-boxes. Just as I was beginning to get myself in a state of passivity, as prescribed by Mrs. Eddy, and was comparing the foul smell of the closets with the wholesome, healthy atmosphere of South Park, something in my head
seemed to give way and the whole factory turned into a colossal whirligig. The big goose of the presser and the little irons of the press girls began to play tag, and machines, operators, finishers, wire-forms, cutters, examiners, messengers, models, forewomen, teachers and firm, all joined in the merry-go-round. To escape being knocked in the head by &amp;two-8tory press-board I clutched a little stitcher, who said: “You ain’t sick, is you?”
   I gaessed I was. Bringing me a tin cup fall of water, she departed,
saying she’d “ be docked if she didn’t go.”
   An old man with grey hair and glasses showed me to the freight ele- yator,and I was let down to the second story. When I reached the staircase I sat down on the top step to recover. A portly man with a straw hat, fall beard, broad shoulders, and a suit of mixed goods, mistaking
me for a tramp, came oat from the stock and informed me that “ no peddlers are allowed on the premises. Move off.”
   I moved off, determined to return another day.
€t
Boy, don’t you take her down! Don’t go down! do you hear? I’ll
discharge you if you let her escape.”
   There I was in the freight elevator, with my day’s work in my arms, and the wire screen separating me from the furies of the proprietor’s wife, her forewoman, the second assistant, and the bookkeeper.
   It was 5:30 o’clock Tuesday afternoon. I had made a big, black cloth cloak all but sewing on the buttons, had resigned my position as slave-stitcher, and had asked to be paid off. I had been refused by the
quartette outside of the elevator screen, and so was on my way to the head of the firm, work in arms.	‘
   At 7:40 o’clock in the morning, I had rolled my hat in my factory jacket, and, stowing the bundle away in one of the holes designed for that purpose, presented myself at the office, a square of six feet near the center of the work-room inclosed in a wire fence, where the forewoman
and an examiner were trying on two models the finished cloaks of the previous day. The models were tall, rather fine-looking girls. They
learned, received $8 a week, and did nothing but "try on and look at
themselves in the glass,” representing the highest class of factory girls. The forewoman, who jerked these tall, animate figures fore and aft to
see the front of a beaver “ empress/’ or the back of a seal-plash “milady,” was very nicely dressed in a black sateen figured with crosses of white. And, oh, how she talked! In dislocated English, in a shrill,
raspi ng voice, compared to which the notes of a peahen would be me
lodious. My steady gaze annoyed her, and, stopping at the hem of a long
coat she was inspecting, she asked:
   “ Why are you sitting there so much ? ”
   I told her I wanted work. Bidding me “ come along,” she pushed me with anything but motherly tenderness toward the desk, and told
€€
Rosy” to give me “ von of them samples.”
   I took a place with nine others, who were waiting for “ Rosy” to pro*
vide them with more work, and fell to studying my neighbors. “ Rosy,” the girl who kept the shop-book, gave out the work and trimmings, and
properly checked it all, may have been fourteen years old. She was short in stature, work having stunted her growth, and emaciated in face and
*
figure. Her hands were black with dye from handling the bundles of
work.
   “I can’t give any of you work till Mary comes back,” she said. “ She's gone down to tell John to send up some."
   I placed a small box on the counter containing some Graham wafers and a lemon, which, being pushed across the board, attracted Rosy's attention. She uncovered the box.
“ Look at the lunch," she said, and a bunch of heads came together
to see.
   “ And a thimble," said a blonde.	^
   “Yes, and scissors. Oh, and the little watch! And whose is it?"
     € Them's awful nice cakes," observed a little creature of about thirteen years old.	v
I offered the child a cracker, and when she refused I pressed it on her till a hungry little friend said: “ She daresn't. She'll be fined if she
eats before the whistle."
When Mary came up I was entered on Rosy's book, given a number,
and a “ Homer."
   “How much does a € Homer' pay?" I asked.
Rosy didn’t know. Neither did the teacher. I went to the forewoman and was told to get out of her way. Persisting in knowing what
revenue the “ Homer" would bring, the attenuated, corset-cramped cc forelady " asked me to go away and find out any particulars when Mrs.
Grinder returned. The teacher gave me a chair at a long, low table with fifteen girls on either side, and asked me where I had" worked before. I mentioned the jersey factory.
   “ Make cloaks?" she asked.
   “ No. Jerseys."
   “ Did you never make a cloak?"
   “ Never."
   “ Oh, you'll have a hard time!"
   Thirty pairs of eyes looked at me.
   “ Can you sew ? " I was asked.
   “ You bet."
This bit of slang captured the teacher, and set me on a comfortable plane with my neighbors. Reversing the tactics of Ella Wheeler Wil-
cox, I began at the hardest task first, and got the blonde-haired teacher to show me how to arrange the collar. It was a rolling affair that was
attached to a cape, and had to be double-faced with satin. The bands were cut on the bias, and novice-like I stretched the first one and had to rip it off. Three times I ripped it and sewed it, and when I showed it to a girl at my right, she said: “ It ain’t right. She'll pull it off.”
   “ Would yon tell me how to fix it ?” I asked.
   “ Oh, I can’t. Go to Miss	She screamed to Miss —— to
come. Despairing of her aid, I made another attempt.
   “ I’d show you if I had time,” my neighbor explained, “ but I’ve
been on this cloak two and one-half days, and it’s only 45 cents.”
   There are chords in a woman’s heart which are struck by accident only—strange, varying strings which, remaining mute to most earnest and passionate appeals, respond at once to the slightest and most casual touch. I sympathized with the poor little woman, who turned about
and opened her heart to me.
   “ It’s an awful hard place to work in,” she said. “ Prices are going down all the time, and the girls can hardly earn anything. Yesterday
was pay-day. We’re paid the 1st and 15th. I had only $6.10 coming to me for the two weeks. I have the toothache all the time, and I am a
month at the dentist’s. He's filling my teeth with cement, and I don’t have
anything coming to me when I pay him. All I keep out of my wages
is 30 cents for car fare. I live out on Fifteenth and Robey streets, and can’t always walk in the morning, and get here at 7:45. Sometimes I do, but I never ride home. If I didn’t live home I’d—I’d—I’d—I’d
*
starve. I would. What’d prevent ? ”
   Interested in our talk, a pretty, brown-eyed girl across the table told us that she had been trying to get a pair of shoes since June. “ I live
at Englewood, and have to keep out $1.25 for car fare,” she continued.
“ Monday I took out this 40-cent cloak, and it isn’t done yet. I took it to the forelady this morning, and she said it was all right. Just a minute ago I showed it to her and she ripped all these plaits and pulled the bustle out. I’ll not be able to get it done to-night, I know. Last fortnight I made only $4.20.”
   “ Here, you girls, stop your talking and do your work, or I’ll have to fine you,” said the teacher.
   “You’re new, and I’ll excuse you,” she said, turning to me, “but
you mustn’t talk any more. Where’s your collar ? Oh! you have the hooks and eyes on the wrong side. Rip them off and put the hooks on
the right and the eyes on the left. Then press out your seam.”
   I took my turn at the gas-stove, skirmished round for a piece of paper or a rag large enough for a holder, burned my finger, and came near burning a hole in “ Homer’s ” neck. When I went back to my chair the little Englewood girl was in tears. She had the fur down the front of her cloak too tight and was ripping it off for the third time. The fur may have been nine-tenths wool, but so uncertain was the hair that the girl had taken a fine comb from her box and was trying to comb
up the nap to hide the needle-line. Her companion* Mary, had been in equally hard luck* Five times she had taken her brown “ mi-lady ” to the forewoman, and five times had come back with it. First the felting was not thick enough; next the color was wrong; the third time the buttons were not plumb; the fourth complaint was lodged against a crescent bustle, Mrs. Stein having expressed a preference for two small square
bags, and finally the ornaments on the shoulders and fronted arts were
not straight. Mary was a pudgy young Irish maiden on whom the men and the world in general had soured.
   “ What will I do when Pm old ? HI be an old maid and live by
myself,” she remarked. t€ Pm saving to buy a house for that time.
Good Lord, I haven’t saved a cent in three years. I’m here now two years, but Pm going to get another place. Here's my third day on this
rag of a cloak that only pays 60 cents. Yesterday I got $0.10 for the fifteen days of July. Pm sick of it now. Where do I live ? I have a room on Bleeker street. I pay $1.50 a week for it and $1 for food.
After I take the price of lunches and car fare from the rest I haven’t enough to pay for washing the bed-clothes.”
The teacher heard the best part of this account, and, coming over to
our table, put her arms about the neck of the morose little worker, and
said: “ Don’t get blue; you’ll do better in a day or two. ”
At noon the whistle blew, and we stopped for lunch. Some of the hands made tea and coffee on the gas stoves, but not a soul left the shop
but Mrs. Grinder and the models.
   You pampered daughters of fashion, you children of ease, you epicureans, who enjoy soups, entrees, fritters, roasts, pastries, could you but see the meal spread out at noon in this factory,the chances are there would be a diminution of your fastidiousness.
   No. 99 was a pretty, brown-eyed, happy girl, with curly hair and a merry, brave, good face. She had two cuts of cherry pie that did not
aggregate a surface as wide as her hand. She finished the juicy crust,
and I insisted on her eating a pair of my Graham wafers. Ninety-nine had a head-ache and was going off for an afternoon in Lincoln Park.
The girl next to her, who said she was “ the very devil, ” devoured two links of Frankfort sausage and a pear. A near neighbor had a slice of brown bread and two tomatoes, and the girl she talked with ate green
apples and soda-cracker.
   At five minutes past twelve we had eaten, drank, and were at work
again. Many of the girls went to the sink to wash their arms, necks and
faces, sconr their teacups or coffee cans, and comb their hair. While I was exploring the toilet (!) section two men came in and I scampered.
A nice arrangement this, but no one seemed to mind it.
   The excellent light that I bad noted at other places I missed at Grinder's, where the ceiling is low and the ventilation and light inadequate* A skylight cuts the center of the roof, but, with the curtains
drawn to keep out the burning sunlight, the machine operators had difficulty in threading their needles.
   “ Please do not take any paper, ” was the notice pasted above a pile
of work ready for delivery. It seems the girls were in the habit of going to this pile for bits of paper in which to wrap their lunch-box or an old
shop skirt, and when the “searcher” found it difficult to look into the
parcels for the possible spool of 2-cent thread,the firm took this method
of stopping the practice.
   Over the iron sink was a placard warning the girls against “throwing any slops into this sink under penalty of 50 cents. ”
   This rather ambiguous motto hung above the hat rack: “ In order
to protect the lanches of our employ6s, no eating is allowed till 12 o’clock.
Anyone breaking this rule will be fined.”
   On the opposite wall hung the literary gem of the factory.	Here it
is:
•	*• Ladies and Gentlemen it is your interest and that of your	• neighbors that no talking is allowed requested that whoever	:
•	talks loud is fined 10 cents. ”	i
   Another legend informed the army of martyrs that Grinder &amp; Go. had “ No goods at retail* Any one wanting to purchase must ask Mr.
	. ” Apropos of the subject, I learned that a girl paid $14 for a garment that I feel sure could have been bought for $9 in any retail house.
She took it on the easy-payment plan, $1 a week, and for three months lived on tea-dust and broken crackers. “The tea was 15 cents a pound, ” she told me, “ and I got (he crackers at a Thirteenth street bakery, two pounds for 5 cents. It was a heavy cloak, though, and I had it on the bed nights. What did I do with my money? Oh! God,
bat you’re fresh. One dollar and fifty cents for the room, 60 cents for three baskets of coal, 30 cents for car fare, $1 for the housekeeping, and
$1 each week for the cloak. Sometimes I only made $6 in two weeks, and often when it rained or snowed I took the car home, and then I run behind. *’
I finished my cloak about 5:20 o’clock, and carried it to the desk to
see about haying it examined. I showed it to the teacher.
€t Your work is very neat,” she said, “and you have nice corners.
Now I'll try you on a jacket.”
“ Thank you; I guess I won’t work any more. If you will get me
the buttons I’ll sew them on and go home.”
She called me her dear, told me to try a month or so, that I could earn $4 a week before next year, and finally said that she couldn’t give
me the buttons because the cloak had to go downstairs to the pressers.
     tc Well, I’ll wait until it comes up.”
   “ But it won’t come up maybe for a week,” she remarked.
   “How will I get my pay, then?”
     € You can’t get paid till the 1st. Go and see the forelady.”
   That party told me to go away and let her alone.
   “ But I have no car fare,” I said, by way of ^mollification. Without mollifying a bit, she asked:
   “ What’s that to me? I ain’t no car company.”
   “ I am not going to work here any more. I want to go home. I live far out, and must have car fare. Won’t you take my order-ticket and advance me thirty-five cents?”
   “ Thanks. I take no orders from you,’’and giving her wiry features
another twist she left me. “ Rosy ” called for the cloak, which I hugged
in my arms and refused to surrender. I carried my woolly burden to the bookkeeper, told my trouble, and asked for an order for my pay.
   “I can’t give you an order,” said that party. “ We don’t pay but
twice a month. See Mrs. Grinder.”
   Mrs. Grinder runs the shop, and runs it with shrewdness. A dozen
or fifteen years ago she graduated from a local factory to become the
wife of the proprietor. She has a beautiful home up on Dearborn avenue and several children, all of whom are cared for by competent servants* Mr. Grinder manages the business, and Mrs. Grinder bosses
the cutters, the pressers, the finishers, the operators, and the clerks, forewomen and models connected with the factory. She is a yellowhaired little woman, with a sharp voice, a trim, graceful figure, generously jeweled hands, and features that were not addicted to much
relaxation. And her eyes! Nothing escapes them, sewing or sewers: Nothing goes that is not right—“precisely right,” to use her own words. Every girl has a number, which is pnt on the cloak she is to make. If there is a flaw or false stitch in the work, all Mrs. Grinder has to do is to scream ont the number on the ticket, and the hapless girl advances with more or less timidity for the never-failing tongue- lashing.
   While I stood at the bookkeeper's desk, with the finished “ Homer” in my arms, Mrs. Grinder appeared^ She was gorgeous in black satin,
witha goblin blue basque trimmed with gold lace, and fastened at the
throat with a gold serpentine brooch. In deference to all this finery, I
began with some degree of obsequiousness:
   “ I beg your pardon; is this Mrs. Grinder?” *
     94 That’s my name,” was the answer, as she disappeared in a pack ing- box and hauled up a handful of patterns. Seeing that she did not intend to refer to me, I took a tighter grip on “ Homer ” and plunged into the fray.
   “ I made this cloak to-day, and wish to sever my relations with your
very excellent establishment,” I continued.
   “ Then put that cloak over to the presser, and go.”
   “ I want to be paid.”
   “ You can not. Pay-days are the 1st and 15th.”
     441 will have my pay now. What do you give for the ‘ Homer V ”
   “ I do not know.”
   “ Who does? ”
   Here she screamed to the forewoman to know why she was “ troubled
by such a creature as this.” The party addressed labeled me with a few choice epithets in hysterical English, and, for an instant, I thought
Mrs. Grinder was going to jump on me.
   “Give me that cloak!” she demanded with heaving breast and
swelling nostrils.
     44	Not until you give me my money,” I replied.
   She called me insolent, beggarly and worthless, and when I told her that a woman who had been reared a factory girl should have some pity for the class, she became a model for the queen of tragedy.
   The audience was speechless and the forewoman so affected that she
rattled like an agitated bagful of clothes-pins. While the lookers-on were waiting for something to turn up, the elevator ascended, and I
stepped into the car, still hugging “ Homer.” I was going to see Mr.
Grinder, when his wife raised her voice and jeweled hand and ordered
the boy not to take me down. “ Homer,” the boy and I stood on the
inside of the wire screen and looked out, and the three women and the bookkeeper stood on the outside and looked in.
“ Raise the door, boy. Your number's 101, isn't it ?” An armistice,
I thought, and answered: “ You have said it.”
   “ Go and sew on the buttons and get your pay—75 cents.”
   I was escorted to the desk, Rosy counted out thirty-six buttons, and I went back to my chair to button “ Homer.” It was 5:45 o'clock, and the hands were beginning to leave. The cashier would be gone, too, in fifteen minutes, and it was not possible to sew on three dozen buttons in that time. However, I had made up my mind not to surrender “ Homer” till I was paid. The teacher, bless her fair hair, came and
helped me to space the button-line, and we had three sewed on when Mrs. Grinder appeared and mentioned her pride at haviHg been factory- born .
   “ You need not put those buttons on. I'll make you a present of
the work.”
   I declined her offer, and was told to go to the desk and get paid. The
bookkeeper made out a check and asked for the cloak, which I gave up with alacrity. When I got in the elevator the boy asked if I had a
pass.
   “No.”
   “Then I'll have to search you.”
   “ For what ? ”
   “ Stolen goods.”
   I defied him to touch me, and the presence of the bookkeeper averted another war.
   At the desk I was identified, and received seventy-five cents for making a $35 cloak. I went up stairs again to'Mrs. Grinder and threw five nickels on the board for the unfortunate girl who sewed the buttons on my cloak. The rest of my wages I gave to the teacher, the only
person connected with the concern who had shown me any kindness.
   The fidelity of the girls passed entirely unnoticed. Not a word of commendation came from the manager or her assistant, who were most prodigal of reproof. By the men and boys these poor, patient, uncomplaining shop-girls were pushed about in the elevators, on the stairs and in the narrow aisles, like so many sheep, and three little girls, two Marys and Frances, were made the slaves of everybody.
How these girls live in winter is a mystery. With few exceptions,
their dresses were poor and insufficient, coarse and shapeless. Many
were torn, and showed the stitches of thread and cord drawn across the
holes.
   But worse than broken shoes, ragged clothes, filthy closets, poor light, high temperature and vitiated atmosphere was the cruel treatment by the people in authority. There are pains that rack a sensitive nature to which no physical agony can be compared, and shots from malicious eyes that fatally wound but raise no cry of injury. There are robberies of a gentle life that beggar peace and joy, and cuts of hatred that murder forever the sweet faith that belongs to woman’s nature.
m
THE HQM£ OF A JEWISH TAILOR IN NEW YORK. Fn«n a Photograph.
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
*
CHAPTER V.—CHILDREN DOOMED TO DRUDGERY.
*
GIRLS OF TENDER Y EARS WASTENG AWAY THEIR LIVES IN A SO-CALLED MODERN
DRY GOODS EMPORIUM—ILL-FED, WAN-FACED CHILDREN WORKING FROM 7:45 TO 6:30 FOR MISERLY COMPENSATION.
THE chapters immediately preceding deal with actual experience
in factories and shops, to which the general public have no access. But right on the most crowded thoroughfare of the Western metropolis, in a retail dry goods establishment, which invites the public through every device known to the catchpenny advertiser, may be witnessed scenes of modern slavery even more abhorrent; and the place selected
by Miss Nelson for investigation is not the only one of its kind in
Chicago, nor ?s Chicago the only city in the Union where such conditions exist.
   Says Miss Nelson: For dismal surroundings, economy of comforts, and heartless treatment, to the store in which I spent the greater part of Friday belongs the palm.
   I did not work in that establishment, although I tried very hard to do so. I was in the store at eight o'clock in the morning, as arranged
with one of the managers, who had partially promised to hire me. “ One
of the girls in the hosiery department,” he had said, “ is sick, and if
she doesn't come back Friday morning, I will try you.”
   I could not find the gentleman, although I hunted the main floor and the floors above and below. My plan of fluctuation was to take the elevator up one story and walk down, then ride up two and walk down the third flight. In that way I took in the enthre store and a great part
of the employes. I began at the bottom and spent a full hour in the
basement, where I saw so much and suffered so much that the upper
floors had no surprises for me. In the first place the atmosphere was
almost unendurable.
   Out in the open air not a breeze was stirring, and the heat was sizzling. Down where I was I could not see a single opening to admit the air, fiery as it was, excepting the open door at the extreme southeast
corner of the floor, leading up a short flight of steps to the sidewalk.
About this doorway so many goods were piled and draped and hung that
the passage of air was obstructed. There must have been forty, and
43
there may have been eighty, clerks, cash boys and girls on this floor,
and five times that number of customers surged in and out under the glaring rays of gas-jets and electric burners. Babies squirmed and cried under the suffocating heat; children screamed and fretted; men and women fanned and wiped their faces, but the little cash-girls and the languid clerks endured their prison uncomplainingly. Add to the heat from gas-jets, electric lights and machinery the exhalations from so many people, the moldy smell from damaged goods, the dampness of the freshly mopped floor, the fames from a stray disinfectant, and the mildew and earthy odor that lurked in dark corners, and you haye some idea of the quarters in which customers are invited to look for bargains,
and where helpless, honest, free-born American men and women, boys and girls, are forced to work for clothes and bread.
   What about the soul? It’s mockery to mention it to these slaves in
such a dungeon.	•
   On a rude plank door painted black is the word “ Ladies/’ The irony of it! “Serfs” would be less impertinent and “bond-women” or “ drudges ” better than either. .
   The door yields to my touch, and I enter the toilet and cloak room. The atmosphere is so intense and the effluvia so offensive that I am almost stifled. A window about eighteen inches sqpare has been cut in the
side of the staircase leading from the street, and here I stand, my face turned up to the clouds of dust that float in from the feet and skirts of the passing customers. By and by I get accustomed to the foulness, and turn around to explore the place. The floor is black and wet from recent mopping; the janitor has swept all the previous day’s rubbish in from the basement, and it forms a big pile behind the door. There is only one gas-jet in the room, and I do not see the wet sweepings until I have stepped in them. On either side of the inclosure are the cloak-boxes, communication to which is offered by a window a foot square. A young and very pretty colored woman is in one section, and in the opposite window is a little boy, possibly thirteen years old. All the female help pass their hats, wraps, and lunches through these windows, and they are put in a cubby-hole, the number of which corresponds to the number of the clerk. The smell of mold forcibly assails the senses, and, mingled with the foul odor from the adjoining closets, the effect on the lunches must be left to the imagination. On the east side of the partition is the toilet inclosure, built like the rest, under the pavement; but for the perforated coal-hole covers overhead the place would be pitch dark. It is damp, dirty, and smelly, the stone sidewalk forming
the ceiling and the gray flag-stones the floor. The closets, fonr or five in number, have not even the luxury of doors, and in a space at one end is a dirty little iron sink into which runs a stream of water. As only two girls can approach the narrow trough for water at a time, it is not hard for the reader to understand how great a luxury this single stream of clear, cool water is to the slave-girls. At one time I counted twenty-eight girls in this filthy little hole, which is unfit for cattle and in which no man would water a faithful dog.
   When I had accustomed myself to the deadly smell that pervaded
the place it was 9:30 o'clock, and the girls were beginning to come in and wash their hands and clean up after arranging their stock. About the little mirror were seven girls, some combing their hair, some dressing it, and all trying to get a peep at their wan faces. The closets were crowded, and while three young girls were washingl&amp;t the sink five moved about with bits of soap in their hands, their arms and faces covered with lather. The soap may have been furnished by the house, but of the absence of towels I am positive. Most of the girls had their own comb, soap, and towel, and where do you suppose they carried them?
   In the bosom of their dresses.
   I cautioned a girl who had opened the front of her waist preparatory to putting the damp towel so near her breast, but she only laughed and said, “ Nothin'll hurt me.”
But it is wet and may cause a lung trouble.''
   “ Indeed it won't. I used to put it here all last winter, and it didn't hurt me. When it was awful cold I wore it home, and I never even had a cold.” As she spoke she folded the little towel, and, laying it against her under-waist, buttoned her dress and went to the hole in the north cloak-box for a glass of lemonade. I told her I was very thirsty, and asked for a drink.
   “ Oh, you have to pay. It's three cents a glass.”
   The colored girl and her little white slave had a bucket full of the
beverage—a very excellent article by the way—which they retailed at the price stated. The ebony vender refused to sell to me till I convinced
her that I expected to begin in the hosiery stock as soon as the manager came down. The girl with the wet damask in her bosom drained her glass to the last drop, ate the slices of lemon, rind and pulp, and with the help of her finger transferred every grain of undissolved sugar to her mouth. She lapped the mouth of the glass with her tongue, and when the boy took it from the ledge it was as dry as could be. I could
not get her to confide her salary, but she said: “ It a’n’t nothing like
♦5. For two years I only got $3, bat now I have more.”
I found a girl named Bessie in the closet-room lying against the wall,
the very picture of death. Her face had no more color in it than a china cup, her lips were blue, dark lines increased the brilliancy of her
big blue eyes, and her hands were cold and clammy. She told me she
was “awful sick.” but her mother made her come because she didn’t
*
want her to lose her place.
   “ The floor-walker ’ud leave me go home if I ast him, but I haven't any car-fare and I don’t want to walk. I lost my tea money and all cornin’ down in the cars this morning. I was asleep.”
   I offered to pay her car-fare.
   “ No; if I ride in the air I’ll be better before I get to the bridge.”
   I bought her a glass of lemonade and gave her “ tea pennies ” for a
week, after which we became quite confidential.
“ I get $2 a week here, and give it to my mother to buy meat. Sometimes I ride home, but them’s the days that I don’t buy tea, ’cause it costs
too much for both. The tea is 3 cents a cup, and the car fare, if you ride both ways, is 10 cents, and that’s 13 cents.”
   Seventy-eight cents subtracted from $2 would leave a precious small sum for meat.
   “The most I ever spend is 50 cents a week. That’s how much mother lets me keep out. Oh, they’re kind of good to us. Last night when it rained the manager gave nickels to the cash-girls that didn’t have car-fare nor gossamers. But I guess he’ll keep it out of their wages
pay-day. Some of the clerks don’t be good to us. They pull us everywhere and push us when we don’t go fast, and we never dast ride in the elevator. The clerks can, but the cash-girls has to walk. They don’t fine us if we come late, though, and they do the clerks, some 15 cents and some 25 cents, and if any of us is sick we lose the whole day out of our wages. The one I like most is Miss Oannon; she is awful good; she
puts three lumps in the tea, and trusts the girls when they haven’t any
tea pennies. ”
   A larger girl, possibly nineteen,showed me.her odd shoes. “I’m wearing this one with the tips to break it in. I have to stand all day, and my feet are so sore I can hardly bear a new shoe. I got these new ones in June. Oh, they’ll last till Christmas I guess. My salary is $5 a week, but I don’t save anything. My mother takes it all for the groceries. 1 don’t know what I’m going to do. Clerking is very hard, but I can’t sew or I’d go and work in a neck-tie factory where girls
get $10. Do housework ? No, I wouldn’t like to live out. I can’t cook, anyway. I could mind the children, but nurse girls only earn $12 a
month. Yes, I know they have their board. No, not their washing. If you don’t help the kitchen girls, when they tell you, you have to do
your own washing, and I’d rather do that than have them bossing me.”
   A mite of a cash-girl who wore broken slippers said she had better shoes at homes, but it was so hard running all day that she couldn’t wear them.
   One of a cluster of girls from the grocery floor, who is earning $3 and $3.50 a week, said: “ People talk bad about this store, but it’s as good as any of them. We needn’t be at the store till eight in the morning, and they never fine us if we’re late. Lots of times when I have been sick the floor-walker has told me to go out and walk round, and if I didn’t feel better when I came back he let me go homev If it rains
the manager lends us car-fare. He never said to pay him back, but I always did. We get 'p. m.’s,’ too, and last week I made 80 cents extra.
At noon we can take forty minutes and go where we like.”
     €€ Why don’t you eat up-stairs in the lunch-room ? ” I asked.
   “ Well, ’cause the benches haven’t any backs, and it’s nicer to go out for a change. ”
   Like “ the wards of Jarndyce,” caged up in this place of abomination
that the heavenly compassion of the proprietors have provided for their hapless “ladies,” I met hope, youth, squalor, want, disease, despair, woe,
cunning, innocence, rags, beauty, bravery and industry variously personified, in all stages of miserable girlhood and womanhood. Much of the talk I heard was coarse, indicative of ignorance and low breeding; but I saw no evidence of depravity or viciousness. 0 ne hears a great deal
about the purchase of the shop-girl, but the insinuations are as false as they are base. The skeptic has only to look at the garb of these poor pale-faced, stoop-shouldered girls to admit their virtue. Vice is better dressed. I spent an hour or more on the main floor, watching the
swarming customers joggle one another and haggle with the young girls who waited on them. So many people in the densely-stocked, overcrowded, ill-ventilated room polluted the atmosphere, making the strong
weak aud the weak sick. Every available foot of space was utilized,
some of the counters consisting of common pine boxes on the side of which emaciated children measured fringes, trimmings, ribbons, and cheap stuffs. One of these “ troughs,” filled with Hamburg edging, was placed between the two elevators, and the little girls in charge were knocked and pushed about by the hurrying crowd in a most unseemly
manner, I did not see any girl sitting down, nor any provision for a
momentary rest. There was no mistaking the poverty of the homes
from which these hapless young creatures came, for their garments were
old and shabby and in many cases unclean, unkempt and unsuitable.
Worse than their clothes was the unkempt condition of the hair and
person of some young girls. As in the adjoining establishment, I saw girls waiting on customers in their stocking feet. I saw the floor-walk- ers push and drag the young girls about, and the managers bully and drive both. One of these dignitaries, a tall, argu8-eyed blonde with bent shoulders and a drooping head, was the right man in the right place.
Everybody dispersed at his coming. His scowl was something terrorizing, and had I been a subordinate and given the choice of the lash and
one of his glances of reproof, I should have taken the former. There
was another head, a tall, compactly-built brunette, almost as formidable,
who had » pair of eyes that seemed to bum holes in everything and everybody contemplated.
   The same sweltering crowd harassed the clerks on the second, third,
and fourth floors, and on the fifth the sight of so many little drudges
selling groceries or handling goods made one feel ashamed of the civilization that fosters such a condition of woman. The younger girls in many instances wore big check aprons to screen rather than save the worthless little dresses beneath. It was harrowing to see these children,
boys of ten and twelve, and fragile girls of eleven, twelve, thirteen and
fourteen, carrying boxes of soap, starch and candles, packages of buckwheat, salt and hominy, and cans filled with oils, syrups, vinegars, and the like. The men in charge had no hesitancy in commanding these
transfers, calling Maggie and Mary as often as John or Dick to make
the removal. I saw one little boy of slight build, with a sweet but very
sad face, dragging a bag of coffee that would have been a strain on the muscles of a strong man, and a little Swede girl, who said she was thirteen in March, had a box full of canned vegetables in her arms, the weigh t of which made her black in the face.
   There is a ruin of youth and beauty which is more appalling than age, and into such ruin have the youthful grace, vigorous beauty, and the charm of gladness and trust of these immature lives fallen. There was no inclination to frolic, no merry bantering, and no semblance of childish glee among the little serfs.
   On the fifth floor, in the rear, is a small room which is used as a caft
by the female help of the store. The furniture consists of two narrow
tables and three long benches extending the length of the apartment.
The benches have no rung or rest lor the back, and here the young women and check-girls sit at noon oyer their lunch. On the wall is an
expansive sheet of 6cru paper bearing this inscription:
   “ Female clerks and check-girls: You are requested not to eat on the stairs or anywhere else. Tou will keep to the right coming up, and to the left going down. You will not talk on the way nor take hold of each other’s hands, but walk by yourselves. Any one breaking this rule will be discharged.”
   Apropos of signs, I forgot to say that in the basement where the cloak-room is designated this notice appeared in bold relief:
| The girl who took the silk umbrella Saturday is known. If it	\
\ is not returned at once she will have to take the consequences.	:
   •	• Another less conspicuously placed sign read: ^
•	All female employes will be ready for work at 7:45 a. m. under \
\	penalty.	•
   The young lady who has charge of the kitchen is the good angel of
the place. She is a plump, nice-looking person of splendid presence, with mild eyes, a firm face, sweet voice, and a heart brimful of motherly tenderness. She makes tea and lemonade which, with fresh milk, are retailed at 3 cents a glass. The tea has cream in it, and the three lumps of sugar that go with each cup are a gastronomical treat to the little
ones, who drink the Japan first and save the sugar cubes for dessert.
Chapter VI.—Shok-Shop Slates.
LITTLE HEROINES WHO WORK FOR THREE MEALS, A ROOF AT NIGHT AND THEIR
CAR-FARE—DIRT AND WORK—No TIME FOR CHURCH OR FOR READING—
How THE LAWS CONCERNING CHILD LABOR ARE OPENLY EVADED.
IN all this wide, weary, work-a-day world there is not a better, brighter, nobler girl than the one who stitches, lines, binds and vamps your
slippers and shoes.
   She is a heroine if there ever was one outside of a civil or religious war. She knows nothing of self-love, nothing of fear, and nothing of her own just rights. Her life is made up of years of toil, months of
privation, and weeks of struggling and striving to keep up with the
rushing throng, ravenous for her bread and envious of her miserable position. She works from dawn almost to dusk, carrying every dollar
of her earnings to some wretched home in which abide parents, brothers and sisters—often, too, relatives having absolutely no claim on her,
	 «
none of whom love her, and none of whom show by word, act or deed
that her generosity, goodness and real nobility of soul are appreciated.
   She goes without shoes the best part of the year, albeit in the employ
of a shoe manufacturer; she goes without pretty dresses that younger sisters may be clad, and the money that should go to the purchase of the hundred little niceties that add so much to the beauty and charm and daintinessof budding womanhood is withheld for the purchase of family
flour or textbooks for the young children who are at school. What does
she get?
   Three meals a day, a roof at night, and car fare.
   Perhaps you think she doesn’t know any better, hence the bliss of
ignorance.
   Well, now, don’t be too sure about that.
   I have just been to one of the largest of Chicago’s shoe factories,
looking for work. The girls were crowded together like sheep in a
stock-yard pen. All were at machines. Some stitched sboe-lininge;
others lined the vamps and uppers; others “ taped;” a few worked but- ton-holes, and all the experienced hands turned the shoe. This consisted in hammering down the seams till the crash lining could be turned in and made “to lay smooth.” To accomplish this each girl had to
50
wield, not a wooden mallet, but a heavy iron hammer, from three to ten
*
strokes being necessary to flatten out the leather seam. This done, there
was the top facing to put in, the holes to be made, the buttons to be marked, and the same process repeated again and again until 5:30 o’clock. The wages vary.
   In order to get work I was told to begin at table work. That means
sewing on buttons—two stitches for each button, finishing button-holes, and pasting sock-lining in the sole of the shoe.
   How much? Two dollars a week.
   At the end of a year I would get a raise of $1. At the end of four
I would be given a machine and a yearly raise till I had reached $8, the
maximum wages for female help. But the proprietors didn’t need any
help, and I left the big, barn-like shop with its naked timber roof and
brick walls, glad to leave the leathery atmosphere and the hollow-eyed,
stoop-shouldered, miserably-clad men, youths and girls. Like their neighbors across the court, the firm disregards the necessity for modern conveniences. There are a few closets and a sink, and there all obligation ceases. Nothing is thought of the four flights of steps to climb, of the deafening machinery overhead, of the impure air and the dirty floors and stairs.
   As I was leaving the building I met two girls on the landing who asked, “What luck?” I told them there was no show for inexperienced girls.
   “ Oh, we’re broke in long ago. Worked for the Slipper Company,
four years. It’s a good enough place, but I got a lame wrist turning shoes. The hammering is too hard. I’ll take a machine, but I won’t
turn any more.
   “Oh, I make $6 a week. Began at table worK for $2.25. They raised me to $3 in six months; after that I got $3.50, then $4, then $4.50, then $5, and last January they gave me $6.
   “ We have six children, and I give all my money to my mother. My
father is a builder. He doesn’t have much work in the year, and winter times when he’s laid off 1 don’t have a cent to myself. Only car fare, that’s all. Sometimes I don’t have any new dress the whole year. My
sister is younger than me. She works at neckties and makes $9. We
two keep the family.
   “Fun? Any fun I have is walking once in awhile. We don’t go
out nights. Mother won’t let us. She makes us go to bed early so we
can get up early. We’re always up at six.
   “ I’d a good deal rather be a boy, because boys have a better time.
52
SHOE SHOP SLAVES.
They can keep their money if they want to, but girls have to give up all they make.
   “No, I don’t read the papers and I don’t go to chnrch either. Haven’t anything to wear. Most of the time I stay home and sew. My mother goes to chnrch.”
   At the factory of the Slipper Company, I took a machine and tried to stitch shoe linings by steam-power. I didn’t get on well. The girls were very good to me. One put my machine in order, and the way she handled it amazed me. She could not have been a day over sixteen, but she pulled off the belt, took out the shuttle, threw the whole top over on its side, and examined into the very bowels of the little engine, using a screw-driver, then the tension gage, and after tightening and loosening alternately, she oiled the whole thing, cleaned it, and set it up again. For more than thirty minutes she worked on a piece of
morocco before getting the right tension, bravely persisting, however,
till all was right, when she gave me a lesson, and went back to her own work. The steam was too much for me. I couldn’t manage it. It kept running off the seam, and I pressed my knee against the starting wheel to make it go slow till the buckle on my garter got red hot; Kate’s sister sat across the aisle making button-holes, and, seeing my helplessness, came over and gave me another lesson.
   “Take it slow,” she said, €€like this,” flying down the head seam like a flash of lightning. “ Don’t worry; you’ll learn. I learned myself. You must press the wheel real hard with your leg, and then it will go slow.”
   I thanked her, and for an hour pressed the wheels on the outer side of my right foreleg, which will suffer for at least a week. To add to my confusion, the foreman gave me his undivided attention. He was a slender man, thirty-five or so, with a face like Siegel, and a pipe in his mouth.
   The thread kept breaking, and at every attempt I ran off the cloth, raveling the edge, and getting very much disgusted at my clumsiness. Just as I was beginning to admire the graceful taciturnity and generous forbearance of the foreman, he told me I had “ better get out; ” but I begged for tolerance, and sewed away on a pair of rags for another hour. A second time I was told to quit, and again I begged for mercy, but when the wheel in the region of my knees began to burn, I threw down the few pairs of lining I had succeeded in stitching, and retired.
   The shop where I had my struggle with the steam-power was cut off from the rest of the factory by a partition. Along the windows looking
   south were the machines, making two rows or aisles, and set so closely
together that they almost touched. At each was a girl whose powers of endurance were seemingly no different' from the machine operated.
Some young girls sat at a cross table finishing button-holes, for which they were paid $3 and $4 a week. Men stood at side tables cutting out shoe and slipper uppers, and behind the machines were boys of twelve,
thirteen and fourteen years, cutting linings. Younger boys were employed in an adjoining department pasting sole-lining in the newly-made shoes, and scores of men were engaged soleing, heeling, shaping and polishing. The walls and ceilings were paneled with soot; oil dripped from
the rumbling machinery overhead, and the floors were as black as ink. Although I saw no evidence of rigid discipline, every man, boy and girl labored with more than conscientious zeal. The labor was serjile. Convicts could not have been more industrious with the prison lash curling
   about them. Work began at 7 o’clock, and, while I was wrestling with
   the steam, I saw a number of girls stop work and eat part of their lunch.
   Notwithstanding the patient fidelity and untiring industry of these people, their neglect is a disgrace to the manufacturers of Chicago. The closet in which I hung my hat was so dark that I had to find a nail with my hands. Thinking my eyes had been tardy in adjusting themselves to a low light, I remained in the hole long enough to know that nothing but feline optics would suffice to scan it. At the entrance was a triangular piece of looking-glass that some good soul had bolstered up
between nail-heads as a tribute to beauty. Neither the stairs nor hallways gave evidence of recent sweeping, and I would question the judgment of anyone venturing to assert that they had been scrubbed this
   year. The closets were in a shocking condition—unflushed, unswept, and abominating to the senses. Not only the outer door but the three inner doors were unhinged and lay in the filthy inclosure, obstructing the unfortunate girls who enter the place. I saw with my own eyes that the girls visited this model toilet-room in groups of not less than two, one acting as guardian for the others. At the very entrance to this filthy inclosure is the sink, a small iron affair, of the cheapest character, supplied with a single faucet.
Towels ? No, nor soap, neither! But who wants them? You can’t
wash in the dark, and although there is a window on the landing the dust and dirt that cover it are as good a shade as a curtain of brown Holland would be.
One of the girls told me she had been in the shop three years, and was ♦
54	SHOESHOP SLA VES.
getting $4 a week. “ Lots of the girls earn $5 and less, but some I
know get $7 and $8. They are old hands, and work on fine shoes.”
   At another factory, on the floor below, where I inquired for work, I received this edifying piece of information from the foreman:
   “No, I guess I can’t take you. If you were an experienced operator I could give you a job, but it won’t pay me to teach you. I can get little girls of twelve for $2.50, and all I want for $3.00 a week to finish. When
table work is dull I put them at the machine, and show them how to work it. The novelty attracts them, and 1 find they spend their noons and every spare minute in running up seams. In that way they soon pick up the work, and when I am satisfied that they can run a machine I give them one, raise their salary 50 cents or $1, and get raw girls again
to do the table work."
   Both firms might be reminded that there is some law relative to the hiring of child labor, and the necessity for fire-escapes.
   I found the physical condition of the girls much better than among
the cloak-makers, tailoresses and seamstresses, but in point of poverty all seem akin. The girls wore clothes that were ragged and dirty, many giving the very young girls the appearance of little sweeps. Worthless shoes were worn as much from necessity as from a sense of comfort, and nothing in the habits or habiliments of these little money-makers betrayed even the ordinary comforts of life.
CHAPTER VII.—THE SLAVES OF “LITTLE HELL.”
A DAY AMONG THE SERFS AND BOND-WOMEN IN THE SLOP-SHOPS OF CHICAGO—
SIX CENTS FOR FOUR HOURS OF UNCEASING TOIL IN A DIRTY, CROWDED
TAILOR’8 ROOM—CHILDREN WHO WASTE THEIR LIVES FOR $1.00 A WEEK—
MEN WHO GROW RICH AT THE EXPENSE OF HUMAN LIFE—-FACTORIES FROM WHICH THE MISERABLE, HELPLESS DRUDGES COULD NEVER ESCAPE IN CASE OF FIRE—TASK MASTERS WHO CAN NOT SPEAK ENGLISH HOLDING AMERICAN
LABORERS IN GRINDING BONDAGE.
IT was 7 a. M. by all the whistles in “Little Hell” when^I reached that section of the city in search of an opening in a slop-shop. The
streets were crowded with shop hands hurrying to their day’s work— men and boys with pipes in their mouths, carrying dinner pails or lunch-
baskets; little girls in groups of two and three in beggarly rags; young women and old women, some of them white-haired and stooped with
age, wearing shawls about their heads and shoulders, and the meanest
apologies for shoes. Many girls were bare-headed, and some went
through the streets in old skirts and dilapidated waists that had neither
collars nor sleeves.
At the corner of Elm and Wesson streets is an immense tailor shop,
into which the girls fairly swarmed, some going into the main and some into the rear building. Both buildings have three stories, each containing a shop under a different “boss.” I followed the crowd through both buildings, beginning in the basement and going up and up and up
the narrow, dirty, covered stairs, stopping on each floor to see the
   “ boss ” and apply for work. No success. The vest shops were full and so were the trousers shops. In the jacket shop there was room for experienced hands only, at the munificent salary of $3 a week. The garments were cut, and the sewer had the entire making.
As I passed through the crowded rooms, I could not help noticing
the machine-like way in which everything was done. Not a moment was wasted in greeting or exchange of friendly remarks. Almost at the very instant the girls took their seats, the machines were whizzing and whirling and the bright little needles flying through seams, collars,
bands, and facings. Cutters clicked their shears and little scissors, and
pressers sponged leg-seams and collars, and moved thei r heavy ‘‘ gooses ”
55
under little clouds of steaming vapor. Everywhere it was work, work, work, for barely enough to keep life in the body and virtue in the soul of these hapless children of misery.
The only real luxury about these two great shops, containing in all about seven work-rooms and five hundred workers, was the wealth of
sunlight and fresh air. On three sides of the building were windows,
through which the heavens smiled. The staircases, which, by the way, were boxed, ran along the right side of the building, and which, in case of fire, would have gone up in an instant, leaving the unfortunate inmates with absolutely no means of escape but the windows. I asked
one of the “bosses” where his fire-escape was, and he told me if I had no other business with him to “get out.”
All the women and girls I talked with lived at home. I was informed
that only those living in the neighborhood were engaged, thus doing away with the car-fare item. Some of the little girls were paid $1 a week
for tacking on tickets, sewing on buckles to backstraps, and pulling out
basting stitches. All other work was paid by the piece and salaries varying from $2 to $10, according to the skill of the laborer, $4 being a fair average for this season of the year. The worst feature of these shops was the limited room. The girls sat elbow to elbow, and the floor was piled full of work half an hour after the shop opened.
At 8 o’clock, I went to a shop at Hobbie and Chatham streets where
some evidences of decency were apparent. Instead of the rude timber
generally put in work tables, I found those on the main floor planed and grained. Off the shop was a cozy little office, and printed in three different languages were framed copies of rules and regulations. Quoting
from the set, the employes were notified that the hours of work were
from 7 to 12 and from 1 to 6; any one desiring to leave before would
require a permit to do so from the office; any one neglecting to give the firm a three-days’ notice prior to leaving, would forfeit any salary due;
every operator was obliged to oil and clean her machine in the morning
before using and in the evening after using it.
The prices paid were miserably low. A couple of girls who “ tacked”
pockets received 80 cents a hundred, and work was kept back so that
often the earnings did not exceed $2 a week. Once or twice $18 was received in two weeks. Girls who did the “ flesh ” basting along the leg seams of pants were paid $1 a hundred; 7 cents was the price paid for finishing the cheaper vests and 9 cents for the better ones. Here I met
white-haired women who sewed from morning till night to make $5 a
WAAiT W VVM
   The “ boss ” didn’t need any help, so I tried a retail tailor store on
Chicago avenue.
   “ Business is dull, and we are not doing much up-stairs. You might come in next week if you are idle, but I’ll tell you now that you can’t earn over 50 cents a day. We are working on vests; make them all by
machine. If you can sew well, I’ll give you one cent for joining the
collar.”	•
   Telling him he would do nothing of the kind, I put into Cleveland avenue and came upon the genuine slop-shop. The proprietor’s family live up-stairs in a cottage, and on the ground floor is the shop, which is entered from the back yard, via the kitchen.
   In the latter apartment was a splendid, big range, brightly polished. A couple of Swedes were pressing at a side-table. In the front room
were the machine girls, nice, healthy creatures, selected, no doubt, for their enduring quality. Nothing but the boards in the floor protected the place from the damp soil, and, while everything was scrupulously neat, the facilities for rheumatism were largely superior to those for health, comfort, and light. Wages varied. The “ boss ” was away, but his salary sheet was safe in his wife’s keeping. “ Some girls earn so much and some not so much, and that’s how it is,” she said. One of her oldest hands told me she worked “ like a slave for $4.50, and never
got more than $5. He won’t let you.”
   The next place I visited is on Cleveland avenue. The proprietor
has not mastered the English language, but knows all about the values of American labor, since he gets it as low as $1.00 a week.
   His establishment is in a rear building adjoining his residence. Ascending a flight of wooden stairs, I found myself on a landing, from
which one door led to the kitchen and another down four steps to the shop. The operatives numbered possibly thirty, in all stages of poverty.
They worked as though salvation depended upon industry, and all the
time I remained not a word was spoken. The girls made signs when a
spool of thread or a skein of twist was wanted. From every window a different house was visible, some of them being nothing more than sheds,
in all of which were young children and mothers.
   The proprietor didn’t want any more help. I sought him through
his wife, but found him so sullen, that out of pity for her I took an early dismissal. It made me very unhappy to see the poor girls slaving over their work, ruining their eyes, health, and appearance by the faulty positions in which they sat. It needed no quizzing to learn that the salaries received were poor, for there was not a decent pair of shoes or a tidy dress in the whole assembly.
   In the rear of another place on Cleveland avenue is a two-story woodshed, on the upper floor of which a German Jew and half a hundred employes work on “shop” clothing, and make money. That is, the Jew makes it. At the foot of the stairs leading from the back yard is a little kennel, from which a ferocious watch-dog bounded and scared me into a fit. The “ boss” was “out on the front sidewalk,” the foreman told me. lie offered to call him, but I protested, and seating myself on the edge of a press-stand, surveyed the room. Girls all around sewing with slavish speed and convict silence. Everything silent as the tomb but the trembling machines. Girls in calico rags and woolen rags, and one with a neat little 3-cent cotton suit, and a pink ribbon about her
neck. A child of a dozen years or so goes round the room with drinking water. The four men wear slippers and smoke clay pipes, and press without ceasing the cheap John and cottony pants and vests. All the windows are wide open, and at the very level of their sills I count the roofs of seven foul-smelling closets.
   The proprietor is middle-aged, with a complexion like pork tenderloin, and a limited knowledge of English. He manages to make me understand that I have no show, and I retire from the scene. At a place on Mohawk street I find that the kitchen is used for a factory. Only three girls are at work. Rest laid off till next week. They have pantaloons for the million about the room, stacked in piles of five feet high, for finishing which girls get six cents, or thirty cents a day.
   On Eugenie street I find another shop in which the girls are packed like cattle in a freight car. The “ boss ” doesn’t want to try me, and I'm glad of it.
   I take a walk down Larabee street. At a place on Sedgwick street
near Superior, I am “ taken.” It is just 12 o’clock. I have been tramping through “ Little Hell99 and vicinity since 7 o’clock, and feel
completely “ done.” I take a rest till 12:30, and explore the shop. The building is a story and a half, extending back to the alley, with a frontage of forty feet. In the basement is a livery stable. The “ boss ” keeps
three or more steeds here, and rents out a stall or two to a neighbor. Off the stable is a closet for the hands. On the floor, above the stables, are quarters for twenty-odd men and women in a dirty, dark, gloomy place,
with bare rafters and smoke-stained, unfinished walls. The machine- tables are set along the window line, leaving the center of the floor for a blazing furnace that supplies the power, and mountains of pants ready to
to be finished. Near the roaring fire is a sink supplied with nothing but a faucet. When it was time to go home my face and hands were coated with dust and dye, but there was neither soap nor towel with which to
TENEM ENT HOUS&amp; CIGAR-MAKtRS, (Size of room 12 by M feet,) From n Puuio^rap'i.
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
make myself decent, and I had to go unwashed. The upper floor had a slanting roof in which windows were cut to admit the necessary, although by no means sufficient, light. The heat was simply enfeebling. Before I had half started my No. 33s I was inclined to throw down the gauntlet and go home, but the patient, uncomplaining, suffering girls made me ashamed of myself, and I resolved to hold on. The perspiration rolled down their arms and faces, and stained the miserable waists they wore at the neck and shoulders.
   “ Yes, it’s awful hot up here/’ my neighbor remarked, “but this is nothing to the cold. In the winter we work with our cloaks on always till noon, and lots of times I have kept my overshoes on all day. ”
   The “ boss ” made me equivocate about my knowledge of the pantaloon trade.
   “ I can’t take any but experienced help.”	v
   “ How much ? ”
   “ Where have you worked ? ”
   I named a few of the places previously visited.
   “ Have you done tailoring ? ”
   “Plenty.”
   “ Well, then, if you’re experienced you ought to be worth considerable. Here, take that for a sample,” and he handed me a pair of No. 33 striped pantaloons with a roll of red and white waistbands, and sent me up stairs, where, between the stable smell and the enervating atmosphere, I came near collapsing.
I hadn’t the faintest idea of how to go about the waist of the garment, but I watched the ‘ ‘ boss ” down stairs, and got the foreman to let me sit by him. The dear man was bald and untidy, but he basted in
   the body lining for me, chalked the buttons on the waistband and fly, and did my ripping—which was not trifling. It was 12:30 o’clock when I began, and I worked every moment of the time with a diligence that was positively criminal, till the work was done. It was 4:45 o’clock when I handed my first pair of factory trousers to the “ boss,” who looked them over from bottoms to bottoms, and said: t€ You’ll do the
others better.”
   “ Yes, sir. How much ? ”
   “ Five cents.”
How is that for American labor ? Five cents for four hours work!
   I wastold by the women that take them home that four pair are as many as they can finish in a day. That is 20 cents, or $1.20 a week.
*
Chapter VIII.—Childhood IN Bondage.
BOYS WHO WORK IN Box FACTORIES FOR THREE CENTS AN HOUR—THE SASH AND
DOOR MAKING CONCERNS AND THEIR CHILD SLAVES—A TRIP THROUGH A MATTRESS FACTORY—WHAT BECOMES OF THE LOATHSOME RAGS PICKED UP BT SCAVENGERS—A “GOOD JEW”—A MODERN SLAVE DRIVER WHO COMPELS UNSHACKLED SLAVES TO TAKE SHORT STITCHES IN ORDER TO SAVE SPACE.
IF you want to see a snow-storm in summer, or its counterpart in appearance,go to the “separating-room” of mattress and pillow mann- factory. If yon have any cariosity to know how it feels to be feather-
lined on the inside go to the same room. One minnte will do the work
satisfactorily. The above suggestions are for people of poetic temperament—or who think they are. Bat the practical masses mast enter
the €€ picking” and “ dusting” rooms to get an intelligent idea of what a factory of that kind is.
   We will go through the mattress department first. The materials for filling are hair, fine and coarse shavings known as €€ excelsior/’ palm- leaf, corn husks, woolen and cotton rags, and sea-grass. The finest hair,
that of the mane and tail of horse, is called “drawings,” and sells at sixty cents a pound wholesale. Thence down the scale yon go by easy stages till hog-hair is reached, which costs next to nothing. As the
average purchaser merely asks for a hair mattress, and buys the cheapest, -
he generally becomes the residuary legatee of a pig. Shavings are
cleanly, and so is the palm-leaf fiber. Most of the alleged ' ‘ sea-grass ” is harvested in the Calumet swamps, so it is the buyer and not the material that is “ salted.” There are no sanitary objections to this home product, however, but there are to the woolen and cotton fillings. They
are made in part from the rags picked up in back alleys, by the Italian rag-pickers. In .the mixed assortment are fragments that have seen service as bandages for every part of the human form, and for every
kind of loathsome disease.
   They have been washed, of course, but in the main the so-called washing is a mere rinsing, which does not even remove the discolorations of
dirt, to say nothing of disinfecting them. Packed in musty bales these rags are bought and stored in the manufactory. In this form they go to the t€ picking-room,99 and are run through machines that destroy all
00
indications of their original shape. It is a dry process; were it a wet one the prodnct would resemble pulp. It is more like grinding than picking, the difference being that the fiber is not destroyed. But as muck of the stuff is shoddy there is no fiber. Only two or three men are employed feeding the machines, and the clouds of dust partially obscure them from view.
   Bad as the dust is in this room, it is as nothing compared with that in the room adjacent, where the picked stuff is dropped into a huge box, after having run the gauntlet of the two fans in the “ duster, ” where, theoretically, all dust is removed and blown into a water-tank in the engine-room. Two or three whiffs will stifle a novice. Up to a recent date this villainous stuff was blown out over the roof, and distributed through the neighborhood, free of charge. Complaints were made to the City Health Department, and the result is that the bulk of it is lifted by suction and hurled downward into a water-tank, where in two or three days it has the consistency of mush, and is scooped out and carted away to the dumping ground. Notwithstanding all recent improvements, one does not have to go far for a sample.
   From the dumping-box the ground stuff is carried up-stairs to the mattress factory in baskets, fashioned and hidden away in ticks, which are tied in bales and shipped to all parts of the United States. Health Commissioner De Wolf has for some time had in contemplation the framing of an ordinance, that should at least require a thorough disinfection of all rags used for secondary purposes. The possibilities of propagating contagious diseases, through this medium, are considered very great by experienced sanitarians. This particular factory is no worse than any other of the kind, and the proprietors show a willingness to accept all suggestions looking toward improvement.
   Feathers for beds and pillows are also bought by the bale. The common grades are dumped into a sort of bin, ten or twelve feet square, the wooden walls rising three or four feet from the floor. In this pen, sitting on the floor, were five women, literally buried in feathers up to their breasts, nothing but heads and shoulders visible. They formed a line across the bin. On their right, and in front of and covering them,
   were feathers fresh from the birds; to their left, and with no apparent line of demarcation, were feathers that had been inspected and passed favorably upon, while each held in her hand a wisp of coarse tail and wing discovered in overhauling the odoriferous and dusty mass. Each girl, by the way, wore a handkerchief over her head to protect her hair from the dust and flying fragments.
   In tobacco factories women sit in rows on low stools, assorting the weed, and only a few inches above the floor, bat they are not engulfed in the material, neither do they have to bandage their heads. Two or three of these feather bipeds were yonng in years bat worn and wan, and one was past life’s prime. From her sad eyes, fringed with feathers that gave
her a fantastic look, all hope had fled. She was looking only to the end.
And yet she and her companions were receiving from $3 to 13.50, each, a week for this light and airy labor. Women are very hard to please!
   Into a revolving cylinder, called a renovator, heated by steam, the feathers next go and are cleaned of imparities, such as animal matter. In a fan or blower they are given a cold-air blast, and the dust removed. Then comes the separator, through the slats of which all fine and perfect feathers are blown to the roof, while the heavy ones remain in the bottom of the trap, and are subsequently ran through a mill and ground to the proper consistency for a cheap grade of goods. It is in this separating room that the summer snow-storm is to be seen. The joists are festooned
with the feather-flakes, the air is filled with them, and ten seconds suffice to transform a business suit into swan’s-down. And in exactly that
time one becomes feather-lined inwardly, as he inhales at least three equivalents of down to one of air, and instantly begins to feel like a pillow-slip.
   “ Don’t you find this everlasting stuffing exceedingly disagreeable ? ”
the foreman was asked.
   “ Well, we do at first, but we get used to it after a time, and don’t mind it then.”
   Any woman connected with the Woman’s Protective Association, who would in the line of duty spend half an hour in the dusting and a like time in the separating room, should be entitled to a life pension.
   All work is done by the piece, except in the feather-room, where, as
previously stated, the girls get from $3 to $3.50 a week. In a light and airy apartment on the main floor, shut off from the noise and dust of
the factory, a dozen or 'more women make ticks and slips on machines,
their pay ranging from $1 to $1.60 a day when work is plenty. The
youngest girl employed in the establishment is but thirteen. Formerly
boys were employed, but a fire or two resulting from their carelessness in
permitting metal buttons to be run through the picking-machines satisfied the proprietors that it was best to employ older hands.
   At one of the largest box factories in Chicago, out of 320 employes fully 100 are boys.
y
y
99
i( We ask them their ages when they make application for work said one of the proprietors, “ in case we have any doubt of their being fifteen, but of course most of them know the provisions of the ordinance, and claim to be old enough. Should we refuse to take their word, in most cases they can obtain certificates from their parents. It is quite
likely we may have a number under fifteen, but of my own knowledge
I do not know that we have a single one.
Most of the little fellows feed the nailing machines. Perched up
eight feet above the floor, they sit for ten hours a day, dropping nails into the tubs that convey them to the hammering point. While the work is light, it is very exacting, any carelessness resulting in damage and consequently being quickly detected.
The manufactory occupies three-fourths of an entire block, and is
i
composed of three separate buildings. One battery of boilers runs two engines on a single shaft, the combined power being 500 horse. It is claimed that a great gain in power can be had by this plan of division, that has no direct bearing upon the subject of “white slaves/’ Indirectly, however, this fact may be at least collateral. The shavings from
all the machines are carried in pipes to a brick building 40x40 feet and
45	feet high, and having a chimney of its own, which is useless except in case the shavings should catch fire. In that event it would act as a conduit for flame and smoke, and the remainder of the plant would be unharmed. It is a protection against loss of property and loss of life. It may be interesting to the trade to say that large packing-boxes, 36x 22x24 inches, cost from 67 to 70 cents each, and housekeepers may like to know that the load of kindling-wood for which they pay $2.50 is
bought at the factory for $1 by the peddlers jwho hawk it about the
streets.
9
The boys who feed the nailing-machines have to feed themselves on
$2 a week, the net proceeds of their toil. Grown men at the machines
make from $2.50 to $2.75 a day, and machinists get $20 a week. In the mill the employes are mostly Bohemians, and in the box-factory proper they are a mixture of Irish and Germans.
At a big sash, door, and blind factory, on Twenty-second street
some four or five hundred men and boys work ten hours a day, the latter beginning at $2 a week, and slowly working up to $6. Formerly the
proportion of boys employed was much greater than now. The persistent efforts of the Oity Health Department have had a salutary effect in this, as in many other large manufacturing establishments. Skillful workmen receive $2 and $3 a day, and in some exceptional cases $3.50.
Perhaps they can afford to work for that, but the average boy under fifteen can’t afford to work ten hours a day for $1 an hour, for the labor
is too hard, and will blight his young life.
   Two weeks ago Rev. Mr. Goss preached a sermon relative to the morals and progress of the working woman. Among other things he referred to " a good Jew,” who, having the comfort of the hundred odd girls in his cloak factory at heart, “ provided every day for one cent a
substantial lunch.” I sent the reverend gentleman a note, inclosing a . stamp, for the address of the “ good Jew,” and in reply came the name. On went poverty’s respectable rags, and off I posted for shop-work and a penny spread.
   The elevator carried me to the top of the building, where every week thousands of jackets, sacques, circulars, dolmans, and cloaks are turned out to supply the country trade of the Northwest. Here, in a crowded room, with low ceilings and dingy walls, poorly ventilated and insufficiently lighted, sit, between 80 and 150 young girls, surrounded from
Monday morning until Saturday noon by the ceaseless clatter of the sewing-machines, in an atmosphere so thick that it can be cut with a knife* The machines are run by steam, and, notwithstanding the great buckram fans overhead, that revolve with a crackling noise, the ceiling is so low and the air so hot as to be positively stifling to the uninitiated. There is the smell of dye from brown, blue, and black cloaks, coupled with the still more offensive odor from the “ English plaids;” along the pressing-table are the gas-stoves, where irons are heated and where the girls sponge and press collars and seams, each operation attended with a little cloud of steam and a stuffy, scorching smell that blows about and around the whizzing fans; clouds of lint from the textures in hand cover everything, and is constantly being inhaled by the workers. Then, too, there is the smell of rancid machine oil; the overpowering exhalations from so many perspiring and unkempt persons, and an occasional whiff from the six or seven toilet
closets, all powerful factors of one mighty smell that must be smelled
to be appreciated. The “good Jew” had all the windows open, but
the place was so foul I almost fainted.
   I have a seat in the middle of the room, and a 35-cent Norfolk to make. It is so dark that I can hardly see my stitches as I bind the sleeve hole with black muslin. The forewoman can’t see either, till she takes the work9 over to the window to examine it, and returns with a gratifying “ Guess that it will do.”
   We are so crowded along the line of tables that the girls are told
to “take short threads,” and I duck my head every time the pale-faced, hollow-eyed girl at my left palls her needle out, to escape being hit*
She has only been able to make three 50-cent long cloaks in five days,
and says:
   “ You won't mind my taking long threads will you, if I don't hit you?”
I tell her to pull away, and offer to fell the bottom hem on her cloak, to which she agrees. She has on a cheap jersey waist, a calico skirt,
and the little bit of underwear that shows at her neck, where she has opened her collar, is as black almost as her jersey. Her shoes are
broken and one of the uppers is mended with black thread. SWlives
with her folks and has “ a lot of little brothers, but the *Q.’ strikes have
put them all out,” so that she hasn't bought anything for herself this
year, except a hat at the “ Fair/'
   “ Do you go to church ?” I ask.
   “ What'd I go to church for ? ”
   “ For the music and the sermon.”
“ I want a seat, though, and I’d rather ride down to the shop and
back than pay 10 cents to get in the pew.”
A poor little creature, bony and grimy, and wild eyed as the “ marchioness,” goes down on her hands and knees and turns out the dust in
the cracks of the floor with the eye of her needle.
   “ I'm huntin' for pins,” she says, “to fix on the braid.”
   “Doesn’t the ‘boss' provide you with pins ?”
   “ Indeed he doesn't; nor with nothin' else but fannin,’ and what's the good of fans in an oven?”
The child turns up the pins some of them begt, and puts them first
in her mouth to straighten them and then in the bosom of her dress,
humming to herself, “ Rock of Ages Cleft for Me.” At the expiration of the hunt a new difficulty befalls her. The needle’s eye is stuffed as she says, and in an effort to remove the filling off goes the head, optic
and all. Nobody has another to lend, and I give her mine. She says she is 13 and the daughter of a Twelfth-street teamster. Her mother is living, and she and her brother “help the family along.”
“ Yes, I went to school and learned numbers and gogerfee, but I
can't sew very well. The forelady says that's why I don't make more.
I got $2.75 one week. But I don't know how much I'll earn this week. I used to be in the “ Fair,” and they gave me $2 runnin' checks. I
didn’t like it there, because I never got home till 8 at night, and the boys was guyin’ us all the time.” •
   At noontime, the girls crowded into the wash-room, and those unable to reach the already wringing-wet towel that hung near the sink, dried on their dresses, I saw a tall young German woman wash her arms and neck, and shake off the water as well as she could with the palms of her hands before putting on her dress waist again. Another, a girl of fourteen, who wore a plaid skirt and an old velvet jacket, dried her hands on her underclothing. The lunch, the “good Jew" served, consisted of a cup of black coffee that was neither nutritious nor fragrant, and
minus cream and sugar, for which the girls paid 2 cents a cup. Then there were cuts of pie at 5 cents each, which delicacy, architecturally speaking, had two stories, substantially built, with water-proof inner lining of fruit mucilage. The top crust had bubbled up in the baking till it was as warty as tripe, and the tenacity of the under dough would have sufficed for hinging a cellar door. This is certainly not the lunch Rev. Mr. Gross referred to in his sermon, but it’s the only one the girls in the factory 1tnew anything about.
   However profitable the menu may have been to the firm, it was anguish to many of the hungry toilers unable to procure it. We girls who had no money to invest in the appetizing (?) viands sat by, begging with our eyes and following with melting mouths every morsel on its way down the throats of our neighbors. One of us, a mite of a girl, wan-faced and hectic, who had been watching the mastication of a well- fed machine-hand, waited till the leathery triangle of peach-paste had almost disappeared, and then asked the conBamer to “ give her the crust."	*
   When the well-fed party said “naw,” the child called her a “dirty beggar," and laid her little head on her arm for a nap. I went out to buy a needle, and some day when “ it rains and the wind is never weary," I shall send in a bill for the 7£ cents the “ good Jew"owes me on a cotton-back Norfolk. Only a half-hour was allowed for the noon rest* during which the girls washed and combed, trimmed their finger-nails with scissors, talked or went to sleep.
   All hands were on deck at 7:30 in the morning, in which manner, and the 5:30 hour of closing, the Saturday half-holiday was made good to the firm. Many of the girls told me they made ten cloaks a week, which averaged 50 cents apiece. Work was good, the season covering ten months of the year. A number of men at work on the long cloaks had chairs at the side of girls, and while well enough personally, I did not relish them, for they were saturated with tobacco fumes and emitted a sour, sweaty, sickening odor.
CHAPTER IX.—THE SLUMS OF A GREAT CITY.
4
AMONG THE HOTELS OP THE POOR—WORK AND WORKERS IN A "SLOP-SHOP”—
No REST FOR THE WRETCHED WOMEN AND CHILDREN THIS SIDE THE GRATE —A DAY AMONG THE BUTCHER-SHOPS AND CANNED-MEAT FACTORIES—THE LESSON TO BE LEARNED—THE REMEDY.
THE birthright of an American girl may be a glorious attribute on the deck of a trans-Atlantic steamship or the floor of a London
ball-room, but it is not worth the flop of a brass farthing in the cloak
factories of Chicago.
It was high noon by the Jesuit College clock, writes Miss Nelson, when I got to the rear of a shop on West Twelfth street. Nobody in but
an old man. His face is seamed with wrinkles; he has a big nose, the color and texture of a mushroom; his head and half his face is covered
*
with hair of chinchilla shade; his back is humped at the shoulders, and his clothes are filthy and worn. I ask for work, and am told that no
hands are needed. He has a pocket that hangs across his waist and into
which he puts rags, pieces of thread, hooks and eyes, pins, buttons, and the empty spools that lie on the floor about the Yacant machine chairs.
I	watch the silent old man as he drags his loose slippers across the floor,
and behold I have the key to wealth ! But it doesn't profit me worth a copper. So I survey the premises.
   One room, windows on three sides, and all shut. From the north windows I get a Tiew of a two-story hen-house. Filth inside and out. The outlook from the east side is a picture of poverty, squalor, and
filth. The buildings have no paint. In some are human beings, in others dumb brutes. Half-washed clothes dangle from window-sills and
clothes-lines in tatters and rags. In the yards are heaps of manure, and the alleys are foul-smelling and filthy. Along the street move flannel-
shirted, horny-handed, sooty-faced men to smoke, to rest, to quarrel,
and to dine. Passing and repassing all day long and every day—Sunday and work day—are young women and old women, youths, maidens
and children, with as many cloaks or coats or pants as they can carry.
The garbage boxes are reeking with filth. Some one has thrown ashes
or sweepings in the box and neither the swill man nor the ash man will remove the contents. The very neighborhood is polluted and the air poisoned by these reeking masses of corruption.
67
   “ Oh, it*8 nothing/’ I am told, and I see for myself and count from the window and door eleven of these garbage piles that swarm with maggots and flies. The snn beating down on the cheap pine box has made the wood shrink, and from constant kicking and shaking and probing of the miserable rag-pickers who inhabit this locality the framework has been loosened and the wood carried off for fuel, leaving on almost every block one or more naked heaps of decaying matter.
   Out of the south windows I looked into the kitchens of some dozen wretched families. The children are numerous and almost naked. They are unshod and unclean, so very unclean that it is barely possible to tell
their complexion. The mother breaks a loaf in pieces in one house, and throws it to the little dirty faces on the doorstep. In another home the children eat from a frying-pan, and next door all drink from the spout
of the teapot. Down in the yard is a pile of filth in which children play
and are followed by a lot of chickens. The stable below stairs is locked, but stronger than bolt or hinge is the smell from within, and viler still is the stench from the closets in and about the yard.
   At 12:45 o’clock the hands begin to arrive from lunch, first a young Pole, then a Russian, then a Oerman Jew.1 They wear woolen shirts, and do the machine work—do it beautifully, too, and their machines go like the wind. The patriarch in skull cap and slippers goes round the shop,looking at one and the other, watching each operator to see that no extra waste of thread is left at the end of the seams. Two more men, and then a girl. She does binding, nothing else, and gets $4 a week. At 1 o’clock six young girls are seated at a table in the northwest corner of the shop. They have been running. They are hot, full of fun, and one throws the window up. Like a volley from the enemy roll in the closet and stable smells, and I move away to escape them. The boss is three minutes late. He is a slight, meek man of thirty-five, with a shirt
the color of brown soap, dark trowsers, and a cheap coat. A light beard
covers his mouth and chin, and the expression in his eye has that soft, quiet, gentle quality sometimes seen in cattle and sheep. I tell him I
want work.
“Machine?”
   “ No.’’
   “ Tou can finish cloaks?”
   " Yes.”	.
   “ Where have you worked?”
   I	name a half dozen places.
   “ Here, finish this. I will see what you can do.”
   “How much?”
   “ Eight cents." And I pray, Father Abraham, forgive this thy son’s
oppression.
   I am given a chair at the table with the girls. Propped up on slender sticks is a stout cord, on which is a lot of spool-thread—white and black, fine, coarse, and medium. Some more of the philosophy of the
proprietor’s old father-in-law. The thread is not wasted, and the girls
are not liable to carry it off. I am given a big cotton-and-wool (principally cotton) ulster to finish. I work like a lash-driven convict on the facings and collar and cuffs till 4 o’clock, and am almost overcome by the air that floats up from the yard below. It is done, and I take it to the boss, who examines it for fully five minutes.
   “ Too fine. Custom work. Doesn’t need so good oh. such cloaks. You stay ? ’’
   “How much a week ?’’
     €t Five dollars. You Christian ? "
     €€ Yes.’’
   “ Work Sunday ? ’’
   “ Never.’’
   “ Then I don’t want you. Shop closed Saturday. Shop open Sunday. ”
   “ How much if I work five days ? ’’
   “ No, you must work six days, like all.’’
   “ Not Sunday. Pay me, please.”
   I get out. Out past the stable-door, past the children in the manure- pile, past the ragged, yellow clothes on the line, past the back doors, past the swill-boxes, and the poor, pale-faced women carrying cloaks to and from neighboring shops.	~
   Mrs. Dr. Clinton Locke is a dear, good woman who has, perhaps, done more real charity for the Chicago poor than any woman on the South Side. Afew years ago she went “slumming ’’— that’s what they call it in New York — went out Archer avenue and along Nineteenth,
Twentieth, Butterfield, Clark, John’s Place, Liberty Court, and Canal-
port avenue, into the holes and hovels under and above the sidewalks,
and in and among the stables and woodsheds, where she personally taught ignorant Irish, Polish, Swedish, German and Italian mothers how
to make broth from scraps, gruels from chaff, and tempting cookies from cheap flours. She made them keep account books for her inspection, and forced them to buy bones and joints for soup, and cheap cuts instead of steaks for their husbands’ meals. She gave them lessons in
“ drips,’’ taught them how to make a plaster, a petticoat, soft soap, and
molasses-cake, helped them smother the fire during the cool days, and
sift the ashes for cold weather; preached the economy of cleanliness, sobriety, cheerfulness, and industry, and helped many and many a mother to make herself and her family decent. She has done her share of mission-work west of State street, and what you want, poor little machine-slave, is another Mrs. Locke to rise up and teach you how to sew, how to keep your clothes and body neat, how to sit at yonr worktable, how to care for your health and save your vital energy. You must be taught that profanity, “ mashes,” the midnight picnic, the pop-corn parties in the park, the *' Dago lunches,” and the insults of the streetcar, advances of men, “ society ” men and factory men, are the very ruination of all that is lovely and holy and good in woman. You must be taught that you are not to be herded and driven like cattle, nor scourged and robbed like convicts. You must be taught that you are a woman, that you live in America, that you are “ some account,” and that there are hundreds of women who will help you to help yourself and thousands of men who will want no better pastime than to knock down the creature who insults your womanhood.
   Bat this is a digression. Leaving the field of cloth and cloaks, I applied to a confectioner, on West Jackson street. The forewoman is a thin, bloodless young woman, with wild eyes and unmistakable evidences of overwork.
   “ No, I can't give you a place. You are too big. I want little girls* All these hands have been sent us by peddlers because they are so very poor. You couldn’t live on the salaries we pay. These children get ♦3, and the old hands up-stairs $4.”
   The midget laborers were filling pans with chocolate and maple caramels. Young boys cut the sheets of soft, brown saccharine stuff into squares which a dozen little girls transferred to the tin. At deep troughs
filled with pop-com and gum-drops were other children filling small
paper bags. Up-stairs the girls worked on stick goods. Their quarters* while rude and bare and hot from the steaming syrup-pots, were light
and airy.
   At a big packing-house on Jackson street I applied for work in the canning-room. The foreman was kind. He took me out in the dark, little packing-room, in which the light and breeze were fenced off by walls of tin cans. The girls were pale and thin and very young. But, oh, how they did paint! Each stood near a wall of cans that had
just been filled with meat—pressed corned beef, tongue or ham—still
warm. At hand was a pot of japan paint with which the girls brushed
the ends and rims of each can. I told the foreman I knew I could do the
work. He tried me. I daubed on the paint, held the brush wrong, and got more color on my hands than on the can. The girls laughed at my awkwardness; so did the foreman. I was chagrined with my failure, and asked for some water to clean my hands. The man gave me a benzine
bath, and then showed me to a basin of dirty water, on the surface of
which a hundred or more dead flies were afloat. The quarters in which these girls work are little more than deadly—no sunlight, no free fresh air, no place to sit, and the blue paint smeared over their hands and arms and dripping from the breasts and belts of their dresses. Their wages are $5, but each is expected to paint at least fifteen hundred cans per day. Dirty little girls in rags and broken shoes, many of their wrists no thicker than your two fingers, were in the rear of the shop scouring cans, for which they were paid $3 a week. The hours of toil
•	are from 7 o’clock to 12 and from 1 o’clock to 5. The girls were gay
and inclined to be happy in their dungeon slavery, for, after all, they
are better paid than scores of other help in other establishments.
„	At the suggestion of the foreman I took a Halsted street car for
the stock-yards, and with so much experience presented myself at the
Fairbank Canning Company. I did not see Mr. N. K., and, what is more, didn’t want to see him. The girls, numbering a hundred or so, were at work up on the second floor in one of the numerous buildings. They painted and labeled by the piece, getting five cents a hundred. Plenty of girls handled 2,500 cans a day, giving them a salary of $7.50 week. Experienced hands earned $9, and beginners and dryers $4
per week. No provision was made for the comfort of these girls. They swept the greasy floors when necessary, packed the goods, and were jostled and pushed about by the bloody butchers and greasy packers. All worked in cast-off clothing, many literally dripping with paint. A great many of the girls were Irish, but the Swedes and Germans were numerous. I can not understand how they endure the work, which, while purely mechanical, requires them to be on their feet from
,	7 to 5:30 every day, and from all I could learn they do not stand it.
Few with whom I talked have been in the yards five years; all wanted to get married, not to have money and nice clothes and theater tickets,
but to get rested.
At P. D. Armour s packing-house the girls were paid from three cents to five cents per hundred for labeling and japanning cans, wages
varying from $6 to $9. Beginners received seventy-five cents a day for
two weeks, or until they could handle fifteen hundred cans per day,
when they received $6, and were raised to the maximum figure as their
skill increased. As at Fairbanks, they were young girls with haggard faces, emaciated figures and work-weary bodies. At noon they sat in the windows to eat their lunch, and the vessel on the sink from which they slaked their thirst was nothing more elaborate than a tin can cut down. It is certainly very good of Mr. Armour to build Sunday-
schools, educate struggling artists, buy pictures, and patronize music, but these young women are human if their senses are dulled to the
sickening smells of the slaughtering establishment, and a clean sitting-
room with neat walls and chairs in which to rest at noon, and clean
towels for the 6-o’clock toilet would not be wasted charity.
These girls are called “tough.” Perhaps they are. Perhaps their
language is not chaste nor their manners pleasing, but Mr. Armour and Mr. Fairbank know as well as need be known that their hearts are pure
and their lives blameless. Considering their origin, their nature, their surroundings and their associates, they are too good to be put on the level they are*
The facts and figures presented in this and the preceding chapters
convey a lesson which should be burned into the brain of every working man, and every friend of the working man. They show what comes to labor that can not protect itself. People talk of the advanced
humanity of the century, of the chivalry of America. But our humanity and our chivalry imprison the most of our working-women
in loathsome tenements and unwholesome garrets; starve them
down almost to brutishness, condemn them from the cradle to the grave, to squalid, miserable lives, ending in wretched deaths, and
leave but one door of escape open to them—the door of the brothel! And Sunday after Sunday, and Saturday after Saturday the sleek
and pious grinder of the faces of the poor goes to church or synagogue, and thanks his God for his virtuous prosperity, or contributes his mite for the dissemination of the Bible among the heathen, an honored and public-spirited citizen—a pillar of society and the church. These unfortunate white slaves are chattels whose misery is no more to
him than the pang in the heart of the overworked car horse who brings
him to his office in the morning* It is a lesson that should teach the
people how much they must depend upon their own strength, and how
little trust they may put in the mercy of others. The same men whose
female workers are trodden into the mud pay their male labor good wages, and accord them excellent treatment—when they must* And why ? Perhaps you have seen a cat catch and eat a mouse and enjoy it
*
thoroughly; at any rate cats do catch and eat mice; but neither you nor any one else ever saw a cat catch and eat a dog. It is not because the cat would not like to eat the dog, but for other reasons which are obvious.
   In shoe factories male fitters get $1.42, and female fitters $0.83 for the same quality and quantity of work, made side by side at the same bench. In American carpet factories male combers get $2.40, female combers $0.80 for identical work. Male hat formers get $2.50, female hat formers $1.33 for the same work. Male hat cutters are paid $1.05,
and female hat cutters $0.84 for the same work. These are figures taken
entirely at random from the pages of the United States Report on Industrial Depression, but they illustrate the differences that; prevail between the two classes of labor, when at work on identical tasks.
   If women could be thoroughly organized, it would be the first step toward their enfranchisement, and the sooner that step is taken the
better it will be for humanity and the world.
CHAPTER X.—THE HOKES OP WORKERS.
THE TENEMENTS OF NEW YORK—SQUALID MISERY AMONG THE WORKING WOMEN
—STIFLING AND FETID ROOMS IN WHICH PEOPLE WORK AND SLEEP—SUICIDAL SEWAGE SYSTEMS—OFFICIAL FACTS, FIGURES AND ILLUSTRATIONS—THE OVERCROWDED METROPOLIS—SCENES IN THE ITALIAN QUARTERS—AMERICAN PAUPERIZATION—A FRIGHTFUL INDICTMENT.
WE have shown the condition of the white slaves in Chicago. Let us turn to another great city, and see if in New York the oppressed and down-trodden and unorganized labor of the East is better housed, or fed, or paid, than the same unhappy classes in the West.
   For our facts we will not go beyond the written record of the public officers of the State. We will confine ourselves to the ghastly revelations of tenement life and tenement methods made in the Third Annual Report of the Bureau of Statistics of Labor, by Charles F. Peck, the Commissioner.
   Here is part of the showing that is made:
   “To such extremities of want," says Commissioner Peck, “are
these people pushed that they are not only compelled to work long and
excessive hours, but their children are dragged in and compelled to
labor as well. This statement is not only fully established by testimony, but is verified by my own personal knowledge, the wood-cut being a reproduction of a scene I witnessed at No. 51 Hester street, of a Jewish tailor and his five-year-old child.
   “ Mr. Theodore Guno, a journalist of Brooklyn, in his testimony says
on this point:
   “ ‘ I have seen children from four to six years of age sitting on the floor of tenement houses pulling threads out of clothing. The sanitary condition of these houses is terrible. They are badly ventilated and
badly lighted/
   “Formerly, Hood’s ‘Song of the Shirt’gave sentimental celebrity
to the wrongs of the sewing women ; but it is not the shirt now, but women’s cloaks and men’s coats or pants, that draw tears and groans from the overdone sewing women, and although the sewing-machine has multiplied goods it has hardly improved wages.
   “ During one of my visits to a tenement house of New York City, I inadvertently entered a room on the attic floor of a wretched old rook-
74
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
ery on Hester street, and f onnd myself in the midst of a number of cloak- makers. The room was, possibly, ten feet square. The ceiling was low and slanting, and its only source of light was through the begrimed panes
of glass of a small gable window opening out on to the roof. In these
cramped quarters were six women and four sewing-machines. Piled up on the floor were stacks of cloaks ready to be put together. The air was stifling to one not acclimated to a temperature well up in the
nineties, and odoriferous with sewer gases. The women were scantily
clad, their hair was unkempt, and their pale, abject countenances, as they bent over their work, formed a picture of physical suffering and
want that I certainly had never seen before, and trust that I may never
again be compelled to look upon. They were working as if driven
by some unseen power, but when I learned that they were enabled
to earn but fifty cents for sixteen (and perhaps more) hours’ labor per day, it needed no further investigation to convince me that the ‘ unseen power ’ was the necessity of bread for their own and their children’s mouths. The style and quality of the cloaks upon which these women
were at work was of the latest and best. They were lined with quilted silk or satin, and trimmed with sealskin or other expensive material, and found ready sale in the largest retail stores of the city, at from thirty-five dollars to seventy-five dollars each. Two of these women could manage, by long hours and the most diligent application to turn out one cloak per day, and the price they received from the contractor, or more properly € sweater,’ was one dollar—fifty cents apiece.
“ Inquiry elicited the fact that the strong smell of sewer gas, which
9
seemed to permeate every crevice in the broken plaster that still clung
in patches on the walls and filled the room with a sickening stench, came from a sink in the adjoining apartment. Curiosity led me to
venture within this “inside'’ room. It was without ventilation or
light, save that which came through the door connecting it with the
front room, and it was only after standing several minutes that I could distinguish the black lines of the walls and sink, from which rose in clouds the deadly gas. Upon the floor was spread a mattress, which,
in appearance, partook of the general filth to be found throughout the
whole building, from cellar up; and it was upon such a bed, and in such quarters, that three cloakmakers, tired and weary with the long
days’ work, and with a scanty, if any, supper, threw themselves down to sleep and awaited the coming day’s toil for bread.
“The top floor of the tenement No. 10 Hester street,* might,
•Also illustrated in this volume.
possibly, measure twelve by fourteen feet, with ceilings perhaps nine feet in height. Unlike the room previously referred to this one has
two windows, and to that extent is an improvement. As will be seen, there are six women and two sweaters at work on cloaks, while a third is engaged in pressing in the inside room, the darkness of which is so great that he is obliged to have his table close to the door in order to get sufficient light. As in the case of the one already referred to, the temperature in these rooms was next to suffocating, and dense with impurities. On one end of the table, at which four of these women sat, was a dinner pail partially filled with soup—that is what they called it—and a loaf of well seasoned bread. These two sumptuous courses, served with one spoon and a knife, satiate^ the thirst and hunger of four working
women."
As to another domiciliary visitation, Commissioner Peck says: “ The
building was five stories in height, very narrow, with an extremely shabby exterior. The main entrance was not over three feet in width, and the stairs which were built in the center of the building were uncomfortably steep, and hardly admitted the passage of two persons. They were lighted(?) from a very small and dirty skylight set in the roof, and
barely discernible by reason of the accumulated cobwebs and dust of generations. Several of the panes of glass had been broken, and the holes thus made filled with old rags and bits of paper. The case of one family, found living on the attic floor, was of a character to touch even
the most hard-hearted. My knock on the door was responded toby the
feeble voice of a middle-aged man, whom, upon entering, I found sitting upon an old box close to the broken-down stove which stood, or rather was propped np by bricks, at one side of the apartment. He was engaged in whittling a small stick with which to kindle a fire, while three children hovered near, chilled with cold. The furniture of the room—if I might dignify it by that name—consisted of a pine table, three legs of which were made from rough pieces of board, one .of those even being
spliced; the fragments of what had originally been two chairs, and the remains of an old sofa, with its hind legs intact and the place of the two missing ones in front supplied with chunks of wood. This room was possibly, ten feet square and lighted by a single window, which gave a view of the walls of a large factory which hemmed in the tenement on two sides. Connected with this was the almost universal ‘ inside, room,
absolutely without ventilation or light, except that gained through the door opening into it. Its cramped space was nearly taken up with a bed, consisting of a filthy old mattress stretched out on the top of two
old tranks and a wooden box. From conversation with the man I learned the fact that he was a cripple and unable to work. In addition to the three children present, he had two older ones, ten and twelve yeara of age respectively, who were out selling papers or begging—he didn’t know which—while the mother was at work at a job of scrubbing. And these seven human beings lived in these two rooms. They were dependent upon the meager earnings of a scrub-woman and the revenue derived
from the sale of papers by two small boys*
   “ This was but one of perhaps twenty family histories in the same
building. It seemed to be the headquarters for this class of people—the hiving ground of wash and scrub-women.
   “A visit to an adjoining room revealed another, and/in some respects, a sadder case of life among this class of working women than the one just cited. The general conditions of the room were equally wretched. The only evidence that the place was inhabited was furnished by the lusty snoring of a drunken man who lay across the bed in an inside room. I learned that he, was the husband and father of the wife and two children, sharing with him this cheerless home. The former had left early in the morning to commence her day’s job of scrubbing, and
the latter, through fear of ill-treatment at the hands of a besotted father, were on the streets trying to earn a few pennies by selling papers. The remains of what had been their breakfast lay upon a dirty old table
in the comer, and consisted of a bone, thoroughly picked, and a few
crumbs of bread. There was no fire in the rickety stove, and the chill
of the atmosphere added to the general sense of misery and want prevailing throughout.
   “ In this same building was the home of another scrub-woman. Her husband was employed in a sugar refinery, but the small amount of wages he was able to earn made it necessary for her to go out to work at such odd jobs as she could find to do, in order to keep the family together. On another page will be found a cut representing the rooms occupied by herself, her husband and several children. The woman was in poor health, as her appearance indicated, and the features of her one child at home—a little girl some five years of age—looked pale, pinched
and forlorn; her emaciated body was covered with an aggregation of rags, and, seated on the floor close to the stove, with the mother occupying the only chair in the room, the two formed a sad and touching picture. And all this within a stone’s throw of Broadway, the great business thoroughfare of New York City. From the window of this wretched room, in which squalor, want and suffering reveled with joined
hands, could be seen the towering walls of magnificent business blocks
and other evidences of fabulous wealth; the hum of the factory wheel,
the roar of business traffic and the throbbing of great industries could be heard ; and from Trinity’s graceful spire the chime of bells pealed forth in sacred notes : ‘ Peace on earth, good will to men/ ”
   In Mr. G. F. Wingate’s article, published in the New York Tribune,
a descriptive list of tenement-houses was given, and it was shown that the Tenth Ward alone contained 999; out of these 183 were rear dwellings; in 324 there were from four to eight families in an increasing ratio,
until in ninety-two there were twenty or more families; but twenty-nine
of the buildings contained water-closets, 833 of the inmates being dependent upon vaults. These and other details show a terrible packing
of people, absence of actual light or ventilation, and a total disregard of sanitary contrivances.
   In 1883, there were 25,633 tenement-houses, technically including flats and apartment-houses for the wealthier people, which, however, are so few that they are scarcely worth deducting—say they were represented by the odd figures 633. It is estimated that a million of people live in what are legally termed tenement-houses. As to the overcrowding, it is estimated that 18,996 tenement-houses accommodate fifty people each, and not a few of these contain three times as many. Against such a mass of misery it is impossible for individuals, however tenacious of purpose, to struggle. They generally accept the conditions and give up the fight. It is in such conditions and surroundings that young girls are brought up, in which decency and womanly reserve cannot be maintained, and then we ask why so many fall away from virtue? When virtue is only heard of, or thought of as a mystery once a week at Sunday- school—and the whole tenor of daily existence is against its observance —the mother of the family and the elder girls, moreover, must work for daily subsistence, all the more because they live in these places and are
the wards of poverty; so it is no wonder that the young resort to outdoor dissipation, and the elders sink into apathy and hopelessness. And yet, with all this, there are a very large number of worthy, honest women who do their duty as they understand it, and persevere in trying to make head against such adverse conditions.
   Here is what the Commissioner found in one of these tenements: “ Iron plates, punched with holes, were set into the flags, giving an opportunity for surface drainage, and also a free escape of the nauseous gases arising from the fermentation of accumulated filth beneath. My companion, with a lighted candle in hand, guided me down the steep
and rickety stairs into the basement of one of these houses, that I might get a closer and better insight into the real condition of affairs. The first object to meet my gaze npon landing was the dead and decaying body of a cat. How long it had lain there is perhaps of little importance ; suffice it to say, however, that the stench from its rotting body was quite, if not completely, neutralized by the greater one which flowed through the crevices in the foundation wall from the sewer. Near the stair landing a large wooden door, held in place by a huge log, gave entrance into the sewer itself. A board stretched from the door to the
opposite side gave me the opportunity to walk over, of which I availed
myself. The sewer proper consisted of a half circular, brick-paved
trough, of perhaps two feet in depth and four in diameter, and was filled with a stagnant mass of fermenting filth and refuse. On the ground on either side, and directly beneath the iron pipes through which the contents of the water-closets above were flushed, was piled a mass of filth, which, by reason of the fact that the pipes did not extend a sufficient length through the walls, was heaped on the ground, only finding its way into the sewer when, by its own weight, it toppled over. I was told that there was an entrance into this awful death-breeding sewer from the basement of each separate house, extending the entire length of the court, on either side. ”
It must be remembered that it is in buildings of this sort that shop
clothing and cigars are made. The pictures of two rooms where cigars are made will be found in this volume. One of them is on the third floor of No. 326 East Sixty-third Street, the other is at No. 398 East
Fourth Street.
“The size of the larger of the two rooms-represented is, by actual measurement, twelve by fourteen feet, and that of the other one much less. In these rooms the families occupying them work, eat and sleep, and the degree of filth, want and misery apparent in both can better be imagined than described. In this connection the testimony of a cloak-
maker is of interest as showing the number of people crowded into these rooms and the long hours of labor: c These people work till twelve or one o’clock, sleep by the machine a few hours and then commence to work again/
* 	
   “ Speaking of the Jewish workingmen, the same witness says: ‘ They begin work on Sunday morning and do not return home until Friday evening; they are mostly Jewish people and do not work on Saturday/
In reply to a question as to how many persons worked in one room he says: ‘ Sometimes we have one room, and sometimes we have a smaller room in addition, in which we employ twenty to thirty/
   “Another witness in testifying as to the manufacturers of cigars says: have visited cigarmakers, sometimes, in tenement-houses and seen how the work was done; I don’t think I would like to smoke cigars made
there—I think it would be dangerous/
“And still another thoroughly reliable witness gave the following graphic, if not altogether pleasant, picture of what he saw. He said:
*	I would be in favor of a bill prohibiting the manufacture of cigars in tene- ment-houses and will tell you why: I very often have to go upon roofs to repair them, where this same class of people are working in tenement-
♦
houses making these cigars. Generally I go through the top floors to
discover where the leaks come through, and the sights that I see in these
i
rooms are very sickening. I see women surrounded by filth, with chil dren waddling in it, and they having sores on their hands and faces and various parts of the body. They can be seen even on their lips—cankerous sores; they are all the time handling this tobacco they make into cigars, which leads me to believe that it is almost impossible for anyone
to smoke a cigar made by such labor as that, and be free from contamination.
cannot, in justice to the subject, dose this review of tenement- houses without referring briefly to what is generally known as the ‘ Italian* quarters, which are by far the worst in degree of filth and depth of degradation of any to be found in the entire city. I visited no less than half a dozen of these dilapidated Italian tenements; and while I do not wish to be understood as citing their condition as at all representative of that of other working classes in the city, I am forced to call attention
44
to it as furnishing additional evidence of the gross and criminal neglect
of the health authorities of that city.
“ Two distinguishing features of the Italian tenement-houses consist
in the excessive number of persons crowded into one room, and the excessive filth of both the room and its occupants. I have seen a family of six and even eight people living in the customary front and ‘ inside'
rooms. Where they all slept was a mystery, but that a portion of them
were obliged to sleep on the floor seemed the only explanation. The temperature of these rooms is excessive, and while the smell of sewer
gas is in itself obnoxious, it becomes simply refreshing when compared
with the stifling fumes that seem to permeate every nook and corner of these dilapidated tenements. They cook, eat and sleep in the same room—men, women and children together. Befuse of every description
makes the floors damp and slimy, and the puny half-naked children crawl
or slide about in it. Of course there can be no excuse for a such a de-
gree of filth and apparent misery. There is at least a sufficiency of water close at hand and most of the male occupants are possessed of a shovel. A free and vigorous use of these two articles would work an astonishing sanitary improvement in these buildings, and that the Board of Health does not compel it to be done is a bitter commentary upon their
usefulness. The cuts to be found on the following pages can give the reader but a faint conception of rooms in these quarters, but may serve
to awaken a public sentiment that shall yet result in the enforcement of the sanitary laws enacted for the protection of society in general.”
   As far as the lodging houses of New York are concerned their squalid misery and uncleanness are almost beyond belief. They are subject to a sort of inspection, but the reader may easily imagine What it amounts
to. Most of them are resorts for tramps, bummers and street loafers, but with these working men and women must herd if they use these houses. These houses, scattered about Chatham Street, the Bowery,
Pearl, Mott, James, Wooster and Oliver Streets, can accommodate from
fifty to three hundred people each. The prices charged range from ten cents to twenty-five cents a night, and no questions are asked of the visitors. Vermin abound, there is no such thing as privacy, and the rank,
fetid odors that hang doubly about these places guarantee typhoids and
epidemics.
   It is thus that many of the working men and the working women of the great metropolis live their wretched lives, * in poverty, hunger and
dirt. The record is an awful one. Were it not that these facts and these
figures are culled from an official publication, we would fear to print
them, because they sound like the exaggerations of a reckless and untrustworthy observer. But they are the truth. - Not Charles F. Peck
alone, the Labor Commissioner of New York, but many independent
witnesses guarantee their absolute exactitude, and we must take them as the truth, and nothing but the truth, although, unhappily, they fall far short of the whole truth.
CHAPTER XI.—COITTRACT LABOR.
Tme Evils or Over-Immigration—The Coetract System—How the Pauper
LABORERS LITE—WOODF.N SHOES AND FILTH—LIFE IN THE MINES—THE BRASS
CHECK SYSTEM—THE WHOLESALE IMPORTATION OF IMMIGRANT LABOR A
MENACE TO SOCIETY.
m
\
THE recent Congressional investigation into the evils of overimmigration has opened the eyes of the country to some of the c angers threatening our social system. Master Workman Powderly appeared before the Congressional committee, and his testimony is of such
an interesting character that it can not be omitted here. Mr. Powderly said:
“For the last twelve months, I have been traveling all over the
United States. I go to all parts of the country in the interest of my
order, and have had many chances to study the condition of the workingmen. I have given much thought to the subject of immigration into this country during the last eight years. I have found from my own observation that the social status of the workingman has deteriorated, and in every part has become bad on account of this flood of immigration and the contract system. Its tendency is to degenerate and degrade
morals. I do not think and do not say that emigration degrades, the
morals of those who come—that is, I mean to say that the morals of those who come under the contract system are so degraded that it tends to pollute the morals of others who have come here before of their own free will. These contract immigrants have but little morals when they arrive, and still less while they remain. They are induced by agents abroad to come here, and they are told that they will receive good wages. An agent of mine who was abroad last year saw large boards hung up in
all the large cities of Europe, with huge posters on them setting forth, in
every language, inducements to emigrants to come to America. American railroads would employ this method of advertising freely, inducing people to come and settle along the lines of their roads, offering cheap homes and lands. This is one system of inducing immigration.
The other is done by the agents of American manufacturers abroad. These men promise high wages and cheap passage out.
44 The result of this system I found practically illustrated in the
United States. I found in 1882 in the town of Frostburg, Md., at what
82
»
is known as the Eckert Mines, an instance of this system. I was admitted within an enclosure which was surrounded by a high board fence, to the mouth of the mine, about the height of this wall—probably a foot or two higher. This enclosed the mine. Inside was a long, low, wooden building; I should call it a shed. In that building I found five rows of
bunks. The first one was about eighteen inches from the floor. It was two feet six inches wide and six feet six inches in length. The mattress
was of straw, and covered with black and blue ticking. At least, it had been white and blue ticking originally, but it was all black when I saw
it, and fully alive to the situation. I saw one Hungarian—there were one hundred and fifty in the mine—this man walked on crutches. He had broken his leg some time before. That man had no assistant.
His leg was so offensive as to keep people away from him. He reeled into his bunk, filthy, his bandages dirty, covered with vermin and
without undressing. He made no pretense of washing. I saw men
come in to the table, dirty and filthy, and sit down to a meal of salt pork and water, the pork extremely lively, without even washing their hands.
These are the men who come to take the places of the American workingmen, who cause the reduction of wages. So that, when the workingman strikes, these men are brought to take his place. They succeed in breaking the backbone of the strike, while they work for less than an American can afford. There were, I believe, one hundred and five Hungarians who lived there in that shed.”
   “ Did you remain that night until the men went to bed?" u I did. They would come into the sheds dirty and filthy, and some of them, those who had wooden shoes, would take off these shoes,
and then, without washingjor*undressing, would cast themselves, dirty, on their filthy beds. They make these shoes themselves from the timber of the trees that they find growing in the neighborhood. They do
this rather than give the work to an American shoemaker. I have one of these shoes now at my house in Scranton. As I said before, the men
with the wooden shoes take them off. As to their clothes, they must have been made in their native land. They never take them off, and
had not, I heard, since they had been in the mine. The few that had
leather shoes did not take them off.
   “ This wholesale importation of immigrant labor has the effect of
thoroughly demoralizing the workingmen of this country. The miner who has been shoved out of the mines by these men seeks employment in the towns. The bottom rung of the ladder is shaken. Inferior men are placed in shops and factories. The discharged miner leaves
home to manipulate machinery so that he can get some kind of occupation. He will work lower than the skilled workman, and the mechanic goes down to the bottom. Until 1873 the immigration was of a differ
ent class. People then came of their free will. Where I was bom there were many immigrants, principally Irish, Welsh and English.
They all prospered and owned their own homes. But with the present
class the American workman is driven out. He can not compete with
them. He can not live on corn meal and salt pork. I met a Moravian
woman some years ago in Cleveland. She was quite intelligent and
spoke English. Many of them never learn the language. She was living in a house with eight men, did their housework, and served
the double purpose of wife and housekeeper to them. I asked the woman why she lived such a life. She said she had no alternative. If she married one of the men she would starve, but with eight she could get enough to live on, and besides there was no danger of her
raising a family.
   Mr. Powderly continued : “ I had occasion a short time ago to take a trip on the Pennsylvania road between Philadelphia and New Tork. I found a lot of Italian laborers working on the road who were identified simply by brass checks bearing numbers attached to a leather belt at
the back of their trousers. When you call them by their names they
did not know what their names were. The numbers of their checks correspond to a number on the pay-book, and if they lost the check was a case of no check, no pay. I have heard that agents of the road
frequently stole the checks and cheated these poor creatures of their
pay
‘ ‘ I would have every man who becomes an American citizen speak
the English tongue. He should be able to read and understand the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution. I should have our
American Consuls abroad examine into the character of everyone who
comes here, and make every emigrant file an application some time before he comes for the purpose of this examination. The Pardee Company in Pennsylvania is responsible for a number of these Hungarians.
Their employes do not know how to read, and can not decipher the words * dangery at the heads or hazardous places in the mines, and often work to their deaths and cause the deaths of others. Their morals are loode, and they become more so the longer they stay. They work under the lash like horses. The contract system has been the cause of demoralizing the American workingman. There are now 1,000,000 of men
employed in the United States. The man who brings over contract
laborers should be dealt severely with. He makes $5,000, and can
easily afford to pay $1,000 fine. As a rule, the class of Hungarians and
Italians who come over by contract are very undesirable. My father
was an immigrant. He came over with a shilling in his pocket, but he raised a family of twelve and did something for his country. Men who
come to stay and earn their livings are welcomed by us. But unless a man comes of his own free will we don’t want him. As far as the
Chinese are concerned, the Knights of Labor do not encourage them.
We object to them. Still we have some Chinese Knights of Labor. There are six or seven in this city. Bnt they are civilized, educated
and have become un-Chinese. The class who come, as a rule, are inferior to those who came twenty years ago. They are not as intelligent,
as industrious, nor as well able to take care of themselves. The cause of their coming is advertising in all languages and the cheapening of rates. ”
p
«
CHAPTER XII.—THE FIELD OF THE TRADES-UNION.
INSINCERE ARGUMENTS AGAINST TRADES-UNIONS—THE REAL REASON FOR THX
Hostility to Labor Organizations — Communism VS. Anarchy—The Fault on Both Sides — Labor as Merchandise—The Workingman’s Limitations— The Goad of Want—The Truck System—Employment for the Trades-Union — The Black-List—The Iron-Clad Oath.
IT has often been objected against trades-unions in America that their tendency is to destroy all individuality among workingmen; that under their methods the good and effective artisan is held back, while the bad and negligent are protected. It is claimed that the unions discourage individual industry or excellence, and tend to make . the average the rule, restraining and frowning down those who, out of a
love of work and an innate honesty, would do more than iiheir allotted task, and thus set a pace which the others would have to keep. It is
urged, in a word, that labor organization is a bar in the way of good
workmanship.
   It is argued that the trades-unions are constantly making the breach between labor and capital wider and more difficult to span; that they have substituted for the old confidence and good feeling which existed between master and man a condition of suspicion and distrust out of which have naturally arisen those bitter and brutal quarrels which are the peculiar feature of the annals of the nineteenth century.
It is reasoned further that besides the tendency to reduce all excellence to the level of the worst member of the organization, besides the
antagonism between employer and employ6 which the unions foster,
they have a still more mischievous tendency towards the rule of ignorant demagogues and the spread of communism as a political faith.
   While there are facts which seem to justify each of these objections, it is evident that the arguments are afterthoughts. They are flaws picked out by those who have gone to seek for them. These are not the real reasons for the opposition to labor organization, but justifications for a hostility whose real ground is selfishness. If we examine closely we will see that trades-unions do not tend any more towards communism than combinations of capital tend towards anarchy; that if one side has fostered
hostility to the employer, the other has raged with equal bitterness
86
against the laborer ; that organization of labor produces the same kind of an average of work as the influence of the corporation system in great factories, to which method industry is tending. In drawing up the balance-sheet we can set labor-saving machinery against the average day’s work, we can put the lock-out against the strike, the black-list
against the boycott, the great corporation herding its employes to the polls like sheep against the windy demagogue who labors only with his mouth.
   There are faults—there are crimes—there is folly on one side; but they are paired with those of the other. It is only by taking a high plane, and regarding the ouestion impartially, that we can come at the
truth.
   Dr. Richard T. Ely of the Johns Hopkins University, one of the clearest thinkers and most judicious political economists now at work in America, has examined very closely the economic value of trades- unions and cognate societies, his conclusions falling in with those of Professor Brentano’s “ Gewerbliche Arbeiterfrage, ” which is the pioneer work in this field. Both are so clear, so convincing, so full, that
CC
The Story of Labor/’ while acknowledging its debt, goes further, and recommends Ely’s “ Labor Movement in America” to all who wish to study this part of the subject further and in more detail.
   After all it is the advancement of the mass of labor which should be the ideal of every person who attacks this subject. The greatest happiness to the greatest number is a political theory which is based upon a
truth that becomes self-evident when we reverse it and put it the least
unhappiness to the least number.
   Ninety per cent of the laboring class will remain laborers all their lives. The loop-holes of escape to a condition less arduous are growing narrower and narrower every year. We are forming distinct divisions in America. The laborer’s son will be a laborer, and so will his grandson. There will always be a great and growing division of the people of America who will have to labor for their bread.
The cunning hand will never be wholly displaced by labor-saving machinery. It is for the amelioration of this class that the workingmen’s organizations have been formed. These combinations gather up all the strength of the scattered units, and their impact on society is so strong that they force us to a line of action which the single workman, uncombined with his fellows, could never command.
   Within recent times the laborer was a serf. One by one class laws have been swept from the statute books, until American labor at least is able to stand upright and struggle unshackled for existence.
   Labor is merchandise. It is something offered for sale, and its price is governed by supply and demand. It is the legitimate purpose of labor organizations to control these laws of supply and demand, and thus fix the price of labor. Unorganized labor cannot accomplish this result. If the price of wheat is too low, the farmer puts the grain away in his granaries and waits for a higher market. The single laborer cannot wait. He
must work or starve. He cannot hold back his merchandise. He cannot cause a scarcity of the commodity, which is all he has to sell, by himself. It is only when labor is in the mass that it is effective. The pool is the solution.
A
   Even the organization of labor, chiefly from its mistakes, from the ignorance of the workingmen, from their selfishness, and from their inherent lack of solidarity, has not wholly covered the field. The sale and purchase of labor differs from any other commercial transaction in that the buyer and not the seller fixes the price. There is no equality
between the parties to the contract. The laborer cannot take advantage of a better market at a distance. He is compelled to sell his work where he is. If the demand grows less he cannot come out of the market with
his goods, but he must go on competing with the greater number of laborers, thus himself adding to the factors of the decline. Production in any other line of trade is regulated by consumption, but in labor it is not.
The workingman must continue producing work till he dies. As Dr.
Ely remarks, misery and death are the factors which must bring about a decrease in the supply of labor and raise its price to the cost of production. Dr. Ely says:
“ Few now starve outright, but a large number, especially of the young, starve
gradually, as has been abundantly shown by recent investigations; but many more
deaths are occasioned in other ways. A carpenter is ill, and previous hard times have exhausted his resources. He dies; whereas a more generous supply of delicacies,
better nursing and more skillful medical attendance would have saved his life. A second mechanic is so poor that he feels that he cannot afford an umbrella. In a severe rain-storm to which he is exposed, the seeds of consumption are laid. A third
is unable to afford new shoes, and wet feet at a time of feebleness, and insufficient nourishment, cause his death. These examples mayjte multiplied ad libit um. Thus it is, that every pressure of hard times kills thousands upon thousands even in America. The most distinguished statistician of our day, Dr. £ngel, calls the causes of most deaths ' social/ The difficulty is not to prescribe a remedy, but to apply it. A physician cannot tell a man, working for a dollar a day, to take a trip to Egypt for weak lungs! No current fiction is more widely removed from the truth than the common assertion that workingmen and their families enjoy exceptionally good health. The exact
opposite is the truth, and statistics have established the fact beyond controversy that
laborers are shorter-lived by many years than those who belong to the wealthier social classes.”
   Many may think the statement that the contract between labor and capital is one in which but one party is free to contract, is not borne out by the facts. Yet even a cursory examination will show how all the power is on one side and all the feebleness on the other.
   The payment of wages at long intervals leads to the credit system and debt. This is demoralizing, and its consequences are extravagance and hopelessness. The laborer cannot escape. He is as much bound to
labor as were the serfs of the middle ages. The truck system is a development of this idea. The employer establishes a store at which the workingmen are, by means more or less high-handed and arbitrary, forced to deal. Thus a double profit is accrued—the profit on the labor which the employer buys at his own price, and the profit on t}ie necessaries of life which the employer sells at his own price. Where the truck system has been permitted to take root and flourish, it is the experience of all that the consequences are all bad to labor. Those who do not deal at the company stores exercise their freedom at their peril. When business, slackens, by a remarkable coincidence, those who have not long accounts with the employer's grocery venture are the first to go. Even under the most honest administration the evils of the system are notorious, but when, as is often the case, the method is administered dishonestly, it is simple robbery. The company store can make its own weights and its
own profits. It can sell inferior grades of goods for better ones. It has
■*
its customers bound to it by the unspoken threat of discharge. Hence in many of the states the truck system is forbidden, although corporation influence has made the law a dead letter.
   The sanitation of factories is a matter which the employ^ has almost wholly within his own hand. The safeguards for life and limb are * costly and unproductive. Hence it happens that there are in the United States fifteen thousand accidents to railway employes every year, while
the casualties among mill operatives, owing to defective safeguards around dangerous machinery, are more than twice as great.
   In every great city, at each election, we see the crowds of corporation
employes herded to the polls and voting as the employer dictates, thus furnishing the very strongest argument, politically, for labor organization. Any system would be better than that which permits one man at his own caprice to control the votes of hundreds or thousands.
   Again, the employer can put penitentiary-taught tradesmen side by side with honest labor; he can take the woman of the streets and put her with honest girls; he can, if he chooses, demoralize his laborers at his will, and there is no power in the state outside of the organization and self-
protection of labor which can conti ol the situation and forbid the disgrace
and wrong.
   Against all of these things the trades-union has been the most powerful and most successful force. Where labor has been thoroughly organized the truck system, the demoralization of labor, the voting en bloc of employes, has been weakened and destroyed. As the laws against workingmen’s combinations were one by one forced from the statute book,
the condition of the workingman bettered. In England, in 1824, the
law making trades-unions conspiracies was abolished, but up to 1869 they were regarded by the courts as conspiracies in restraint of trade, and in New York, in this present year CJ grace 1886, Justice Potter granted an injunction against the Musical Unipn to prevent them from
forbidding their members playing with non-union musicians, on the ground that such a command was in restraint of trade and was
opposed to public policy I
   The black-list is a boycott pure and simple. It is a notification sent
by one employer to others warning them of the discharge of certain men
and describing the unfortunates, under the understanding and agreement that, having lost work in one factory, or under one corporation, they shall not be permitted to get employment at any other. In that excellent work “The Labor Problem,” which is a symposium of views from many sources on the question of the hour, Fred Woodrow, one of the most humane writers on the subject of labor, says:
*4 Blacklisting has the merit of beiug very effective; its edict is final; it troubles
no jury and sends for no sheriff; it has its watch-dog by eveiy door, and woe to the man who, with its brand on his brow, seeks for work. He is proclaimed by a corporation czar. I well remember a workmate of my own being put under this ban of ostracism. He was discharged without notice, and the reason refused him. I did my best
for his reengagement; previous successes made me confident, but this case baffled me.
I suggested application to another department, under the management of a humane and kindly man. He refused. Another was tried—the same result. I completed the circle, and in every case blank but unwilling refusal—my unfortunate comrade sent adrift with the onus of some unknown disgrace staining his name, for more than six hundred miles. It came to my knowledge subsequently that he was blacklisted at
the request of one man, whose personal ill-will was gratified in his discharge. Such cases are not few, as many a hungry man and shoeless child can testify.”
%
   Next to the black-list in unfairness comes the iron-clad oath, which is often made the sine qua non of employment, and which usually compels the laborer to withdraw from any trade organization to which he may hare belonged. One of these oaths runs as follows:
TH^ HOME Or A tTENlMEKT-H5[EESE GLGAB^NA|ER, iffom ajPhotograpK.
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
I,	, hereby agree to work for	at my trade, at the regular established
prices, withdrawing from the Knights of Labor, and ignoring all outside parties, committees, and trade or labor associations, and also agree not to connect myself with
the Knights of Labor or any similar organization, or to join in any meeting or procession of any such organization while in the employ of	.
[Sign here. ]		
Sworn to and subscribed before me,	, this	day of	,	
	[L. S.]	Attest: 	,
	, Witnesses.
It is against Buch developments of class prejudice and class antagonism that trades-unions make their bitterest fight. As long as they
confine themselves in this field is it any wonder that the impartial citizen of America should bid them “ God speed ”? ,
THE WAGE SYSTEM A RELIC OF FEUDALISM—COMPROMISE THE ULTIMATE LAW OF NATURE—THE TRADES-UNION THE EMANCIPATOR OF LABOR—THE ETHICS OF THE LABOR QUESTION—A SELF-ADJUSTING APPORTIONMENT OF PROFITS TO BE SUBSTITUTED FOR THE ILLOGICAL SYSTEM NOW IN VOGUE—AN APPEAL FOR INDUSTRIAL EMANCIPATION.
THE wage system is, after all, a relic of feudalism. On the one hand it is admittedly an awkward and obsolete method of apportioning to labor its share in the results of work, a method which can only be
adjusted to the conditions of modern industry with infinite trouble and annoyance. On the other hand if it is difficult for the laborer to bring wages up with a rising market, the very clumsiness makes it no easy task for the employer to reduce them in a time of general depression. The
inconvenience of the system thus presses both ways; and were it not for our inherent conservatism, something better would long since have been found.
In spite of the demagogues of labor, capital has rights and purposes
which must be protected by society if industry is to go on at all. And in spite of the equally fatuous demagogues of capital, labor must organize and ameliorate itself from within, and all good people should give aid and comfort to the worker in his task. If we listen to one set of thinkers, we are told that the goal to which the laboring classes are tending is communism and anarchy—two utterly irreconcilable conditions. If we listen to the other school of declaimers, we will be told that capital inevitably tends to monopoly, that America is becoming a plutocracy pure and simple, that the laborer is being defrauded of his wage and that the rich man is growing richer and the poor man poorer. This statement is just as unfair and illogical as the other. If the truth is to be found anywhere it is between these two errors. There is a tendency toward communism on one side, and a tendency toward anarchy on the other,
   which must come sooner or later to a stable compromise, for compromise is the ultimate law of nature. It may be a new statement to many readers that the real tendency of the great corporations of the country is towards a limited anarchy, the legitimate consequence of the laissez fain doctrine, which Mr. Oould and his lieutenants preach so thoroughly.
92
The line along which capital and labor touch is the wages system. As we have said, it is a crude and clumsy way of dividing profits, as much
a part of the dark ages as the cross-bow or the astrolabe. Its unfitness for the work which it is called upon to do is the prime cause of the irritation between labor and capital. It seems to be generally admitted, after we have winnowed away the straw of controversy, that labor is entitled to a share in the combined product of work and capital, which is to be ascertained by the real or artificial scarcity of workers, the
real or artificial scarcity of capital and the real or artificial scarcity of the commodity prepared. Under these conditions labor’s proportion
should shift and vary in obedience to a complex set of laws. Under our
system we ignore the plexus of reasons by which wagqs ought to be computed and come to a rough working result by paying the laborer a dollar or a dollar and a half a day. In other words, we proceed as would an astronomer who desired to calculate an eclipse if he took the ratio of the circumference to the diameter as 3} instead of 3.14159. Our errors are the consequence of obvious mistakes. Yet we stupidly repeat our
blunders in the blind hope that Providence will interfere and make the total somehow right. As long as labor was an inconstant, loose aggregation of ignorant units, it did not make yery much difference whether
there was error in the calculation or not, as the error was not on the side
of those responsible for the computation. But with labor organized, vigilant and powerful, we can not go on in the easy old-fashioned way. We must reason together and strike out a new path along which labor and capital can travel hand in hand. We must change the system by which labor is recompensed, and base the new method upon justice to
both sides. Thus we will attack the very coje of the labor question,
whence, if we can dispose of the original cause of irritation, we may come to a time when permanent peace may be declared and guaranteed. Before we can do this, the laborer must admit that capital has rights to its profits; that it is the essential and indisputable corner-stone of the fabric
of our industry, without which the whole superstructure must tumble to ruins; and capital must allow that labor is an intelligent as well as a mechanical force, with rights certainly as precious as its own. Out of these admissions alone can reconciliation come.
Labor has hardly been enfranchised for more than a century. In the
statute books of many of the states, in the dark and forgotten comers of
legislation, lurk acts which are relics of a time when classes were further
apart than they are in this year of grace 1886. Like everything else worth the having in this world, the amelioration of labor came from
within. It was an evolution. When we get far enough away in time to grasp the history of the present straggle in all its details, we will all
admit that the trades-union was the emancipator of labor.. Just as we
will all now admit that slavery was a curse and a reproach, although less
than a quarter of a century ago good men were ready to give up their
lives for the peculiar institution. The present oommanding position of
the workingmen has been achieved by organization more than by any
other single factor. It is to the trades-unions that the credit is due for
the progress made in the last half century.
   To many this will seem a radical and hardly a defensible position. And yet let us look at the facts. Let us take the average workingman and the average employer, and follow them throughout their mutual
relations. The laborer has much to learn, so has the master. * Both
have to adjust themselves to a complex and delicately arranged industry. Imagine the workingman as a unit, unaided by any organization, and
what can he do for himself ? Nothing.
   He has not the means to support himself in a struggle with his
employer when the wages cease coming in. His life at best is from hand to mouth, and if the supplies are interrupted he must starve. Again, there be not concert of action among the workmen, each individual is helpless. One man cannot by himself exercise any effect at all upon the
labor market: it is only when he acts in the mass that he is effective. By
working in the mass, by pooling his issues with those of his fellows, he
finds himself after all master of the situation. In union there is strength. In the first place he finds that a large trades-union ramifying, as it does, over many cities, has a command of money sufficient to support those
who are fighting the battle of all the members. In the next place he
discovers that while the willingness or the refusal of one man to do given work at a given price has no effect upon the average employer, the joint action of a hundred or a thousand men has a very marked effect. We have seen this problem worked out so often that the result has become almost a truism. Labor is a commodity in the market just like grain
or dry goods or capital, and when from any cause the supply is checked the price must rise. Thus effects prove to the laborer the efficiency of
the trades-union. He has tried it and found it not wanting.
On the other hand the employer, accustomed by long habit to the complete control of his labor, suddenly finds it self-asserting, and, if pressed,
defiant. He does not examine far enough into the situation to grasp the principles which govern the revolt, but attempts, as his fathers have done to suppress the rebellion with a strong hand.
   Unfortunately for the employing class, the strong hand is now on the side of the opposition.
   Out of the fifty millions of Americans there are ten millions of employers and forty millions of employed, roughly speaking. Man to man the laboring class certainly outnumbers the class buying labor four to one, if not greatly more than that. And one man cannot successfully
coerce four, when the four have been educated to the duties and privileges of citizenship. When manhood-suffrage was made the rule in the United States, the old order of things was destroyed, and it is only a question of time and of organization when we must come to the new. But we are yet in the transition stage. New systems are crystalizing all
about us, and we feel the shock of force against force in the political world as in the religious.
   For more centuries than men can count, might has been, practically, light. The greater insect has preyed upon the lesser, the greater bird upon the smaller; mice have eaten cockroaches in obedience to nature,
and cats have eaten mice. The rat ate the malt, the cat ate the rat, the
dog worried the cat, and the cow with the crumpled horn tossed the dog, the cow herself being milked in her turn, as all readers of the old nursery rhyme will remember, by the maiden all forlorn. And so it goes. The cry of murder is going up day and night from every blade of grass in the fields, from every leaf in the forests. The law of life is death; the law of right is force. We may cloak it under nice words and high-sounding phrases, but the nineteenth century is no better and no worse! than its predecessors; it is more polite, not more gentle, nor more
Christian.
The ethics of the labor question are sopn decided. Every man,
whether he has money or work to sell, has the right to make the best
bargain for himself in his power; there is no immorality in labor's most
extravagant demands, just as there is no immorality in capital’s demands,
no matter how excessive. The only law governing the case is the ability to take and hold a strong position. The weaker must go to the wall. Our industry is the diagonal of a parallelogram of forces of which the master is one side and the man the other. Our knowledge of economics is not yet exact enough to permit us to draw this diagonal accurately.
The world is still settling the question which is the stronger force. It
is still governing itself by the good old plan of working out questions of justice and economics by thickness of skull and hardness of fist. Experience is a dear school, but fools will learn in no other. When labor began to organize itself, it began dimly to recognize its own strength, and
after the manner of our kind it tried to find a way ont of the trap in which it lay by simple brute force. The industrial world was divided into two bitterly hostile camps, becoming yearly, as attacks on one side
and reprisals on the other followed each other, more deeply inimical. The protagonists of labor were experimentalists; they were discoverers in
a new field of research. Their logic was the bludgeon and the torch; in their attack on the employers they attacked all society, and they were met and convinced of the erroneous major proposition of their syllogism by the bayonet and ball cartridge. It took nearly half a century to even partially clear the strike of open and nefarious brutality; these flowers of crime yet blossom out of the fallow field of human weakness and ignorance. The labor question was for years purely a question of
physical force in which one side was as bad as the other. When a trade
had organized itself into a union, taking in a majority of the workingmen in a particular line, it demanded an increase of wages, or objected to a reduction. If its demand was not obeyed a strike was ordered, and then followed a contest in which each party did its utmost to damage and cripple the other. It was a battle in which no quarter was given or received. It was a servile revolt at first in which one side at least was not given combatant rights, and it certainly accorded no more courtesy than it received.
   One of the first laws upon which political economy was founded was
that supply and demand control all the processes of industry. The laboring class was not the last to discover that combination could not control
supply, and that artificial conditions could supplant natural ones. Thus far they were strictly within the metes and boundaries of their rights; but when they tried to supplement combination by rattening, by machine- breaking, by arson, and even in some cases by murder, they arrayed against themselves all of that force in society which makes for law and order. We cannot blame them too much, for they knew not what they did. We cannot blame them more than we blame their opponents, who
added to a similar brutality education, which should have taught them
better methods.
   The wages system, as we have said, was the chief factor in the trouble. Workingmen were paid a certain fixed sum per diem, for a fluctuating result in value. They were naturally unable to locate the exact factor which was the chief cause of the industrial disturbance. It has taken some of the best thinkers years of study to fix and study the disease;
but we do know now where the trouble lies, and we should be able to apply the cure.
The consequence of work and capital is an added value to the raw product. This must be shared in some proportion between the laborer
and the owner of the wealth employed. It makes no difference what the
ratio is, it should be a constant one, and as the values of manufactured material fluctuate in obedience to a number of conditions, the result in
money should also fluctuate. Under our present system the result is
fixed and the ratio fluctuates—an abnormal and indefensible method. We will not have peace between labor and capital until the ratio is fixed and master and man share good and evil portions together. Then both will labor to one end, and an impetus will be given to industry which will
lead it to the conquest of newer and larger fields. We will have to replace
wages by an elastic, self-adjusting apportionment of the profits which will
rise and fall in automatic harmony with the results of the toil. In the
French system of “participation ” and in our own rather crude system of
“profit-sharing" we probably have the germ of the system upon which all can agree.
But we have not yet reached the goal to which all good citizens should
strive.
   Careful statistics compiled by a trustworthy statist, Mr. Charles Waring* go to show that the strikes in England during the decade ending with 1879 cost $134,060,000 to the workmen and $20,947,500 to the employers, the total loss being $155,011,500 in all. This, however, is merely
the direct and apparent damage. The loss to commerce could only be put
in figures so large that they would be met by incredulity. In America the loss would not be smaller; and throughout the civilized world it has been estimated that $75,000,000 is annually thrown away in strikes, lockouts and similar disturbances. Certainly the war is a costly one.
It has taken many years to bring the conflict to the plane of humanity upon which it now runs its course. The rancorous cruelty of fifty years ago has given place to a more reasonable and more civilized dispute. Labor has discovered that it is more powerful to injure the employer than to win benefits for itself. It can do more harm to others than it can do
good to itself; but out of many mistakes, out of the bitter school of experience, it has learned the paramount necessity of keeping its campaign within the limits of the law. Since this lesson was learned the power of
organized labor has immensely increased, because in a righteous cause, not
disfigured by violence, public sentiment, the very strongest power in America, is sure to be found on the side of justice and fair play.
Thus the theory and practice of strikes are wholly different now from
their attitude in the times of our fathers. Labor, better organized and
better equipped than it ever was before in the world's history, is coming to proceed along peaceful and lawful lines to its certain victory. A strike now is a wholly different thing in theory, and a materially different thing in practice, from what it was a generation ago. In principle it is now all for peace, law and order. The right of men peaceably to combine to do or not to do something which each individual has a right to do or to leave undone, cannot be gainsaid. If men want to quit work in a free country, they may. If they wish to persuade othors to quit, that is within their rights. Unfortunately it is at this point that the rank and file of the army of labor mutinies and rejects the wiser counsels of its leaders. We still hear of intimidation, threatening language and actual violence, and until we can get wholly rid of these, the strength of organized labor can never be truly tested.
   Many makeshifts have beeen suggested by many men who have seen the absolute necessity of making labor and capital come to some sort of a modus vivandi if progress is to continue. Each of these will be treated in its proper place in this volume. Unfortunately the schemes are all empiric—all unsatisfactory* They imply the continuance of the wage system, and while it endures strikes and lockouts will also endure. The history of strikes goes to show that the greater proportion of them is to be attributed to disputes about the rates of wages. The method is so clumsy that it can only be readjusted by a convulsion of industry. If this bone of contention could be removed we would come to lasting peace. We would reach a final settlement.
   Wages are unjust to the laborer and unjust to the employer. They are illogical. They are obsolete. They have no true relation, no scientific nexus to their origin and cause. The accompanying chart exhibits the history of a century of American labor and of American capital.
The fluctuations of wages compared with the cost of living are illustrated and the steady growth of wealth—seemingly influenced but slightly by those conditions which affect wages strikingly — is also shown. The chart will 'bear careful study. It is an indictment of our American civilization. It is in itself an appeal for industrial emancipation.
1090
1800
1810
1880
1880
1840
1860
1880
1870
1880
Chart A—A CESTDBT OF VOBK AND WAGES, ud UukiM Liter empared witk the Cost of Lifinf.
The Wares of Stifled
M
CHAPTER XIV.—THE RIVALS OF AMERICAN LABOR.
IMMIGRANT COMPETITION —- THE PRODUCTS OF AMERICAN LABOR PROTECTED, BUT
NO PROTECTION FOR AMERICAN LABOR ITSELF—THE CONNECTION BETWEEN
IMMIGRATION AND BANKRUPTCY—CONVICT COMPETITION—THE WHOLE DOMAIN OP NATIONAL INDUSTRY AFFECTED BY CRIMINAL LABOR—MECHANICAL COMPETITION—THE EFFECT OF MACHINERY ON MANUAL LABOR.
ONE of the most illogical things in our applied economics is the fact that while the government protects assiduously the products of American labor, it takes no care to protect American labor itself. The protection does not begin until the industry has reached a point where the laborer does not participate as he should in the results. It is no part of this inquiry to go into the relative merits of protection and free trade, but it is pertinent to question where the benefit of a protective system applies, when we see our ports jealously quarantined against the output of the pauper labor of Europe, while that pauper labor itself is invited in, to come and compete with American labor. We keep out the effect and welcome the cause. We will not let the symptom in, and we go out to meet the disease. Of course this is unfair. If a tariff is to be put on the result of the cheap labor of Europe, surely there should be, in justice to the American workingman, an equally effective tariff on the cheap labor itself. This would be only justice.
The subject is one not generally understood. We have heard so much talk about the development of the country, we have dangled before our
eyes such glittering rhetoric about America being the home of the oppressed, we have waved the star-spangled banner so proudly over the exiles from the effete monarchies of the old world, that we have wholly lost sight of the facts. Like the flowers that bloom in the spring, all these pansies and hollyhocks of declamation have nothing to do with the case. It has seemed so noble and so generous to us to exercise a
magnificent hospitality that we have never yet counted the cost—and the cost is tremendous.	.
We have a tremendous national domain whose development and
cultivation would be a source of wealth to all of us, and our fond delu*
sion is that the flood of people yearly pouring into our ports spreads
over the great West, and at once begins its work of making the wilder-
100
ness blossom like a garden. But it does not. In 1870 there were
5,307,887 foreign-born persons in the United States over ten years of age; of these but 619,108 were engaged in agricultural pursuits. In
1880 there were 6,491,301 foreign-born persons over ten in this country, of whom but 812,829 were engaged in agriculture. To make it a
little more plain, Ilf per cent, only, of the foreign-born population
over ten years of age was on the farms of the land in 1870, and 12£ per cent in 1880.
|	1870.
FOREIGN-BORN OYER 10
5,307,887.
ON FARMSI
619,108.
   The aboye diagrams will illustrate the point to be made even more plainly than a statement of the figures. The small number of foreigners at farm work shows the larger proportion pressing steadily upon all
the other departments of industry. Yet it is for the development of the
unsettled portion of the country that, according to our theory, we have
thrown our doors open to all who wish to come. We have put every
premium upon immigration. After a very short residence we confer
upon the newcomers citizenship, we give them, farms, we give them everything that they ought to have, and a great deal more. But look at the result!
   Nor is this the worst of it. A very singular law seems to bind together in a mysterious nexus the fluctuation of immigration and the fluctuation of the amount of liabilities of bankrupts in the United States. This has been made the subject of another chart to which the
reader will please refer in order to follow the line of argument presented.
   The statistics of immigration go back to 1820. The exact figures
of bankrupt liabilities begin with 1857. The former are given in the census reports. The latter are drawn from the excellent publications of R. G. Dun &amp; Co. But even prior to 1857 we know, in a general way, that 1837 and 1847 and 1848 were years of great business depression, which was felt deeply by the whole business community, and which
resulted in the loss of much money by bankruptcy. A glance at
the chart will show that the number of immigrants had gone np from 45,000 in 1835 to 79,000 in 1837, when the crash came. Immigration then decreased steadily so that in a year it fell to 38,000. After some fluctuations of which we cannot trace the causes closely the figures rose to 104,000 in 1842, and to 234,000 in 1847. There was great financial and economic disturbance, but the immigration
did not stop, and in 1854 had reached the hitherto unprecedented
figure of 427,000. It dropped for a while, and business became easier and better. In 1856 it was 195,000, and it rose the next year, 1857, to
247,000.	There was another industrial catastrophe; the liabilities of the bankrupts in that year were $291,000,000. In 1858 immigration
dropped to 119,000, liabilities to $95,000,000. Then came the war time, when so many new elements of disturbance occurred that the comparison would hardly be worth attention. From 1868 to 1873, immigration in* creased from 282,000 to 459,000, and bankrupts’ liabilities during the same years grew from $68,000,000 to $228,000,000. From 1879 to 1884 immigration increased from 177,000 to 518,000 and liabilities of bankrupts grew from $98,000,000 to $226,000,000. Even the lesser fluctuations are rhythmic. There is no one who will not admit that the connections in the sympathetic increase and decrease of immigration
and bankruptcy are too close and too long continued to be explained away on the ground of accidental coincidence. The only escape is the argument that the commercial depressions checked immigration. But
an examination of the facts destroys this hypothesis, unless we are
willing to admit that immigration is prophetic and can tell when bad times are coming, and how long they mean to continue. We do not question that the country’s prosperity should invite and stimulate a folk- movement this way, and that depression should check immigration, but the facts go to show that this is a reaction rather than an action.
   When some of the balder facts as to the importation of foreign labor are examined, it is very easy to see the consequences which follow from them. Take the importation of foreign labor under contract, which Congress has already attempted to restrict, as the following most imnort- ant act will show:
AN ACTT to prohibit the importation and migration of foreigners and aliens under contract or agreement to perform labor in the United States, its territories, and the District of Columbia.
   Be it enacted by the Senate and Route of Representatives of the United States of America in Congress assembled, That from and after the passage of this act it shall be unlawful for any person, company, partnership, or corporation, in any manner whatsoever, to prepay the transportation! or in any way insist or encourage the importation
STAIISHCS SUPPLEMENTARY TO CHABT.
IMMIGRATION INTO THE UNITED STATES.
BANKRUPTCY.

Tears.
Immi
grants.
Years.
Immi
grants.
1880	
8,385
1844	
78,615
1831	
9,137
1845	
114,371
lssj		
6,911
1846	
154,416
1833 	
6,354
1847	
234,968
1834	
7,913
1848	
236,537
1825	
10,199
1849	
297,034
1806	
10,837
1850	
369,980
1837	
18,875
1851	
379,466
1828	
27,383
1853	
371,603
1839	
22,520
1853	
368,645
1830	
23,322
• 1854	
427,833
1831	
23,633
1855	
200,877
1833 	
60,483
1856	
195,857
1833	
58,640
1857	
246,945
1834	
65.365
1858	
119,501
1835	
45,374
1859	
118,616
1836	
76,243
1860	
150,337
. 1837	
79,340
1861	
89,734
1838	
38,914
1863	
89,007
1839	
68,069
1863	
174,534
1840	
84,066
1864	
193,195
1841	
80,289
1865	
247,453
1842	
104,565
1866	
167,757
1843	
52,496


Tears.
Fiscal year ending June 30.—
867
868
869
870
871
873
873
874
875
876
877
878
879
880 881 883
883
884
885
• •
Immi
grants.
Total..
298,967
283,189
353,768
387,203
331,350
404.806
459,803
313,339
237,498
169,986
141,857
138,469
177.806 457,357 669,431 788,993 599,114 518,593 395.346
13,110,233
Tear.
Amount of
Liabilities.
1857	
$291,750,000
1858	
95,749,000
1859	
64,394,000
I860	
79,807,000
1861	
207,210,000
1863	
23,049,000
1863	
7,899.000
1864	
8,579,000
1865	
17,625,000
1866	
53,783,000
1867	
96,666,000
1868	
68,694,000
1869	
75,054,000
1870	
88,242,000
1871	
85,252,000
1872	
121,056,000
1873	
238,499,000
1874	
155^39,000
1875	
201,000,000
1876	
191,117,000
1877	
190,670,000
1878	
234,383,000
1879	
98,149,000
1880 	
65,752,000
1881	
81.156,000
1883	
101,548,000
1883	
172,874,000
1884	
226,343,000
POPULATION,
1830	
1830	
1840	
9,633.823
12,866,060
17,069,453
1850
1860
1870
20,191,876
31,443,331
38,558,371
1880
50,155,783
IMPORTS INTO THE UNITED STATES.

Tear.
Value.
Year.
Value.
Tear.
Value.
1880	
$74,450,000
1837	
$140,989,217
1854	
$304,562,381
USSi	
62,585,724
1838	
113,717,404
1855	
261,468,530
1822	
83,241,541
1839	
162,092,132
1856	
314,639,942
1823	
77,579,267
1840	
107,141,519
1857	
360,890,141
1834 	
80,549,007
1841	
137,946,177
1858	
283,613,150
1835	
96,340,075
1842	
100,163,087
1859	
338,768,130
1826	
84,974,477
1843	
64,753,799
I860	
362,166,254
1837	
79,484,068
1844	
108,435,035
1861	
335,650,153
1828	
88,509,824
1845	
117,354,564
1862	1
205.771,729
1839	
74,492,527
1846	
131,691,797
1863	
252,919,920
1830	
70,876,920
1847	
146,545,638
1864	
339,562,895
1831	
103,191,124
1848	
154,998,928
1865	
248,555,652
1832	
101,029,266
1849	
147,557,439
1866 ....
445,512,158
1833	
108,118,311
1850	
198,138,318
1867	
417,833,575
1834	
126,521,333
1851	
216,234,932
1868	
371,624,808
1835	
149,895,442
1852	
212,945,442
1809	
437,314,255
1886	
189,980,035
1853....
267,978,647
1
1870	j
463,377,587
Tear.
Value.
187	1		$541,493,708
187	2		640,338,766
187	3		663,617,147
1874			595,591,248
187	5		553,906,153
187	6		476,677,871
187	7		492,097,540
187	8		466,872,846
187	9		466,075,775
188	0		760,989,056
188	1		753,240,125
1883		767,111,964
188	3		751,670,305
188	4		705,133,965
103
*
Chart
I
Tke Geuectin ketveei Imigntin ul Buknptcj.
101
or migration of any alien or aliens, any foreigner or foreigners, into the United States, its territories, or the District of Columbia, under contract or agreement, parol or special, express or implied, made previous to the importation or migration of such alien or aliens, foreigner or foreigners, to perform labor or service of any kind in the U nited States, its territories, or the District of Columbia.
   Sec. 2. That all contracts or agreements, express or implied, parol or special, which
shall hereafter be made by and between any person, company, partnership or corporation, and any foreigner or foreigners, alien or aliens, to perform labor or service or
having reference to the performance of labor or service by any person in the United States, its territories, or the District of Columbia, previous to the migration or importation of the person or persons whose labor or service is contracted for into the
United States, shall be utterly void and of no effect.
   Sec. 3. That for every violation of any of the provisions of section one of this act the person, partnership, company, or corporation violating the same, by knowingly assisting, encouraging or soliciting the migration or importation of any alien or aliens, foreigner or foreigners, into the United States, its territories, or the District of Columbia, to perform labor or service of any kind under contract or agreement, express or implied, parol or special, with such alien or aliens, foreignei or foreigners, previous to becoming residents or citizens of the United States, shall forfeit and pay for every such offense the sum of one thousand dollars, which may be sued for and recovered by the United States or by any person who shall first bring his
action therefor, including any such alien or foreigner who may be a party to any such contract or agreement, as debts of like amount are now recovered in the circuit courts of the United States; the proceeds to be paid into the treasury of the United States, and separate suits may be brought for each alien or foreigner being a party to such
contract or agreement aforesaid. And it shall be the duty of the district attorney of the proper district to prosecute every such suit at the expense of the United States.
   Sec. 4. That the master of any vessel who shall knowingly bring within the United States on any such vessel, and land, or permit to be landed, from any foreign port or place, any alien laborer, mechanic, or artisan, who, previous to embarkation on such vessel, had entered into contract or agreement, parol or special, express or implied, to perform labor or service in the United States', shall be deemed guilty of a
misdemeanor, and on conviction thereof, shall be punished by a fine of not more than five hundred dollars for each and every such alien laborer, mechanic or artisan so brought as aforesaid, and may also be imprisoned for a term not exceeding six months.
   SEC. 5. That nothing in this act shall be so construed as to preyent any citizen
or subject of any foreign country temporarily residing in the United States, either in private or official capacity, from engaging, under contract or otherwise, persons not residents or citizens of the United States to act as private secretaries, servants, or domestics for such foreigner temporarily residing in the United States as aforesaid; nor shall this act be so construed as to prevent any person, or persons, partnership, or corporation from engaging, under contract or agreement, skilled workmen in foreign countries to perform labor in the United States in or upon any new industry not at present established in the United States; Provided, That skilled labor for that purpose cannot be
otherwise obtained; nor shall the provisions of this act apply to professional actors, artists, lecturers or singers, nor to persons employed strictly as personal or domestic servants: Provided, That nothing in this set shall be construed as prohibiting any individ-
ual from assisting any member of his family, or any relative, or personal friend, to
migrate from any foreign country to the United States, for the purpose of settlement
here.
SEC. 6. That all laws or parts of laws conflicting herewith be, and the same are
hereby, repealed.
Approved, February 26,1885.
As to voluntary immigration tbe remedy is not so easy, although a
remedy must be found. Mechanical competition is displacing labor in
the old country even more rapidly than it does here, and the superfluous
workingmen seem to have no choice between America and death. More than thirty per ccnt of the people now employed in mechanical industries in the United States are of foreign birth. No truer statement in a
few words of the whole question has been made than that of Mr. Carroll D. Wright, the United States Labor Commissioner : “ However much
foreign immigration has aided the development of railroad building,
public works, rivers and other enterprises, these industries have been obliged to assimilate labor faster than the demands for products have
warranted.” This, it must be admitted, is rather a remarkable statement for a government offi cer to make, and yet the facts more than bear out the deduction.
It is the development of machinery, of labor-saving devices, which has interfered with the benefits which immigration, up to a certain point,
undoubtedly has produced. Our home-made surplus population is
increasing annually in numbers, as it must under our industrial conditions. Labor-saving machinery, it is estimated, annually displaces
70,000 workers, who are thrown on the market to find some other avenue of work. To these must be added the immigrants who also annually come to our shores. There are honest, industrious, intelligent and effective men who cannot find work in the United States. The supply of labor is already greater than the demand, and yet we go on adding to the supply by every steamer which crosses the Atlantic, and subtracting from the demand by every patent filed in the patent office. A certain
amount of immigration is good ; a surfeit of it is bad.
The matter must be examined without prejudice, and solely from the
point of view on what is for the best interests of American labor. There is no “ know-nothingism ” in wise adjustment of the supply of labor to the demand. There is no injustice; it is after all the working of nature’s first law, self-preservation, which impels us to protect American labor, even at the expense of Europe. The oppressed of all nations are becoming, by the mere weight of their numbers, the oppressors of this nation. No one wants immigration stopped. Every one who
HOME OF AN ITALIAN MASON IN NEW YORK, From a P^otograpi;.
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
■will examine the facts will desire it regulated and adjusted, so that it
will no longer be an annual and constant disaster to the business of
America. We can assimilate safely a quarter of a million a year, but a
larger number is unfortunate for us in direct ratio to its volume.
CONVICT COMPETITION.
The question of what should be done with the convicts was supposed to have been solved when a system was introduced wherein manufactures
of different sorts were introduced in the prisons, and the felons were
made to learn and work at different trades. The supporters of the system
*	pointed out with truth that several very important ends were gained.
In the first place the convicts were made self-supporting. The cost of
their keeping was taken off the state. The felons were taught trades
which would enable them to make an honest living after leaving the penitentiary. The work in itself had an influence for good and toward
reform, being in itself a powerful disciplinary force.
All of this goes to show how very little social economics are understood, and how it is only after many blunders that we can come to the
That the cost of keeping the convicts was taken off the state, was true,
but the cost was paid by some one, as all should have known, and it was
paid by the honest labor with which convict work came into competition. Convicts working at an average of fifty-one cents a day produced
shoes which were put in the market side by side with those made by free labor at an average of a few cents over two dollars a day. The prison contractor had thus a margin of $1.50 per day per laborer against
outside rivals. He could still sell at a profit while they were selling at
a loss. The consequence was easy to forecast. The free laborer had to adjust himself to meet enslaved competition, and he was assisted in
his adjustment by the pressure upon his employer. Instead of taxing
the whole community for the support of the convicts in the shoe shops, the shoemakers of the country are ingeniously compelled to pay for their imprisoned co-workers. The free coopers must pay for the convict coopers, the free saddlers support the immured saddlers, and so the vicious circle is completed along the whole line of industry. As far as
the careful investigations of the Illinois Bureau of Labor Statistics have
gone, the following industries are to be found in the prisons of America,
with the number of felons employed:
SKILLED PRISON LABOR.
No. Employed.
EMPLOYED
Knm or WORK.
s
I
*3
I
fa
i
KINDS or Work*
Adobe and buildings
Agricultural tools...
Biucers—crackers.. ..
Baking and kitchen.
Baskets	
Beds	
Bedsteads—wood. 		
Blacksmiths«...
Blacksmiths, painters, furniture and wagons...
1131
174
401
04
21
14
84
286!
Blacksmiths, masons, tailors, carpenters, farm	
Bolts	
Bolts and nuts	
Bone ash	
Boneworkers
Bookkee
tlKfi'.
mere... d shoes
Bricklayers..
Brickmaking
Brooms	
42
107 10 « 4
2,7W|
14
Brooms and brushes	
Brooms and trunks....
Brush blocks and backs.
Brushes	
Brushes and shoes	
Brushes and wire work.
Building boats	
Canes	
381
8
9
IS
Caning chain	
Gone seat chain....
Garpenten	
Carpenters and blacksmiths
and
1001 2 271 1447
91
187 17
Ckrpenten*
tools
joiners’
Gurrlage bodies and shafts
OnrTOgeB »nd trimmings.
Outings	
Chair cane seating	
Chain	
• *
• • •
Chain and cradles
Chain, flag seating...
Chairs, seating	
Chain and woodwork Children's carriages
* * •
* • •
Cigars
Ciganand cigar boxes..
Clothing	
Coal mining	
Coats and vests	
Collare	
Coopere	
Cots	
CulIS	
Cutting and dressing stone..
Doors
Dressing granite
Dressing granite and marble
Dressmaking Dressing marble .... Farming implements Fnrm implements and wagons
Foundry and machinery	
Foundry worken	
Furniture	
Hame and saddlery hard-
100
7*7
5
100
8
22
36
47
9
54
*7
19
401
113
174
40
24
2
14
84
Harness and collars. Harness and saddles Harness	
Hats	
Heel making	
Hollo wware	
Hollowware and castings Hose	
• *
40
808 60 107 10
4
2,799
14
634
831 30
9
15 871
   33911 Pain ten 20011 Pantaloons 2 Paper boxes 271 Planing mill 1,166 91 187
Hosiery			
Hosiery and knitting.	
Hosiery and woolen jrood...
Jute	
Knitting	
Knitting, sewing, etc.
Knitting socks	
Knitting and tailoring Laundry	
Leather	
75
• •
181
82
Machinists.
Matmaking
Mattresses.
• *
Milling	
Molding	
Nebraska Mfg. Company.. Overalls	
31
3
• *
38
Printing Saddlery hardware
Saddle trees	
20
17 Saddle trees and stirrups...
110
106
00
10
um
182
35
Sewing	
Sewing and knitting
Sewimr machines....
231
25
284
sewing Shelf hi
ardware
24
35
813
55
838
1,071 40 100
787
5
Shirts	
Shirts and laundry 	
Shoemaking	
Shoemakingand tailoring..
8hoes	
Socks	
Steampipe fltten	
Stockings	
Stoves	
129
13
31
10
9 • « t
Stoves and hollowware.
Stoves and stove castings..
Tailoring	
Tinware	
Tinware, toys, garden, etc..
Tobacco	
Upholstering
Wagons		
Weaving	
Weaving carpet	
Wheels and spokes ...
Whips and brooms ...
Window shade rollere
Wire and wire fence.. Wirework	
Wood worken	
Woolen boots	
Woolen goods	
Total	
40
• *
127
103
314
48
103
205
60
75
30
184
310
4
181
61
207
17
100
35
7
2
55
121
3
65
30
38
11
545
173
35
231
60
284
60
300
463
100
967
3,094
75
2
477
1,045
114
80
491
66
130
94
2
20JB6 1M 30*808
*
UNSKILLED PRISON LABOR.
KOIM or Won.
• *
Breaking1 stone	
Building and working on
railroad	
Building railroads and
levees			
Building railroads, mining,
do	
Burning lime	
Chopping wood 	
Constructing prisons and
roads	
Constructing public sewer..
Constructing public streets
Constructing public works Constructing roads and
work on plantation	
Cutting timber and sawing lumber.	
Engine bouse	
Farm, construction, garden and prison duties	
Farm and garden	
Farm, garden and
live
stock	
Farming	
Gardening	
General work	
Grading public park....
No. EMPLOYED.
Males.
Females.
Total.
62
78
140
515
U
526
820
44
864
1,104
88
1,142
46

46
225

225
420

420
65

65
80

80
1,166

1,166
197

197
55

55
11

11
1,530
65
1,505
276

276
56

56
1,891
90
1,921
51

51
154
3
157
55

55
No. Employed.
KINDS or WORK.
Green-house	
Helpers	
Improvements and repairs.. Mining coal and burning
coke	
Mining coal and constructing	
Milling iron ore
Phosphate works	
Picking cotton waste
Plantation	
Quarrying
gra
line
nite
Quarrying lime stone and burning lime
8uarrying stone	
uarrying stone, breaking
and grading	
Quarrying stone and crushing 	
Quarrying stone and cut*
ting	
Rag cutting	
Sawing lumber.	
Sewing rags	
Prison duties	
Total
3
*3
£
10
24
7
400
291
190
76
8
1,148|
200
   231 1,17
147
210l
961
1391 21 1
$
as
B
r*
15
4
46
4
6,854 1,906
20,012 2,334
oi
§
10
24
7
415
291
180
76
8
1,148
200
23
1,174
147
210
961
185
21
18
8,850
22,346
SUMMARY.





•
Male.
Female.
Total.
Skilled	




1
28,826
20,012
1,567
2,334
90,393
22,346
Unskilled		







Total	




48,838 1
3,901
52,739
   If to these figures be added the 4,592 prisoners who are for various reasons idle, the prison population of the United States, which amounts to 57,331, will be accounted for. In order that the statistics in the case
may be made complete, the distribution of convicts in the different states is also appended:
I
UNITED STATES
Alabama	
Arkansas	
California	
Colorado	
Connecticut .. Delaware ... .
Florida	
Georgia	
Illinois	
Indiana	
Iowa	
Kansas	
Kentucky	
Louisiana... . Maine	
Maryland .. ..
Massachusetts
Michigan.
Minnesota
Mississippi
Missouri ..
Nebraska, Nevada ...
New Hampshire.
New Jersey	
New York	
North Carolina
Ohio	
Oregon	
Pennsylvania,..
Rhode Island..
South Carolina
Tennessee	
Texas	
Vermont.
Virginia	
West Virginia
Wisconsin	
The Territories
• 9
t
c
o
J5
3
a
&amp;
   £ 57,331
ADD
wv
667
1,621
455
990
89
m
1,650
3,300
1.737
1,011
1,376
1,384
864
183
1,214 3,819 2,628 549 812 2,000 376 132
224
Mrl
1,579
9,032
1,085
3y224
291
5*533
744
945
1,339
2£39
170
1,024
2751 1,052
420
!
PRISONERS AT
WORK.

6
•
©
i
i
&amp;
3
©
o


H 1
48£38
3,901
52,739
867

899
582
15
507
1,547
14
1,561
431
3
434
643
207
850
197

197
1,620
39
1,650
2,730
89
2,819
1,714

1,714
092
13
905
1,342
16
1,358
1,300
84
1,384
820
44
864
174
3
177
491
31
522
2,749
649
3,398
2,377
250
2,627
515
10
525
780
32
812
1,604
133
1,737
363
13
376
126
2
128
203
16
220
1,325
60
1,385
7,474
670
8,144
1,020
65
1.085
2,665
4301
3,095
282
1
283
4,009
649
4,748
661
79
740
901
44
945
14393
46
1,339

33
2392
150
20
170
966
68
1,024
269
6
275
989
33
1,022
327
2
329
Idle.
4,502
00
21
80
89
502
23
106
18
6
602
421
1
24
263
4
4
194
ass
ooo
129
8
785
4
147
30
93
METHODS or EMPLOYMENT.
I
a
o
o
u
•o
fl
U
200
1,873
1,172
318
2451
439
649
900|
330
869
99
4,350
I
1 i. fl •S
Q &amp; g
O-tJ
P
P. 8 a
o
14,999 9,291
863
597
197
1,650
2,980
* * •
769
60
1,142
864
407
287
3481
110
741
QtflQ
OwO
278
1,085
625
1,199' .•••«.
170
402
163
122
109
70
806
215
340
60
526
1,339
45
10
340
436
350
932
169
168
876
1,195
130
543
56
105
93
511
2,255
992
50
2,698
465
398
2,128
84
456
207
SJ
•O fl
II
&amp; A
16,6791 8,850
36
385
147
242
496
106
237
181
73
9
83
975
522
65
71
325
42
23
28
249
1,539
441
63
1,603
143
21
155
16
215
60
226
62
From these figures we come to the very important facts depending
upon them. Taking Illinois as a basis of calculation, we can very soon see how prison competition operates. There are 120,558 males of 16 and over engaged in the industries of Illinois. There are eight specific industries
employed in the Illinois penitentiaries,* while there are in round numbers a hundred specific industries followed by the hundred and thirty thousand free laborers* Making a general average then, which, however, would be
misleading, there are 2,819 convicts competing against 1,205 free laborers,
While the proportion would not really arrange itself this way, it must be
borne in mind that convict competition is a serious and often a fatal
• At the election in November, 1886, convict labor was abolished in minds.
#
thing to free industry. The saddlery business of St. Louis is in the
hands of the convict contractors. The census report of 1880 shows 2,297 coopers in Illinois, of whom 686 are employed in Chicago. Of the convicts at Joliet 204 are employed in making cooperage for the Chicago market exclusively, by a firm of Chicago contractors. Even yet the figures are delusive, for the penitentiary work competes directly with that
part of the Chicago coopers who are engaged in making pork barrels.
The same firm of contractors owns the labor of one of the Indiana penitentiaries, and as a consequence no free labor at all is employed in making
pork barrels for the Chicago market. The honest workingman has been
driven out of the field utterly. The manufacture of boots and shoes employs 883 convicts in Illinois, while the free labor engaged in the same
and cognate branches of industry in the state amounts to 3,443. The convicts are therefore one fourth of the free labor in this department of work. The number 3,443 represents the whole shoemaking labor in all its branches. There were 2,060 persons in the factories and it is directly against these that the 883 felons are fighting. Thus the competition is 43 per cent instead of 25. In the states immediately surrounding Illinois, viz.: Indiana, Ohio, Michigan, Wisconsin, Iowa, Missouri, there are, as
a reference to the table will show, 1,431 convicts employed in shoe- making. Under such a condition of things is it any wonder that the shoe-making business in Illinois is languishing. Free labor must come to convict labor rates. It is an actual fact, which will be found true in
all save isolated instances, that wages are lower than they were thirty,
twenty or ten years ago in the trade, and that the number of idle men is larger. And we can see how this must be true. The average price
paid for prison labor in Illinois is 52£ cents a day. Against such figures
how can the honest man compete ?
   And these are after all only isolated instances. The whole domain
of industry is affected by this criminal labor. It does not need that the
percentages of felons to honest men should be larger. If there is enough
prison output to make any appreciable effect on the market the honest
product must come to the price set by the dishonest product. The
markets are sensitive and sympathetic and they govern wages. The end of it all must be that free labor will approximate nearer and nearer in
pay and treatment to prison labor if we keep on in the vicious road in
which we are now traveling.
   And there are other points to be considered. It is simply rot to talk about either the disciplinary value of the work done in these prisons, or the reformatory value of the contract system. The felons are
mere machines held to labor by the dark cell and the scourge.
They do not learn trades; they simply learn parts of trades out of which an honest living can not be made. The advantages claimed
for the system simply do not exist. When we examine them closely they
fade away. But even if the method was all that the fancy of the most enthusiastic prison reformer painted it, it would still be bad, dangerous and demoralizing. The state has no right to fit to the backs of one class of workers the burden which should be shared by all.	_
   In this year of grace 1886, the evils of the contract system are generally admitted by all legislators. Laws have been passed in most of the states sweeping the system away, and in others at the termination of existing contracts the method will terminate; but, somehow, the remedies proposed by the economists simply change the form and not the substance of the evil.
   It seems to be still held as a cardinal principle that the convict must be made self-supporting, and herein lies the radical defect of all the remedies suggested. It is overlooked that a convict can only be self-supporting by working at some business in which the product of his labor can be sold. He thus competes, no matter under what name, with free labor, and as a consequence free labor suffers much more than the extent to which the state is benefited.
   The public account system makes the state furnish the plant for
manufacture, and sell the goods in open market. It dispenses with the contractor, but does not help the free laborer, who is met, just as before,
by slave labor.
   The piece-price plan involves the setting up of factories by the state, and the making of raw material furnished by outsiders into finished
product at a fixed price per piece. Here again the convict competition is manifest.
   Indeed exhaustive study of the works of prison reformers shows that they base their systems invariably upon making the convict a moneymaking machine. The prisons are to be factories of some sort, rather
than penitentiaries. It is here where the workingmen should insist that
the line be drawn. He should argue that the prison should not
be a factory, but a prison. He should agitate until the penitentiary is a
penitentiary, and not a device for fixing the cost of crime upon a part of
the community instead of upon the whole, as it would be in a rightly
ordered society.
   It is not our business, it is not the business of labor, to find a remedy
which shall meet the exigencies of the case. It would be better for this
country to have the convicts in utter idleness, than to force them into a pernicious activity which destroys the free workingman. When the real
remedy is found it must, at least, take wholly out of the market convict competition. Slave labor should not be employed against free. It makes no difference who is to benefit by the difference, whether the contractors, the state, or th e middlemen; it is not j ust to make labor pay that difference, and the sooner our lawgivers realize this fact the better it will be for American industry.
   And thus we see how we are even more extravagantly burning our candle at both ends than the first two departments of this chapter indicated. We are adding to the supply of labor by a constant stream of immigration, and subtracting from the demand not alone by labor-saving
machinery, but also by a system of prison industry, which adds a new
and wholly unjust competition that is insidious, dangerous and pernicious, and against which honest labor cannot hold its own.
MECHANICAL COMPETITION.
The chart in the statistical appendix to this work shows in a graphic
manner the displacement of manual labor by machinery in various
industries. In the manufacture of wall paper, for example, one man
now does the work formerly requiring a hundred men without machinery. It is an admitted fact that in the past thirty years mechanical
devices in the shoe trade have made unnecessary six men for every one now employed, while within a comparatively recent period, eight per
cent of the shoe factory operatives have been displaced. In the six years last past machinery has made it possible for one man to do the
work of two. In carriage-making, twice the present number employed have been displaced; the same in cotton manufactures; while the proportion in other branches is still greater. We could, if we wished, go through the whole catalogue of industry and show similar facts in all.
   The ultimate effect of machinery on labor has been so thoroughly
debated that it has been moved out of the arena of dispute. We know
that while immediate disturbance follows the introduction of labor-saving
machinery the product is greatly cheapened, and the workingman
participates in this benefit along with the other classes of the community. Whether labor thus gets back into one pocket all that it loses out of the other is not so clear. In the statistics collected by the United States Government occur some figures so very interesting in this connection that they are worthy reproduction and comment. In agricultural machinery, it is estimated that the displacement of labor owing to the
improved machinery brought into use in the last fifteen or twenty years amounts to fully fifty per cent. The actual facts in one factorv are given as follows:
Number of Kmployfig.
Deportment.
ter				
Foundry	
Wood-working	
Setting up	
Blacksmitn 			
Machinists	
Erecting-room	
Paint-ehop	
Teamsters	
Pattern-making	
Draft-room 	
Tool-room	
Shipping and stock	
Lumber	
Bolt and nut	
Belt		
Watch	
95
10
5
15
10
H)
6
7
9
600
70
ao
20
40
ISO
10
ao
10
5 14
6
2,145
Required
with
machinery.
That would be required
without
machinery.
Displaced
machinery.
60
540
480
70
210
140
110
165
55
60
800
210
50
50

45
90
45
45
405
360
35
10
135
7
3
1,545
	A m	
rroporuoo.
Ito 9
Ito
Ito
Ito Ito 1
Ito 2
Ito 9 Ito 2
Ito 1 Ito 2
Ito 8
Ito 10 Ito 1
Ito 1
Ito 1
4 to 1
Ito 2
Ito 2
8
Ito 3.57
   It will be seen that the place of the 2,145 men who would have been working in this factory to produce its present output is adequately filled by 600 men. From this losing of labor one would naturally look for a large decrease in the price of the product. By the census report we find that plows which had sold for $6.37 in 1866 were sold for $4.00 in 1880. Another grade was reduced from 18.50 to $5.90; still another from $11.90 to $8.00, and a fourth from $10.90 to $9.33 in the same period. Thus an economy of somewhat more than 70 per cent in the labor has produced a saving to the consumer of a little more than 30 per cent on each plow. Nor is this all. Wages in agricultural shops are very much lower now than they were in 1866 and for some years subsequently. In 1866 the percentage of wages to the cost of the whole manufacture of the plow was 37, in 1880 it was 29, and it is in 1886 even less than that. There are not alone less laborers at work in the agricultural machinery business as a consequence of the development of labor-saving devices, but those in employment are paid less per capita. The price of the product has gone down, but it has not gone down in proportion to the increased
economy in manufacture. The whole loss to labor has not been made up by an equal profit to the community.
The result of the government inquiry has shown that 35,000,000
horse-power of the steam engines and water powers equals in muscular effect the strength of 21,000,000 men. The report of the Labor Bureau is so interesting that we quote from it the following:
   “ Twenty-one million men represent a population, according to the ratio of the census of 1880, of 105,000,000. The industries are now carried on by 4,000,000 persons, in round numbers, representing a population of 20,000,000 only. There are in
the United States 28,600 locomotives. To do the work of these locomotives upon the
existing common roads of the country, and the equivalent of that which has been
done upon the railroads the past year would require, in round numbers, 54,000,000 horses and 13,500,000 men. The work is now done, so far as men are concerned, by
250.000,	representing a population of 1,250,000, while the population required for the
number of men necessary to do the work with horses would be 67,500,000. To do the work, then, now accomplished by power and power machinery in our mechanical industries and upon our railroads would require men representing a population of
172.500.000,	in addition to the present population of the country of 55,000,000 or a total population with hand processes and with horse-power of 227,500,000, which population would be obliged to subsist on present means. In an economic view the cost to the country would be enormous,. The present cost of operating the railroads
of the countiy with steam-power is, in round numbers, $502,600,000 per annum; but to carry on the same amount of work with men and horses would cost the
country fl1,308,500,000. These illustrations, of course, show the extreme straits to which a country would be brought if it undertook to perform its work in the old way. The figures are only interesting because a condition represented by them is utterly impossible. They are, to a certain extent, valuable to show the enormous benefits gained by the people at large through the application of improved motive*
power. They illustrate, too, the extreme view of the displacement of labor, which, as already remarked, has been positive, and, it may well be said, to some extent permanent. Certainly, to the men individually involved, the displacement has been severe indeed. It is not necessary to show that all the effects of the introduction of power machinery have been to raise the standard of life wherever the introduction has taken place. It is true that in those countries where machinery has been developed to the highest, the greatest number of work people are engaged, and that in those countries where machinery has been developed to little or no purpose, poverty reigns, ignorance is the prevailing condition, and civilization consequently far in the rear. These statements are simply facts which common observation teaches. They could be easily
illustrated by statistics. ”
   Every thinker will agree with Mr. Carroll D. Wright, the Labor Commissioner, in his conclusion that to machinery is due the progress of our industrial development, but that the workingman has not received his rightful share of the benefits which labor-saving machinery has conferred
upon America.
CHAPTER XV.—Thb ABJCT OF THE DISCOATBJXTBDI,
BY T. Y. POWDEBLT.
THE NUMBER OF THE UNEMPLOYED—THE DOWNWARD TENDENCY OF WAGES— THE
“LAW OF SUPPLY AND DEMAND” —THE RELATION OF WAGES TO THE COST OF PRODUCTION — CHILD LABOR—THE PLEA FOR SHORTER HOURS—THE
EFFECT OF LABOR-SAVING MACHINERY—THE EIGHT-HOUR SYSTEM—“THE SIN OF CHEAPNESS” —"Too MUCH WHEAT,” YET MILLIONS OF MEN AND WOMEN IN WANT OF BREAD.
IN January, 1884, the following paragraph appeared in one of the daily papers:
   It is estimated that at the present time one million and a half of men are out of employment in the United States; it is safe to predict that, if opportunities were offered to these men to drop into useful occupations, a large majority would not avail
themselves of them.
Since then, the nnmber of the unemployed must have increased, for
nearly every day we read such items as this:
   The worsted mill connected with the Bigelow Carpet Mills, which employs about 800 hands, shut down this morning for three weeks. This, with the five per cent cut down at the Lancaster Gingham Mills, where 2,500 hands are employed, which also
went into effect this morning, makes Clinton’s business outlook decidedly poor.
In the two years ending December 1, 1884, those employed in and
around the coal-mines worked but little over half-time, and for the length of time that they were not at work they must be counted in with the unemployed. If the figures above quoted were correct in January,
it is safe to assume that at present the number will not fall short of
2,000,000. The census of 1880 shows that the number of persons engaged
in gainful occupations was 17,392,099. Of this number 3,837,112 were
engaged in manufacturing, mechanical, and mining pursuits, while 5,183,099 gained a livelihood as laborers (agricultural and otherwise).
Thus in 1880 we had in the United States, between laborers, mechanics,
miners, and those engaged in manufacturing establishments, 9,020,211 persons.
From a personal experience, I am led to believe that the greater portion of those who are now out of employment comes from occupations
lie
that go to make np the 9,020,211. It is safe to assume that the 2,000,000
unemployed persons are discontented with their lot; and not only are
they discontented, but those who labor at the same occupations that they previously followed have every reason to be dissatisfied also. With so many men and women seeking employment, the tendency of wages must be downward. It does not follow, because men are out of employment,
that such articles as their fellow-workmen produce should decrease in
value, or that the profit on the manufactured article, accruing to the
owners of the establishments in which they work, should be any less; on the contrary, the expectation is that diminished production will increase the price of the manufactured article, or at least prevent its depreciation when thrown on the market. Notwithstanding the reduction in the expenses of the mining company, we pay the same price for coal that we paid a year ago. It matters not that the carpet mills “ suspend 300
hands, ” the price of carpeting remains unchanged. The gingham mills
and the cotton and woolen mills may reduce the wages of employes five
and ten per cent, yet the price of gingham and calico continues as be* fore. Whether the manufactured article commands the same price in
the market or not, the employer, knowing that he can secure an abundance of help, reduces the wages of his employes. Those who are out of employment are no longer producers, and they certainly are not customers to any increased extent. The wages of those employed having been reduced, their powers of consumption are limited. The merchant whose shelves are stocked with goods becomes discontented when he views the rows of men and women that stand in front of his store, peering with hungry-looking eyes through his windows at the goods so
temptingly held to view, willing and anxious to buy these goods, but
deprived of the means, through enforced idleness or inadequate compensation for services rendered. Ask the business man what the cause of the depression is, and he, parrot-like, will say, “It is all regulated by the law of supply and demand.” A moment's reflection would show him that the law of supply and demand, like all other laws, is open to
different constructions. On his shelves is a supply of goods ; outside of
his window is a demand for these goods—a demand that is at all times equal to the supply. Why is it that the demand does not reach forth and secure the supply ? The answer comes, “ Because the medium of
exchange is lacking; because labor is too cheap and plenty, and money
too dear and scarce. ” That a deep-rooted feeling of discontent pervades
the masses, none can deny; that there is a just cause for it, must be admitted. The old cry, “ These agitators are stirring up a feeling of dis-
satisfaction among workingmen, and they should be suppressed," will not avail now. Every thinking person knows that the agitator did not throw two millions of men out of employment. The man that reads such paragraphs as this will not lay the blame of it at the door of the agitator:
   Mrs. Sarah Jane Geary, an Englishwoman, residing in this city, committed suicide a few days since. Her husband is a miner, and owing to the frequent suspensions of business in the mines during the past winter, his meager earnings were insuf- ficent to support the family. The fact preyed on Mrs. Geary’s mind, and she resolved
to end her life, that her children might receive her share of the food, otherwise they would go hungry.
   That the army of the discontented is gathering fresh recruits day by day is true, and if this army should become so large that, driven to desperation, it should one day arise in its wrath and grapple with its real or fancied enemy, the responsibility for that act must fall upon the heads
of those who could have averted the blow, but who turned a deaf ear to
the supplication of suffering humanity, and gave the screw of oppression
an extra turn because they had the power. Workingmen's organizations are doing all they can to avert the blow; but if that day dawns upon us, it will be chargeable directly to men who taunt others with unequal earnings and distort the truth as was done in an interview recently had
with Mr. William H. Vanderbilt:
   One of the troubles in this country Just now is the relation of wages to the cost of production. A skilled workman in almost every branch of business gets every day money enough to buy a barrel of flour. I don't refer to ordinary laborers, but to men skilled at their trades. The man who makes the article receives as much wages
in many instances as the article is worth when it is finished. This is not exactly fair, in my opinion, and must be adjusted. Until wages bear a truer relation to production, there can be no real prosperity in the country.
I have seen no denial of the above, and take it for granted that it is a correct report. Mr. Vanderbilt starts out well enough, but he is in
error when he says that “ a skilled workman in almost every branch of
business gets money enough every day to buy a barrel of flour." I know
of no business in the United States in which a skilled mechanic, working regularly at his trade day by day, gets money enough for his day's labor
to buy a barrel of flour. That they earn the price of a barrel of flour, 1 do not deny; but that they get it, is not true. It may be that Mr. Vanderbilt refers to superintendents, foremen or contractors, for they are the only ones that receive such wages. The average wage paid to the skilled mechanic will not exceed $2.50 a day. I know of but few
branches of business in which men can command that price. The wages of skilled mechanics are on the decline, while the price of flour remains unchanged, from $5.75 to $8.50 a barrel. If Mr. Vanderbilt will demonstrate how one can purchase a six-dollar barrel of flour for two dollars
and a half, he will have solved a very difficult problem for the workingman. It is not the labor of the skilled mechanic alone that must be taken into account in computing the cost of the manufactured article;
the average price paid to labor in the establishment should be the standard, if a standard of wages is required.
An examination of the last census report shows that tne number of manufacturing establishments in the United States was 253,852, and
the amount of capital invested was $2,790,272,606 ; the average number of hands employed was 2,732,595; the value of raw material was $3,396,823,549; while the product of the manufactured articles was $5,369,579,191. Deduct the sum paid for the raw material from the product of the manufactured article, and we have $1,972,745,642. This
sum represents the difference between the price paid for the article when
in a raw state and that received for it when manufactured. It is evident
. that something more than interest on money invested was required to
give this additional value to the material. That something was the labor of the hands referred to. The total amount paid in wages to the employes of these establishments was $947,953,795. Deducting this
amount from the $1,972,745,642, we have left $1,024,791,847. This
sum goes to the manufacturer. It is estimated by some that the amount paid for raw material includes taxes, insurance, salaries and repairs; but, in the absence of reliable statistics, I am not prepared to prove that
such is the case. By adding the sum paid for raw material to the
amount of capital invested, we have $6,187,096,155, the total investment of the manufacturer. From this sum we have, pitted against every one of the 2,732,595 employes, a fraction over $2,264. While the average yearly earnings of each employe were $720, he received in wages
but a fraction over $346, or a trifle over one dollar a day for every working day in the year. Subtract the wages of the employ^ from his earnings and we have left $374. The employe receives an average of $346 a year for his labor, while his employer receives $374 o:i an investment of $2,264. Instead of basing the cost of the manufactured article on the
wages given to the highest-priced skilled mechanic, it should be based
on the average wage paid to the men in these establishments. It thus
appears that a barrel of flour costs several days* labor.
It may be said that many of the employes of the manufacturing
establishments are minors, and consequently cannot perform as great an amount of labor as a corresponding number of adults. That argument
might have had some weight years ago, but now it is fruitless. The age and strength of the workmen are no longer regarded as factors in the
field of production; it is the skill of the operator in managing a labor- saving machine that is held to be the most essential. It is true that a
child can operate a machine as successfully as a man, and that muscle is no longer a requisite in accomplishing results. It i~ 'Jso true that less time is required to perform a given amount of labor than heretofore.
This being the case the plea of shorter hours is not unreasonable. Benjamin Franklin said, one hundred years ago, that “ if the workers of the
world would labor but four hours each day, they could produce enough
in that length of time to supply the wants of mankind." While it is
true that the means of supplying the wants of man have increased as if by magic, yet man has acquired no new wants; he is merely enabled to gratify his needs more fully. If it were true in Franklin’s time that four hours of toil each day would prove sufficient to minister to the necessities of the world’s inhabitants, the argument certainly has lost none of
its force since then. At that time it took the sailing-vessel three months
to cross the ocean; the stage-coach made its thirty or forty miles a day; the electric wire was not dreamt of; and the letter that traveled but little faster than the stage-coach, was the quickest medium of communication.
   It required six days’ labor at the hands of the machinist, with hammer, chisel, and file, to perfect a certain piece of machinery at the beginning of this century. The machinist of the present day can finish a better job in six hours, with the aid of a labor-saving machine. In a yarn mill in Philadelphia the proprietor says that improved machinery
has caused a displacement of fifty per cent of the former employes within five years, and that one person, with the aid of improved machinery,
can perform the work that it took upward of one hundred carders and
spinners to do with the tools and implements in use at the beginning of this century. In Massachusetts it has been estimated that 318,768 men,
women and children do, with improved machinery, the work that it would require 1,912,468 men to perform if improved machinery were not in use. To insure safety on a passenger train, it is no longer necessary to have a brakeman at each end of the car; the automatic air-brake does the work, while one brakeman can shout “All right here !” for the
whole train. The employ^ that has had a limb cut off in a collision, must beg for bread or turn the crank of a hand-organ and gather his
pennies under the legend, “ Please assist a poor soldier who lost his leg at Gettysburg.99 He is no longer stationed, flag in hand, at the switch; the automatic lever directs the course of the train and renders the onelegged switchman unnecessary. It is said that the iron-molder recently
invented is capable of performing as much labor as three skilled workmen ; while the following dispatch to a Philadelphia paper, from Mahanoy City, shows what is being done in the mines:
   For the past three years the reduction in wages has been systematic and steady. When one of the officials of one of the great companies was interviewed on the matter, he replied that the advance in labor-saving machinery had lightened the labor of the men. A miner at one of the Reading collieries says that some months ago he expended a large sum for a patent drill, which enabled him to do five times the usual amount of work. He was employed in driving a gangway, the price paid being $10
a yard; but at the end of the week, when the officials saw the amount of work he had done, the rate was reduced to $4.50 a yard.
Take the iron-molder as an illustration. Three flesh-and-blood men, who require shelter, clothing, recreation and social intercourse, who
must eat or starve, who must pay taxes to support the state, and whose bodies can be taken to defend the state in case of invasion or rebellion;
one iron man, who does not feel, sleep, eat, or drink, who never tires and never rests. Three flesh-and-blood men, who have children depending upon them for bread; one iron man, who has no family to support;
and the three men whom he has displaced must continue to support
families or enlist in that ever-increasing army of tramps. Heat, steam, electricity, labor-saving machines pay no taxes, municipal or national; the men thrown out of employment through the in troduction of these agents are deprived of the means of contributing to the support of the state, and an extra burden is shifted to the shoulders of those that continue to work. The existence of such a state of affairs gives evidence
that the introduction of machinery, from which the many should derive an advantage, is being used for the benefit of a few, who already feel the
blow given to trade through the displacement of so many consumers.
A great many remedies are recommended for the ills that I speak of; let me deal with what seems to be the most unimportant—the reduction
of the hours of labor to eight a day. Men, women and children are
working from ten to eighteen hours a day, and 2,000,000 men have nothing to do. If four men, following a given occupation, at which they work ten hours a day, would rest from their labors two hours each
day, the two hours taken from the labor of each, if added together,
would give the tramp that stands looking on an opportunity of stepping
into a position at eight hours a day. It is said that a vast majority of
those who are idle would not work if they had work to do. That statement is untrue; but let us admit that 500,000 of the 2,000,000 idle men
would not work, we still have 1,500,000 who are anxious and willing to work. If but 6,000,000 of the 17,000,000 producers will abstain from working ten, fifteen and eighteen hours a day, and work but eight, the
1,500,000 of idle men that are willing to work can again take their places in the ranks of the world’s producers. Need it be said that 1,500,000 of new hats will be needed; that a corresponding number of
pairs of shoes, suits of clothing, and a hundred other things, will be required; that the wants of these men and their families will be supplied; that shelves will be emptied of their goods, and that the money expended will again go into circulation. It would entail hardship on some
branches of business to require men employed in them to work eight
hours a day. Miners and those working by contract could not very well adopt the eight-hour plan without lengthening their hours of labor. Before giving the matter a second thought, many of these men look upon the eight-hour agitation as of no consequence to them. If a mechanic is thrown out of employment and cannot find anything to do at his
trade, he turns toward the first place where * an opportunity for work is presented. If he is reenforced by 2,000,000 idle men, the number that apply at the mouth of the mine, or seek to secure contracts at lower figures, become quite large, and the miner and contract-man grumble because so many men are crowding in upon them in quest of work. Every new applicant for work in the mine makes it possible for the boss to let his contract to a lower bidder; therefore it is clearly to the interest of the miner to assist in reducing the hours of labor in shop, mill and factory, to the end that the idle millions may be gathered in from the streets to self-sustaining positions.
   The eight-hour system, to be of value to the masses, must be put in operation all over the country, for the manufacturers of one state cannot successfully compete with those of other states if they run their establishments but eight hours while others operate theirs ten or twelve hours a day. The movement should be national, and should have the
hearty co-operation of all men.
   A Scottish clergyman, Dr. Donald Macleod, in a sermon on “ The Sin of Cheapness,” says that “ the craving for cheapness and hunting after bargains is not only economically false, but a cause of great suffer- . ing to thousands of men, women and children.” If men worked shorter hours, they would learn that when a man begins to look for cheap bar-
HOUE OF :TAL!AM LABORERS EN NEW YORK From a Photograph.
Harvard University - Collection Development Department, Widener Library, HCL / McEnnis, John T. The white slaves of free America. Chicago: R.S. Peale &amp; Co., 1888.
gain8 he strikes a blow at trade everywhere. The employer looks for a
better bargain in labor, and reduces his force or hires cheaper men. His
employe must practice enforced economy, which is no saving; he drives
sharper bargains for'articles manufactured by others; he cannot purchase so good an article, or in such quantities, as before; and the effect is felt where these articles are made, taking the shape of a reduction either in the working force or in the wages. When the President of the United States issued his Thanksgiving proclamation in 1884, there were millions of men and women in want of bread, notwithstanding “ the abundant harvests and continued prosperity which God hath vouchsafed to this nation," and the cry, not of thanksgiving, went up from millions of
farmers of “ Too much wheat! ” Doubting as to the exact meaning of
the Creator in growing so much wheat, they invoked the aid of such institutions as the Chicago Board of Trade, in the hope of thwarting the will of God by cornering wheat. These men invoked blessings on their
Thanksgiving dinners, and thanked God for the turkey, while they hoarded the wheat away from those who asked for bread.
Give men shorter hours in which to labor, and you give them more
time to study and learn why bread is so scarce while wheat is so plenty.
Yon give them more time, in which to learn that millions of acres of
American soil are controlled by alien landlords that have no interest in
America but to draw a revenue from it. You give them time to learn that America belongs to Americans, native and naturalized, and that
the landlord who drives his tenant from the Old World must not be permitted to exact tribute from him when he settles in our country.
#
BY T. V. POWDERLY.
THE prospect ior the future of the laboring man in America is brighter today than it ever was, notwithstanding the seemingly
*	* strained relations" at present existing between employer and em-
ploy6.	...
   That we are passing through an epidemic of strikes, lockouts and
boycotts, is true, but the fact must not be lost sight of, that were it not
for the growing power of organization we should have a great many more strikes to contend with than we have had for the first three months of the present year.
   The growth of organization for the past ten years has been steady and healthy. It is only where organization is in its infancy that serious troubles such as strikes and lockouts exist. The causes from which strikes and lockouts spring are to be found in all parts of the country, but the methods of dealing with the troubles as they arise are different. In places where no organizations of labor exist, or where the seeds of organization hare just been planted, disputing parties are apt to become
involved in strikes. The reasons advanced in support of that proposition
are as follows: Until recently very few workingmen dared to express their opinion in public on the subject of labor, for the reason that they were almost certain of an immediate dismissal from the service of the man or company they worked for, if it became known that they in any
way favored the association of workingmen for mutual protection.
With, such a sentiment existing in the breasts of workingmen they could not be expected to feel very kindly toward the employer who so jealously
watched their every movement, and who, by his actions, made them feel that they were regarded rather as serfs than freemen. While the real bone and sinew of the land remained in enforced silence, except where
it could be heard through the medium of the press and rostrum, through chosen leaders, another class of men who seldom worked would insist on “representing labor/’ and, in making glowing speeches on the rights
and wrongs of man, would urge the “abolition of property,” or the
“ equal division of wealth; ” such speakers very often suggesting that a
124
good thing to do would be to “hang capitalists to lamp-posts.” The employer of labor who listened to such speeches felt that in suppressing organization among his workmen he was performing a laudable act. Yet he was by that means proving himself to be the most powerful ally the anarchist could wish for. He caused his employes to feel that he took no interest in them other than to get as nuny hours of toil out of them for as few shillings as possible. The consequence was that the employer, who was himself responsible for the smothering of the honest
expression of opinion on the part of labor, became possessed of the idea
that the raw-head-and-bloody-bones curb-stone orator was the real representative of labor, and determined to exercise more vigilance and precaution than ever in keeping his “ help ” out of the labor society. The speaker who hinted at or advocated the destruction of property or the hanging of capitalists to lamp-posts, was shrewd enough to speak very kindly, and in a knowing manner, of labor associations, giving out the impression that he held membership in one or more of them. Workingmen who were denied the right to organize, very frequently went to hear
Mr. Scientific lecture on the best means of handling dynamite. And when the speaker portrayed the wrongs of labor, the thoughtful workman
conld readily trace a resemblance between the employer painted by the
lecturer and the man he himself worked for. Workmen employed by those who frowned on labor organizations became sullen and morose; they saw in every action of the superintendent another innovation on their rights, and they finally determined to throw off the yoke of oppression, organize and assert their manhood. The actions of the superintendent, or boss, very often tended to widen the breach between employer and employ^. When the organization did come it found a very bitter feeling existing on both sides, and before studying the laws of the society they joined, or becoming conversant with its rules or regulations
regarding the settlement of disputes or grievances, the workmen determined to wipe out of existence the whole system of petty tyrannies that
had been practiced on them for years. Not being drilled in organization, and feeling that the employer would not treat with them, the only remedy suggesting itself was the strike. And, on the other hand, the employer who felt that every move of his workmen in organization would
be directed against his interests, determined to take time by the forelock
and turn them all out on the street. Thus we find the organization in
its infancy face to face with a strike or lockout.
This condition of affairs existed in a great many places throughout
the TJnited States in the beginning of the present year. Absorbed in
the task of getting large dividends, the employer seldom inquired of his superintendent how he managed the business intrusted to his keeping,
or how he treated his employes. In thousands of places throughout the United States, as many superintendents, foremen, or petty bosses are interested in stores, corner groceries or saloons. In many places the employ^ is told plainly that he must deal at the store, or get his liquor from the saloon in which his boss has an interest; in others he is given
to understand that he must deal in these stores or saloons, or forfeit his situation. Laws have been passed in some states against the keeping of company stores, but the stores are kept nevertheless, and workmen are made to feel that they must patronize them.
In many cases the owners of mills, factories or mines are not aware
of the existence of such institutions as the “pluck me"—the name applied to the company store—but they stand so far away from their employes that they cannot hear the murmur of complaint, and if a whisper of it ever does reach their ears it comes through the boss who is not only interested in the store, but in keeping its existence a secret from his employer. The keeping of such stores is another source of injustice to workmen, for their existence tends to widen the breach between employer and employ^. It may seem that I am dealing with insignificant things in this paper, but when the statement is made, that seven out of
every ten superintendents or bosses are interested in the management, and derive profits from the operation of stores which employes are forced to patronize, I make an assertion which can be proved. In a country where every man, no matter how humble, is taught from his infancy that he stands the equal of all other men, it is but natural for a citizen who is given to understand that he must patronize a certain store, or that he cannot join a certain society, to feel restive, and, where so much is promised and so little obtained, men are apt to lose faith in a lawmaking system which obliges the workman himself to become complainant and prosecutor in cases where the laws are violated to his detriment. If he prosecutes, he is discharged. If he does not prosecute for infractions of law, but simply complains, he is told to invoke the majesty of the law in his own behalf. In this way law is disregarded; it becomes a
dead letter; men lose hope in law and law-makers.
   The constant itching and irritation caused by the indifference of the employer to their welfare, and the injustices practiced on them by petty bosses, go on until the men feel that the only remedy is through the
strike. In this way men who belong to no organization are launched into strikes.
«
   Workingmen are not, as a rale, educated men. When the strike does come, while they feel that they have been wronged, yet they are lacking in the command of language necessary to state their case properly to the world, and, hence, set forth their claims in such a way as to ' arouse prejudices or create false impressions. The other side haying the advantage of education, either personally or by right of purchase, can
and does mold public opinion in a great many cases.
   I	have pointed out one or two of the little things which cause a great
deal of uneasiness and vexation to workingmen; others have pointed out
the root of the evil. The workingman of the United States will soon realize that he possesses the power which kings once held—that he has the right to manage his own affairs. The power of the king has passed away. The power of wealth is passing away. The evening shadows are closing in upon the day when immense private fortunes can be acquired. The new power dawning upon the world is that of the workingman to rule his own destinies. That power can no longer be kept from him. How will he wield it ?
   This question is of great concern not only to the workingman but to
every citizen of the republic, and the hand of every citizen who loves his country should be extended to assist the new ruler. I have no fears because of the present apparent disturbed condition of the labor world; on the contrary, the signs are very hopeful. Wendell Phillips once said,
“ Never look for an age when the people can be quiet and safe. At such times Despotism like a shrouding mist steals over the mirror of Freedom. 99
   The people are not quiet today, but they are safe. It is the power of
monopoly that is not safe. The men who pile up large fortunes must
compensate for that privilege in the payment of “a graduated income tax. The blessings which they derive from wealth must be shared by the
nation from which they extract that wealth.
   The hours of labor must be reduced throughout the nation* so that the toilers may have more time in which to learn the science of selfgovernment. Labor-saving machinery instead of making a slave of man must become his servant. How will the workingman wield his power ? Organized labor says the power will be wisely handled, but we must have the cooperation of the vast middle classes. The employer and employed must no longer stand apart. The barriers of pride, caste, greed, hatred and bitterness must be tom down. The workingman and his employer must meet face to face, they must discuss every detail in the management of the concerns they are jointly operating. No sacrifice of princi-
*
pie on the one hand or of manhood on the other need attend such a transaction. In the management of great or small concerns each grievance, each trouble or difference, whether in relation to discipline or
wages, should be talked over in a conciliatory spirit and arbitrated. Joint boards of arbitration should be formed between manufacturer and workmen all over the country. Each party should devote considerable time to the perfecting of the plans best suited to their interests or surroundings, for rules governing one case or locality might not work well in another.
   Having after careful deliberation agreed upon the rules, each party should sign the articles of agreement, binding itself to abide by them until changed by consent of both. Agreements of this kind will be the
means of settling differences as they arise, and with their inauguration strikes, lockouts and boycotts will not be entered upon so readily, and
if ever called into play, then only as the very last resort.	'
9
Tlx foregoing article appwut hy special tmmgwntnt with the ** Worth American Bartow,” and toy permission
V. POWPPLT. Hi author.
</text>
</xml>