<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title corresp="#CT014"><date when="1888-08-12">Sunday Morning, August 12, 1888</date></title><sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor><sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Rebecca Parker</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#nll">Nicole L. Lottig</persName><!--RJP: Each editor will have their own xml:id that will be linked here from the project's site index... the xsml:id will be represented by a hashtag and then the editors initals... for example my xml:id will be rjp so when I am referencing myself inside of the value of other attributes (like here in the @ref) I will put #rjp --></respStmt><respStmt><resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><persName>Gregory Bondar</persName></respStmt><!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:<respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt>--></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2015-01-03">2016-02-27</date><!--RJP: put the date for when the article was transcribed and/or encoded?-->. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor's degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head><title><name ref="#CT">Chicago Times</name> <date when="1888-08-12">Sunday Morning, August 12, 1888</date></title></head><div type="headlines"><list><item>Nell Nelson Continues to Expose the Salve-Grinding Hell-Holes of Chicago.</item><item>Graphic Account of Her Experiences in the Filthy <hi rend="double">Slop Shops</hi> of the West Side <!-- 2016-02-27: nll: Should 'West Side' be surrounded in a placeName tag? 2016-04-08: rjp: we never markup anything more than stylistic 'things' inside of our headlines because it only causes duplicate data (since everything in a headline is repeated in someway in the body of the article -->.</item><item>No Rest for the Weary and Wretched Women and Children This Side of the Grave.</item><item>A Day Among the Butcher-Shops and Canned-Meat Factories of the Stock Yards.</item><item>How Messrs, Armour and Fairbanks <!-- 2016-02-27: nll: Are these persNames?? 2016-04-08: rjp:see above comment-->Might Brighten the Lives of Their Employes.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p>The birthright of an American girl may be a glorious attribute on the deck of a trans-atlantic steamship or the floor of a <placeName type="city">London</placeName> ball-room, but it is not worth the flop of a brass farthing in the cloak factories of <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName>.</p><p><seg>It was high noon by the <placeName type="locRef">Jesuit college</placeName> clock when I got to the rear of <placeName type="address" ref="#Karasick">230 West Twelfth street</placeName>, where <persName ref="#employer">David Karasick</persName> has <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" ana="#Karasick">shop</w></phr>. Nobody in but an old man. <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">His</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> is seamed with wrinkles; he has a big nose the color and texture of a mushroom; <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> and half <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> is covered with hair of chinchilla shades; <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">back</w></phr> is humped at the shoulders and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">clothes</w></phr> are filthy and worn.</seg> I ask for work and am told that no hands are needed. <seg>He has a pocket that hangs across <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">waist</w></phr> and into which he puts rags, pieces of thread, hooks and eyes, pins, buttons, and the empty spools that lie on the floor about the vacant machine-chairs. I watch the silent old man as he drags <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> loose <w type="noun">slippers</w></phr> across the floor, and behold I have the key to wealth!</seg> But it doesn't profit me worth a copper. So I survey the premises.</p>
<p>One room, windows on three sides, and all shut. From the north windows I get a view of a two-story hen-house. Filth inside and out. The outlook from the east side is a picture of poverty, squalor, and filth. The buildings have no paint. In some are human beings, in others dumb brutes. Half-washed clothes dangle from window-sills and clothes-lines in tatters and rags. In the yards are heaps of manure and the alleys are foul-smelling and filthy. Along the street move flannel-shirted, horny-handed, sooty-faced men to smoke, to rest, to quarrel, and to dinner. Passing and re-passing all day long and every day&#8212;Sunday and Saturday&#8212;are young women and old women, youths, maidens, and children, with as many cloaks or coats or pants as they can carry. The garbage boxes are reeking with filth. Some one has thrown ashes or sweepings in the box and neither the swill man nor the ash man will remove the contents. <seg><persName ref="#promMen">Mayor Roche</persName> and <persName ref="#promMen">Dr. DeWolf</persName>, equally ignorant of the manner in which <phr><w type="poss" ana="#promMen">their</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#employer">subordinates</w></phr> discharge <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun">duty</w></phr>, permit this sort of thing to go on till the very neighborhood is polluted and the air poisoned by these reeking masses of corruption.</seg></p><p><said who="#promMen" ana="male">Oh, it's nothing,</said> I am told, and <seg>I see for myself and count from <phr><persName ref="#employer">Karasick</persName><w type="poss" ana="#Karasick">'s</w> <w type="noun">window</w></phr> and door eleven of these garbage piles that swarm with maggots and flies.</seg> The sun beating down on the cheap pine box has made the wood shrink, and from constant kicking and shaking and probing of the miserable rag-pickers who inhabit this locality the frame-work has been loosened and the wood carried off for fuel, leaving on almost every block one or more naked heaps of decaying matter.</p><p>Out of the south windows I look into the kitchen of some dozen wretched families. <seg>The children are numerous and almost naked. They are numerous and unclean, so very unclean that it is barely possible to tell <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">complexion</w></phr>.</seg> The mother breaks a loaf in pieces in one house and throws it to the little dirty faces on the doorstep. In another home the children eat from a frying pan and next door all drink from the spout of the teapot. Down in the yard is a pile of filth in which children play and are followed by a lot of chickens. The stable below stairs is locked, but stronger than bolt or hinge is the smell from within, and viler still is the stench from the closets in and about the yard.</p><p><seg>At 12:45 o'clock the hands begin to arrive from lunch, first a young Pole, then a Russian, then a German Jew. They wear woolen shirts and do the machine work&#8212;do it beautifully, too, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">machines</w></phr> go like the wind.</seg> The patriarch in skull cap and slippers goes round the shop looking at one and the other, watching each operator to see that no extra waste of thread is left at the end of the seams. Two more men and then a girl. She does binding, nothing else, and gets $4 a week. At 1 o'clock six young girls are seated at a table in the northwest corner of the shop. They have been running. They are hot, full of fun, and one throws the window up. Like a volley from the enemy roll in the closet and stable smells and I move away to escape it. <seg>The boss is three minutes late. He is a slight, meek man of 35, with a shirt the color of brown soap, dark trousers, and a cheap coat. A light beard covers <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">mouth</w></phr> and chin and the expression in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">eye</w></phr> has that soft, quiet, gentle quality sometimes seen in cattle and sheep.</seg> I tell him I want work.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Machine?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">No.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">You can finish cloaks?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Yes.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Where have you worked?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">A dozen places. <orgName ref="#Stein" type="exposedCompany">Stein's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Ellinger" type="exposedCompany">Ellinger's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Benson" type="exposedCompany">Benson's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Olsen" type="exposedCompany">Olsen's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Newman" type="exposedCompany">Newman's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Schlessinger" type="exposedCompany">Schlessinger's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#NRJC" type="exposedCompany">Never-Rip</orgName>, etc.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Here, finish this. I will see what you can do.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much?</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Eight cents</said>, and <seg>I pray, <persName>Father Abraham</persName>, forgive this thy <phr><w type="poss">son's</w> <w type="noun">oppression</w></phr>.</seg></p><p>I am given a chair at the table with the girls. Propped up on slender sticks is a stout cord, on which is a lot of spool-thread&#8212;white and black, fine, coarse, and medium. <seg>Some more of the philosophy of <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Karasick</persName><phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">'s</w> old <w type="noun">father-in-law</w></phr>.</seg> The thread is not wasted and the girls are not liable to carry it off. I am given a big cotton and wool, principally cotton, ulster to finish. I work like a lash-driven convict on the facing and collar and cuffs till 4 o'clock, and am almost overcome by the air that floats up from the yard below. It is done and I take it to the boss, who examines it for fully five minutes.</p><p><!-- 2016-02-29: nll: There is no open quotes here.--><said who="#employer" ana="male">Too fine. Custom work. Don't need so good on such cloaks. You stay?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much a week?</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Five dollars. You Christian?</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Yes.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Work Sunday?</said>"</p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Never.</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">Then I don't want you. Shop closed Saturday. Shop open Sunday.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">How much if I work five days?</said></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="male">No, you must work six days, like all.</said></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">Not Sunday. Pay me please.</said></p><p>I get out. Out past the stable-door, past the children in the manure-pile, past the ragged, yellow clothes on the line, past the back doors, past the swill-boxes, and the poor, pale-faced women carrying cloaks to and from neighboring shops till <seg>I reach <placeName ref="#Berliner" type="address">147 Twelfth street</placeName>, where <persName ref="#employer">Isaac Berliner</persName> hires me. <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">His</w> <w type="noun" ana="#Berliner">shop</w></phr> is over a rag store and the smell is far-reaching.</seg> Mr. and Mrs. <persName ref="#employer">Berliner</persName><!-- 2016-02-29: nll: How do I tag this??--> work with the men and girls. <seg>There are two rooms, poor light, bad ventilation, low ceilings, disgusting smells from the kitchens, the snarling, faul-finding remarks of the man, the petulance of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">wife</w></phr>, and the filthy condition of the place and the revolting contiguity of so many people were something not to be endured.</seg> <seg>I occupied <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">chair</w></phr> in the dark, crowded room fifteen minutes and left. Like <orgName ref="#Karasick" type="exposedCompany">David Karasick's</orgName> this shop is open all day Sunday.</seg></p><p>In the rear of <placeName type="address" ref="#TailorShop2">441 Taylor street</placeName> I was offered work by a tailor. He had two small rooms in which men and girls were working like slaves on custom coats. <seg>There was a fire in the stove on which the men heated <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employee">their</w> <w type="noun">irons</w></phr>, and two boxes of garbage just outside on the pavement filled the room with <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">odors</w></phr>.</seg></p><p>Leaving the field of cloth and cloaks I applied to <orgName ref="#EAmorris" type="exposedCompany"><persName ref="#employer">E. A. Morris</persName></orgName><!-- 2016-02-29: nll: I'm pretty sure this is a person's name and not an orgName. Double check me just to be sure please!-->, the confectioner, <placeName type="address" ref="#EAmorris">81 West Jackson street</placeName>. The forewoman is a this, bloodless young woman, with wild eyes and unmistakable evidences of overwork.</p><p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">No, I can't give you a place. You are too big. I want little girls. All these hands have been sent to us by peddlers because they are so very poor. You couldn't live on the salaries we pay. These children get $3 and the old hands up-stairs $4.</said></p><p>The midget laborers were filling pans with chocolate and maple caramels. Young boys cut the sheets of soft, brown saccharine stuff into squares which a dozen little girls transferred to the tins. <seg>At deep troughs filled with pop-corn and gum-drops were other children filling small paper bags. Up-stairs the girls worked on <!-- rjp: check transciption -->stick goods. <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Their</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#EAmorris">quarters</w></phr>, while rude and bare and hot from the steaming sirup-pots, were light and airy.</seg></p><p><seg>At <orgName ref="#Brougham" type="exposedCompany"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">Brougham's</w> <w type="noun" ana="#Brougham">packing-house</w></phr></orgName>, <placeName type="address" ref="#Brougham">80 Jackson street</placeName>, I applied for work in the canning-room.</seg> The foreman was kind. He took me out in the dark, little packing-room, in which the light and breeze were fenced off by walls of tin cans. The girls were pale and thin and very young. But, oh, how they did paint! Each stood near a wall of cans that had just been filled with meat&#8212;pressed corned beef, tongue, or ham&#8212;still warm. At hand was a pot of japan paint with which the girls brushed the ends and rimsof each can. I told the foreman I knew I could do the work. He tried me. <seg>I daubed on the paint, held the brush wrong, and got more color on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hands</w></phr> than on the can. The girls laughed at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">awkwardness</w></phr>; so did the foreman. I was chagrined with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">failure</w></phr> and asked for some water to clean <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hands</w></phr>.</seg> The man gave me a benzine bath, and then showed me to a basin of dirty water on the surface of which a hundred or more dead flies were afloat. <seg>The quarters in which these girls work are little more than deadly&#8212;no sunlight, no free fresh air, no place to sit, and the blue paint smeared over <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">hands</w></phr> and arms and dripping from the breast and belt of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">dresses</w></phr>.</seg> <seg><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Their</w> <w type="noun">wages</w></phr> are $5, but each is expected to paint at least fifteen hundred cans per day.</seg> <seg>Dirty little girls in rags and broken shoes, many of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">wrists</w></phr> not thicker than yout two fingers, were in the rear of the shop scouring cans, for which they were paid $3 a week.</seg> The hours of toil are from 7 o'clock to 12 annd from 1 o'clock to 5. The girls were gay and inclined to be happy in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">dungeon slavery</w></phr>, for, after all, they are better paid than scores of help in the employ of <persName ref="#employer">Pardridge</persName>, <persName ref="#employer">Julius Stein</persName>, <persName ref="#employer">Ellinger</persName>, and <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Wellman</persName>.</p><p>At the suggestion of the foreman I took a <placeName type="locRef">Halsted street</placeName> car<!-- 2016-03-02: nll: I don't think Halsted gets tagged, but just wanted to make sure.--> for the stock-yards, and with so much experience presented myself at the <orgName ref="#Fairbank" type="exposedCompany">Fairbank Canning company</orgName>. I did not see <persName ref="#employer">Mr. N. K.</persName>, and what is more didn't want to see him. The girls, numbering a hundred or so, were at work up on the second floor in onw of the numerous buildings. They painted and labeled by the piece, getting 5 cents a hundred. Plenty of girls handled 2,500 cans a day, giving them a salary of $7.50 a week. Experienced hands earned $9 and beginners and dryers $4 per week. No provision was made for the comfort of these girls. They swept the greasy floors when necessary, packed the goods, and were jostled and pushed about by the bloody butchers and greasy packers. All worked in cast-off clothing, many literally dripping with paint. <seg>A great many of the girls were Irish, but the Swedes and Germans were numerous. I can not understand how they endure the work which, while purely mechanical, requires them to be on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">feet</w></phr> from 7 to 5:30 every day, and from all I could learn they do not stand it.</seg> Few with whom I talked have been in the yards five years; all wanted to get married, not to have money and nice clothes and theater tickets, but to get rested.</p><p><seg>At <orgName ref="#PDArmour" type="exposedCompany"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">P. D. Armour's</w> <w type="noun" ana="#PDArmour">packing-house</w></phr></orgName> the girls were paid from 3 cents to 5 cents per hundred for labeling and japanning cans, wages varying from $6 to $9.</seg> <seg>Beginners received 75 cents a day for two weeks, or until they could handle fifteen hundred cans per day, when they received $6, and were raised to the maximum figure as <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">skill</w></phr> increased.</seg> <seg>As at <orgName ref="#Fairbank" type="exposedCompany">Fairbank's</orgName>, they were young girls with haggard faces, emaciated figures, and work-weary bodies. At noon they sat in the windows to eat <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">lunch</w></phr>, and the vessel on the zinc from which they slaked <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">thirst</w></phr> was nothing more elaborate then a tin can down.</seg> <seg>It is certainly very good of <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Armour</persName> to build Sunday-schools, educate struggling artists, buy pictures, and patronize music, but these young women are human if <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">smells</w></phr> of the slaughtering establishment and a clean sitting-room with neat walls and chairs in which to rest at noon and clean towels for the 6-o'clock toilet would not be wasted charity.</seg></p><p><seg>These girls are called <hi rend="double">tough.</hi> Perhaps they are. Perhaps <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">language</w></phr> is not chaste nor <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">manners</w></phr> pleasing, but <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Armour</persName> and <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Fairbank</persName> know as well as need be known that <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">hearts</w></phr> are pure and <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">lives</w></phr> blameless. Considering <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">origin</w></phr>, <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">nature</w></phr>, <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">surroundings</w></phr>, and <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">associates</w></phr> they are too good to be put on the level they are.</seg></p><p><persName ref="#nellNelson">NELL NELSON.</persName></p></div><div type="headline"><list><item>SCHLESINGER'S SLOP-SHOP</item></list></div><div type="headlines"><!-- 2016-03-30: nll: This section is bolded and isn't really part of the article body, so I made a new div element and named it subHeadline. It's just a placeholder, so someone can change it!!--><list><item>Working Nearly a Day On a Cloak to Earn Ten Cents&#8212;Girls Who Toll For Three Dollars a Week and Board Themselves.</item></list></div><div type="articleBody"><p>Another day in a slop&#8212;a shop where I get a blinding headache and a dime.</p><p>The place of servitude is at <placeName type="address" ref="#Schlessinger">1187 Milwaukee avenue</placeName> and the proprietors are <orgName ref="#Schlessinger" type="exposedCompany">Mr. and Mrs. <persName ref="#employer">Schlessinger</persName> and son</orgName><!-- 2016-03-30: nll: How would I tag a group of people??-->. It is 9 o'clock when I enter what seems to be a store. On the right is a small office containing a desk and a mountain of cloaks. Two yards back is a long cutting-board at which the father, mother, and son are chalking or cutting out cloth. <seg>The old man has the everlasting frosts on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr>, and in the <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">wife's</w> <w type="noun">hair</w></phr> is more silver than jet. The son is still in the morning of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">manhood</w></phr>. <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">His</w> <w type="noun">manner</w></phr> is arrogant, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">tone</w></phr> harsh, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">treatment</w></phr> of an old Christian, who has come in with a letter, presumably from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">wife</w> or <w type="noun">daughter</w></phr> soliciting work, is painful to contemplate.</seg> <seg>I feel like a vagabond when <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName> demands an explanation for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">presence</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">I was here yesterday and you told me I might come to work today,</said> I venture to remark.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Oh, yes. You was the one that looked on yesterday and asked all about the wages, hey?</said></p><p>T<seg>his is overwhelming and I tremble internally, expecting every moment to be seized by <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> jersey <w type="noun">collar</w></phr> and Psyche knot and thrown out in the car-track. I bite <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">lips</w></phr> to keep <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">knees</w></phr> from knocking.</seg></p><p>When she says <said who="#employer" ana="female">Well, you may come this way,</said> <seg>I am thankful for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">safety</w></phr> and follow.</seg> Half-way down the store is a partition some five feet high, hung on both sides with cloaks and jackets, braided sacques and Dutch dresses, which contrivance screens the girls on the opposite side from view. A short distance back is a perfact embankment of work, fringe and inner trimmings. Passing these two fortifications we came into the presence of the "sweaters," all but six of whom are running machines at a tremendous speed.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Girls! Girls!</said> exclaimed <persName>Mrs. Schlessinger</persName>.</p><p>Some of the little engines stop.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Girls! Girls!</said> she says again.</p><p><seg>They all stop. And so does <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">breathing</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">This girl has come to work here</said>, <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName> continues. <said who="#employer" ana="female">I aint got no time to learn her. You all help her if you got time.</said></p><p>With this unheard of and unexpected introduction <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName> leaves me. <seg>I find a dusty table near a dirty <choice><sic>zinc</sic><reg resp="#rjp">sink</reg></choice> to put <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">hat</w></phr> and ask for a machine.</seg></p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Can you run a machine?</said> the head of the establishment asks.</p><p>I tell her a falsehood which I defend by personally arguing that I can do anything that these untutored young foreigners can perform. Determined to try I drop into a chair before a big <hi rend="double">Household</hi> and agony begins. <seg>I endeavor to apply <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">knowledge</w></phr> of the <orgName ref="#WandW">Wheeler &amp; Wilson</orgName> to the machine.</seg> Trouble follows. The wheel is not under the table and is not meant to turn forward. The thread breaks a dozen times in twenty-four minutes, the intervening time being spent in the threading the needle, which, like an equestrienne, has a side seat. I hem and tuck rags to get the stitch. The bobbin gives out, and how to fill it again, thread the shuttle and lace the top cotton gives me much trouble. <seg>A little German girl at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">left</w></phr> throws an occasional hint of value to me. She has a frightful cold in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> which she frankly confesses she cought the night before in <placeName type="locRef">Wicker park</placeName>.</seg> I offer to help her, agreeing th stitch all day if she will only tell me how to put the work together. It's a bargain. I bind the edges of the front, back, and side gores, get the hood in shape, and stitch the pockets. <seg>Just as I am beginning to feel like a Household conqueror <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName> comes along and throws a bundled Dutch dress on <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">machine-table</w></phr> and tells me to make it.</seg> I protest that I had much rather help <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie</persName>, fearing I may not get the cloak right.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Just make it. When it aint right you rip it. That's the way we learn the girls.</said></p><p>Of course the string and sleeves, cuffs, hood, pocket laps, collar, fronts, side bodies, back gores, back straps, and three skirt breadths are spread out before me. I seize a bunch of bias binding and I bind and rip and rip and bind till noon, marveling all the time at the work that literally rolls out all about me. <seg>Poor <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Annie's</w> <w type="noun">eyes</w></phr> get red; so does <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> little <w type="noun">nose</w></phr>; <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">face</w></phr> swells, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">voice</w></phr> gets husky, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">handkerchief</w></phr> is as wet as a laundry.</seg> She has only made two garments working from 7 to 12. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I only made 40 cents this morning,</said> she said, <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">but it's this awful cold. I can make six when I work hard. I usually earn $7 a week. Some times it's more, but not often, and some times it's less. I must go home now.</said></p><p><seg>She folds up <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">work</w></phr>, covers <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">machine</w></phr> with <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">apron</w></phr>, has the two dresses entered in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">book</w></phr>, and goes off to nurse <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">cold</w></phr>.</seg></p><p>A girl with a complexion like a peach and light blue eyes says she has been working four years. <seg><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I began at 14 in <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#Zimmerman"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">Zimmerman's</w> <w type="noun" ana="#Zimmerman">factory</w></phr></orgName>,</said></seg> she says. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">There I got so I could make $1 a day easily, but I had awful headaches and the doctor said I must only sew three days in the week. Then I went to the shop every other day for a year, but the pain didn't go away and the doctor said it was the stream power and made me leave. <seg>Since I have worked by foot <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> is all right. Yes, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">my</w> <w type="noun">parents</w></phr> are living and own a little cottage on <placeName type="locRef">Sedgwick street</placeName>.</seg></said></p><p>The hand girls were all beginners. They were all ages from 11 to 16, earning $1, $2, and $3 a week sewing on buttons, putting in bustles, and filling the inside linings. Most of them were Swedes and unable to speak a word of English. All the hands brought big lunches of bread, sausage, or ham, and fruit pancake. <seg>I was hungry enough to devour <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> worst <w type="noun">enemy</w></phr> and not withstanding I interviewed a dozen or more of the diners not a morsel was offered me.</seg> There was an hour for noon, but most of the machines were thundering away at 12:30. The closets, two in number, were down in the cellar, and the foulness of the place was sickening. A kerosene lamp, hung four feet from the floor partially lit the dark passage along which were coal-sheds and closets in suites for the several flats in the building.</p><p><seg>At 3 o'clock <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">cloak</w></phr> was not finished. I had pains in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">head</w></phr> and back, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">ankles</w></phr> ached, <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">feet</w></phr> were scalded with heat and perspiration from the constant motion of the machine.</seg> No need of acting this time. I simply went to <persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName> and told her I had no dinner and was too faint to work another moment.</p><p><said who="#employer" ana="female">Didn't you have no lunch?</said> she asked. <said who="#employer" ana="female">Why didn't you tell me? I could have given you a cup of coffee.</said></p><p><seg>I thanked her for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">her</w> good <w type="noun">intention</w></phr>, and asked to be paid.</seg> <said who="#employer" ana="female">Well, that Dutch dress is 20 cents. If you done half you get half pay. That's right, ain't it? I tell you you can't make a living at this; it's too hard for a woman that ain't used to it. I vould like to pay more, for when the girls make I make, don't you see?</said></p><p>F<seg>or the sake of exit I acqiesced; took <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">dime</w></phr>, and went out.</seg> At the door I met two little Polish children, <persName ref="#workingGirl">Polly</persName> and <persName ref="#workingGirl">Annie Schmidt</persName>, who told me they lived at <placeName type="address" ref="#workingGirl">318 George street</placeName>, near <placeName type="locRef">Carpenter</placeName>, and could not get work in the shop till they were <hi rend="double">leven.</hi> <seg>Both had a basket of greasy, filthy victuals they had picked along the alleyways and into <phr><persName ref="#workingGirl">Polly</persName><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">'s</w> <w type="noun">hamper</w></phr> I dropped <phr><persName ref="#employer">Mrs. Schlessinger</persName><w type="poss" ana="#employer">'s</w> bright <w type="noun">dime</w></phr> for luck.</seg></p><p><seg>Some day soon I shall use the money so kindly sent to the editor of <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> for a <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">shop-girls'</w> <w type="noun">shoe</w></phr> and stocking party (and little <persName ref="#workingGirl">Polly</persName> and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">sister</w></phr> shall have a card)</seg>.</p><p><seg>You poor, dependent, neglected girl, who started out in real earnest, without education or training, to earn <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> own <w type="noun">living</w></phr> from the bottom of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#nellNelson">my</w> <w type="noun">heart</w></phr> I pity you.</seg> I have been thinking all day where I could send you for aid and instruction, but as I believe in the goodness of woman I do not know where you can find one to succor you. There's <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Tillie M. Carse</persName> with ther eloquent, soulful eyes. But she is begging $100,000 for a temperance temple and has no time to give you help or counsel.</p><p>Go to see <persName ref="#promWomen">Miss Willard</persName>?</p><p><seg>She is sympathetic. It will do you heart good to meet her for she will call you <hi rend="double">dear child</hi> when you have told her <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">errand</w></phr>, and press <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">hand</w></phr> in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#promWomen">her</w> warm <w type="noun">palm</w></phr>, and tell you&#8212;well, I don't know what she will tell you, for she and <persName ref="#promWomen">Miss Mary Allen West</persName> have a heap to do</seg> between <seg>the <orgName ref="#WoCo"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> <w type="noun">council</w></phr></orgName>, the <orgName ref="#WNL"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> National <w type="noun">league</w></phr></orgName>, the <orgName ref="#WSuff"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> <w type="noun">suffrage</w></phr></orgName>, the <orgName ref="#WCTU"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> Christian Temperance <w type="noun">union</w></phr></orgName>, and the <orgName ref="#ProhibParty">prohibition party</orgName>. There is <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. George Marsh</persName>&#8212;but she can spare no time from the Industrial school; <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. A. A. Carpenter</persName> has a big heart, but the <orgName ref="#WoEx"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> <w type="noun">exchange</w></phr></orgName> fills it, and so it is with <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Blatchford</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Hobbs</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Leander Stone</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. N. K. Fairbank</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Field</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Armour</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. J. M. Flower</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. A. L. Coe</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. S. M. Allerton</persName> and <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Potter Palmer</persName>. They have <orgName ref="#StLuke">St. Luke</orgName>, the <placeName type="address" ref="#StLuke">Illinois street</placeName> boarding-house, the <orgName ref="#WoChrist"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Woman's</w> Christian <w type="noun">boarding-house</w></phr></orgName>, the <orgName ref="#DAS">Decorative Art society</orgName>, or the <orgName ref="#GFS"><phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">Girls'</w> Friendly <w type="noun">society</w></phr></orgName>, and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">case</w></phr> doesn't come under any of these. don't you see?</seg></p><p><persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Dr. Clinton Locke</persName> is a dear, good woman who has, perhaps, done more real charity for the <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> poor than any woman on the <placeName type="locRef">South side</placeName>. A few years ago she went <hi rend="double">slumming</hi>&#8212;that's what they call it in <placeName type="city">New York</placeName>&#8212;went out <placeName type="locRef">Archer avenue</placeName> and along <placeName type="locRef">Nineteenth</placeName>, <placeName type="locRef">Twentieth</placeName>, <placeName type="locRef">Butterfield</placeName>, <placeName type="locRef">Clark</placeName>, <placeName type="locRef">John's place</placeName>, <placeName type="locRef">Liberty court</placeName>, and <placeName type="locRef">Canalport avenue</placeName> into the holes and hovels under and above the sidewalk and in and among the stables and woodsheds, where she personally taught ignorant Irish, Polish, Swedish, German, and Italian mothers how to make broth from scraps, gruels from chaff, and tempting cookies from cheap flours. <seg>She made them keep account books for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#promWomen">her</w> <w type="noun">inspection</w></phr> and forced them to buy bones and joints for soup and cheap cuts instead of steaks for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">husband</w>'s meals</phr>.</seg> <seg>She gave them lessons in <hi rend="double">drips,</hi> taught them how to make a plaster, a petticoat, soft soap, and molasses-cake, helped them smother the fire during the cool days and sift the ashes for cold weather; preached the economy of cleanliness, sobriety, cheerfulness, and industry, and helped many and many a mother to make herself and <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> <w type="noun">family</w></phr> decent.</seg> <seg>She has done <phr><w type="poss" ana="#promWomen">her</w> <w type="noun">share</w> of mission-work</phr> west of <placeName type="locRef">State street</placeName></seg>, and <seg>what you want, poor little machine-slave, is another <persName ref="#promWomen">Mrs. Locke</persName> to rise up and teach you how to sew, how to keep <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">clothes</w></phr> and body neat, how to sit at <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">work-table</w></phr>, how to care for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">health</w></phr> and save <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> vital <w type="noun">energy</w></phr>.</seg> You must be taught that profanity, <hi rend="double">mashes,</hi> the midnight picnic, the pop-corn-parties-in-the-park, the <hi rend="double">Dago lunches,</hi> and the insults of the street advances of car men, <hi rend="double">society</hi> men, and factory men are the very ruination of all that is lovely and holy and good in woman. You must be taught that you are not to be herded and driven like cattle nor scourged and robbed like convicts. <seg>You must be taught that you are a woman, that you live in <placeName type="country">America</placeName>, that you are <hi rend="double">some account,</hi> and that there are hundreds of women who will help you to help yourself and thousands of men who will want no better pastime than to knock down the creature who insults <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">your</w> <w type="noun">womanhood</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><persName ref="#nellNelson">NELL NELSON.</persName></p></div><div type="headline"><list><item>VOICES OF THE PEOPLE</item></list></div><div type="headline"><!-- 2016-03-30: nll: This section is bolded and isn't really part of the article body, so I made a new div element and named it subHeadline. It's just a placeholder, so someone can change it!!--><list><item>The Wealthy Are L<damage agent="smudge" unit="chars" quantity="4"/><unclear/> Up W<damage agent="smudge" unit="chars" quantity="4"/><unclear/> Against a Day of Wrath.</item></list></div><div type="letterToTheEditor"><p>TO THE EDITOR: <seg>It is a mistake to suppose that the <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> employers of cheap female labor confine <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun">attention</w></phr> to that city alone. No, no, they are as many-mouthed as any octopus and gather in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun" ana="#workingGirl #employee">victims</w></phr> with each capacious maw.</seg> <seg>These philanthropists would scorn to limit <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun">sphere of usefulness</w></phr> and consequently employ agents, who appear to be converts to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun">points of view</w></phr>, in many country towns not only in <placeName type="state">Illinois</placeName> but in neighboring states.</seg> For munificence the prices paid in the country for crochet work by an agent for a <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> dry-goods house compare well with those of the <orgName ref="#WLMC" type="exposedCompany">Western Lace Manufacturing company</orgName>. The country worker, if she has no other means of conveyance, must walk to the nearest town. There she will receive wool enough to make several dozen toboggan caps. By working from 7:30 a. m. until the same hour in the evening she may manage to make three of these a day, and she will be paid 6 cents a piece. Other articles, commonly called fascinators&#8212;the name may strike the workers as being what the late <persName>Artemus Ward</persName> called <hi rend="double">sarkasm</hi>&#8212;pay even better. The price is the same, but four can be made in a day. <seg>The country lasses can take <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">choice</w></phr> on which article of headgear they will grow rich.</seg> The wreched part of it all is that the agents have small difficulty in finding girls willing to undertake the work, so scarce is work that the opportunity for making a few dollars is eagerly seized. What wonder that country girls leave home, hoping for better things in the great cities. That they but escape <persName>Scylla</persName> to fall on <persName>Charybdis</persName> <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> has all too plainly made manifest.</p><p><seg>What seems to be needed is a home in the city for young women who work for a living, where they can live in comfort on a small sum and be assisted in <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">endeavor</w> to find respectable employment</phr>. Something of the kind has , I am given to understand, been started, but on a very limited scale for want of funds.</seg> <seg>This misery need not be, could not be, if those who can afford it would give more generously, and if those who do give would exercise <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">benevolence</w></phr> in a proper direction.</seg> In <placeName type="country">England</placeName>, where the wages of women are as pitiful as those quoted by <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>, &#163;475,442<!-- 2016-04-02: nll: &#163; is the British pound sign unicode!!--> was given last year to foreign missions; and in <placeName type="country">England</placeName> the streets of the large cities, especially of <placeName type="city">London</placeName>, swarm with prostitutes. So many are there that it is a mockery to attempt to arrest them. <seg><placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> is not overmoral now, and if the mills of the gods are allowed to grind on as they are grinding now&#8212;and grinding down the poor and helpless&#8212;we shall have the same state of things in <phr><w type="poss">our</w> own <w type="noun">city</w></phr> when we, too, have a population of over four millions of souls.</seg></p><p>Is it a matter of such wonderful congratulation that there is a church to about every four blocks in <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> when the poor never enter them? Do you see the working-classes in <orgName ref="#GraceCh">Grace church</orgName>, <orgName ref="#StJohn">St. John's</orgName>, <orgName ref="#Lorimer"><persName>Dr. Lorimer</persName>'s</orgName>, the <orgName ref="#SecPresb">Second Presbyterian</orgName>, or even at <orgName ref="#Swing"><persName>Prof. Swing</persName>'s</orgName> services? Is there a single <hi rend="double">fashionable</hi> church in <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> where the poor and rich meet together? <seg>Is it not, indeed, requiring a great deal of philosophy when we expect young people to display <phr><w type="poss">their</w> shabby <w type="noun">clothes</w></phr> in such places?</seg> With what feelings do you suppose these young people listen to the anthem which bids them <hi rend="double">Trust the Lord, wait patiently on him.</hi> What aspect can religion take on for them. <seg>A writer to <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>, who signs herself <hi rend="double"><persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary</persName></hi> says concerning <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">her</w> own <w type="noun" ana="#employer">employer</w></phr> and that of others: <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">If such men are not punished in this world then I can only cherish the hope that there is another where punishment will be meted out to them. What are we living for?</said></seg> she goes on.<seg> Another few years of injustice and hardship and <persName ref="#workingGirl">Mary</persName> and many others will be living for the avowed purpose of taking <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">revenge</w></phr> in this world.</seg></p><p>The employers talk about <hi rend="double">crushing out anarchy.</hi> They are building it up. What kind of citizens do they expect the sons of the working women of <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> to be? Will they be taught to look upon the rich as brethren in the <persName>Lord</persName>? I fancy not. Self-interest alone should move the influential men and women of <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> to stop this human slavery. Think how hideous are the disparities in a great city like <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> in the eyes of the poor. Think how many noble natures are crushed into the mire by the force of mere physical want. Think of the temptations of the poor, of the sadness of the home where the parents see in each little child given them but a future bread-winner! <seg>Remember how much more lenient we are to the crimes of the rich than to those of the poor. We only help the <hi rend="double">deserving</hi> poor, and often keep <phr><w type="poss">our</w> sweetest <w type="noun">smiles</w></phr> and best civilities for rich men whose money has not been honestly acquired and whose morals are shocking, and rich women who never thought a noble thought or did a generous act.</seg> <hi rend="double">The hand that rocks the cradle rocks the world.</hi> <seg>Don't harden that hand by too much unpaid work, for the heart will keep pace and then, as an outcast, the desperate women will be already <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">compulsory</supplied></unclear> on parents and guardians so <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">children</w> and <w type="noun">wards</w></phr> to the public school and a given number of months in the year.</seg></p><p><hi rend="double">It is a shame to <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> girls and women to work for such grinding, <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">niggardly</supplied></unclear> wages,</hi> says still <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/>. And yet it will not do for a tariff-return organ like <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> to advocate protection to even this <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> or labor. In other words, why <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">insist</supplied></unclear> that these shall be paid higher wages, when if these places were made vacant you could <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">mall</supplied></unclear> every place several times over in a single day by a single advertisement in <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>? The free trade factory, if right at all, must be right in regard to wages; and if <seg>a manufacturer must take an open market for the sale of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun">products</w></phr> he must have an open labor market in which to obtain <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">his</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#employee #workingGirl">help</w></phr></seg>. <seg>It is scarcely within the range of a possible philanthropy to take all these hapless victims of the worst phase of labor and give them good clothes, good educations, happy homes, and hives of <damage agent="blurred" unit="chars" quantity="4"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">bile</supplied></unclear>ness by any public process. And, while <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">lot</w></phr> is a hard one, it is none the less apparent that it would be much harder if they were denied or could not get the work they are now doing even at the miserable apology for wages of which you complain.</seg> <seg>Perhaps if these manufacturers were guaranteed double price for <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun">product</w></phr> they would at once double the price of wages to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#employer">their</w> <w type="noun" ana="#workingGirl #employee"><choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employes</reg></choice></w></phr>, and yet the country resounds with the partisan cry of <hi rend="double">Cheap everything,</hi> which from sheer force of sympathy <damage agent="blurred" unit="chars" quantity="4"/><unclear/>udes cheap wages.</seg> <seg>But these girls and <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">desperate</supplied></unclear> women are in the world, and must, like everybody else, work <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">way</w></phr> through it.</seg> Active labor is better than idleness for woman or man. But labor ought to be respected even in a factory that pays small wages, and in this respect <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> is a good missionary agent. The measures of manufacturers is often manifested in <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">indignities</supplied></unclear> offered to help <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> and unnecessary burdens that are harder to be borne than the poorly paid labor. Added to this comes the temptation&#8212;often emphasized by this <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> supervision&#8212;to wrong doing as an <hi rend="double">easier way</hi> to <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">case</supplied></unclear>, and it is a compliment to the native modesty and virtue of the sex that while the list of the overtempted is a long one it is not ten times as long.</p><p>But <seg>these poor working-women are with us and they are here to stay. What will society do with them? Order <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun" ana="#employer">employers</w></phr> to pay them more and treat them better?</seg> Who can enforce such an order in the face of such overprotection of labor from that source? Women have crowded into all fields of labor and nearly cut in twain the former wages of men. Have we too many girls and women? If so, how shall we reduce the number? By the process common in <placeName type="country">India</placeName> or the theory of <persName>Besant</persName>?</p><p><persName>P.</persName></p></div><div type="headline"><list><item>A Possible Remedy.</item></list></div><div type="letterToTheEditor"><p>CHICAGO, <date when="1888-08-02">Aug. 2</date>&#8212;TO THE EDITOR: If ever a newspaper deserved credit for unflinching courage in advocating the cause of the oppressed when to do so must bring the hatred of the rich and powerful surely <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> now deserves full stint of praise. The boldness with which it publishes name, place, and manner of the offenders is as remarkable as the reports of <persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName> are vivid and stirring in description of cruelties inflicted on the <hi rend="double">white slaves.</hi> These articles must bring good results. They will arouse strong indignation, which may in the end lead to devising some means for regulating the treatment of now defenseless employers. They will certainly warn the thousands of girls who foolishly wish to come from innocent and safe homes to seek work in the city. If the articles serve no other end than to keep such girls safe at home they will have done a most noble work.</p><p>But these downtrodden girls deserving of the <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">waring</supplied></unclear> sympathy the articles in <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> excite? <seg>Is it not true than many if not all of these workers prefer <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun">lot</w></phr>, with all its hardships, privations, <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#nll">lawsuits</supplied></unclear>, and , too often, its prostitution and utter ruin of body and soul, to honest work which may be harder than that of the shops, but which affords plentiful and good food, honorable shelter, and much larger pay than they now get&#8212;assuming that the reports published by <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> are true of all or of the majority of shop girls?</seg> Judging from those reports the tasks of the shops, the bending over sewing or other machines, the confinement behind counters without opportunity for rest, the long hours in close rooms, the exposure to stormy weather, and the want of sufficient nutritious food must be at least as hard to bear as more active work would be under more healthful surroundings.</p><p><seg>Is it not a fact that if one-half of the number of girls now working in shops were to withdraw the other half could dictate terms to <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun" ana="#employer">employers</w></phr></seg><choice><sic></sic><reg resp="#rjp">?</reg></choice><!-- 2016-04-03: nll: There is no punctuation mark here.--> If this is true do not the girls bring on themselves needlessly all they endure? Is it not a fact that every one of these girls can, if she will accept it, get respectable, healthful, and profitable employment? If she will not take such work is she deserving of sympathy and aid? If she persists in staying in the shops does she not deliberately choose to endure all that follows rather than help the thousands who are begging for the services of bright, capable girls? <seg>Would it not be well for the girls to look the case squarely in the face, that they may see a truth patent to many of <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">their</w> <w type="noun" subtype="refTo" ana="#workingGirl">friends</w></phr>, and then act promptly and decisively, each for herself?</seg> <seg>They need no help from legislation nor from <phr><w type="poss" ana="#workingGirl">women's</w> aid <w type="noun">societies</w></phr> of any description to relieve themselves from the oppression so vividly described by <persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName>, for a rem<damage agent="blurred" unit="chars" quantity="2"/><unclear/>ly for all <phr><w type="poss">their</w> <w type="noun">wrongs</w></phr> lies in <phr><w type="poss">their</w> own <w type="noun">hands</w></phr>.</seg></p><p><persName>P. E. W</persName></p></div><!-- 2016-04-03: nll: The continuation of the VOICES OF THE PEOPLE section is cut off in the available NYU PDFS. Ideally the project would want to have all parts of the series including these direct responses in our database, but until we are able to re-photograph these articles the transcription will have to end here or sit mid-paragraph unfinished. Note: these responses are also not included in the Barkley text.--></div></body></text>
</TEI>