<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            
            <title corresp="#CT010"><date when="1888-08-08">Wednesday Morning, August 8, 1888</date></title>
            <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">newtFire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
            <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#nll">Nicole Lottig</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
               <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:-->
            <!--<respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="yyyy-mm-dd">yyyy-mm-dd</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2016-07-14">yyyy-mm-dd</date>. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2014</date>
            <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <div type="headlines">
               <list>
                  <item><hi rend="double">Nell Nelson</hi> Investigates the Boston Store and Is Shocked at What She Finds.</item>
                  <item>A Basement That on a Hot Day Is So Stifling It Reminds One of the <hi rend="double">Black Hole of Calcutta.</hi></item>
                  <item>Hundreds of Ill-Fed, Wan-Faced Children Working from 7:45 Until 6:30.</item>
                  <item>And Receiving in Exchange for the Terrible Drudgery and Hard Labor a Miserly $2 or $3 a Week.</item>
                  <item>The Managers Make Haste to Explain, but Their Explanation Scarcely Betters the Matter.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="articleBody">
               <p>For dismal surroundings, economy of comforts, and heartless treatment, to the <orgName ref="#BostonStore" type="exposedCompany">Boston store</orgName> belongs the palm.</p>
               <p>I did not work in that establishment although I tried very hard to do so. I was in the store at 8 o'clock on Friday morning as arranged with <persName ref="#employer"><!-- 2016-07-14: nll: I did some research and Mr. Hillman was the manager of the Boston store for a while in 1888, does this mean he's the employer? -->Mr. Hillman</persName>, who had partially promised to hire me. <said who="#employer" ana="male">One of the girls in the hosiery department</said> he had said <said who="#employer" ana="male">is sick, and if she doesn't come back Friday morning I will try you.</said></p>
               <p>I could not find the gentleman, although I hunted the main floor and the floors above and below. My plan of fluctuation was to take the elevator up one story and walk down, then ride up two and walk down the third flight, in that way I took in the entire store and a great part of the <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#nll">employees</reg></choice>. I began at the bottom and spent a full hour in the basement, where I saw so much and suffered so much that the upper floors had no surprises for me. In the first place the atmosphere was almost unendurable.</p>
               <p>Hot! It must have been</p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <p></p>
            </div><!-- RJP: some articles concluded with an advertisement refering to later publications of the series ... I created this <div> because we want to capture those ads but have them sitting separately from the text of the article itself. If the article you are transcribing does not have an advertisement simply delete or comment out this final div-->
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
