<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../..//webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title corresp="#CT012"><date when="1888-08-10">Friday Morning, August 10, 1888</date></title>
                <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">Newtfire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
                <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and partial coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#bas">Brooke Stewart</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-07-11">2016-07-11</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:-->
                <!--<respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-01-01">2016-01-01</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2016-01-07">2016-01-07</date>. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item>Places Where Virtue Counts for Nothing and Is Not Tolerated by the Employer,</item>
                        <item>Body and Soul Must Be Given Up to the Scoundrels or the <choice><sic>Employe</sic><reg resp="#bas">Employee</reg></choice> Loses Her Situation.</item>
                        <item>Practicing the Arts of the Fiend In Order to Debauch Helpless Girlhood and Womanhood.</item>
                        <item>In the Book-Binderies the Young Women by Hand and Incessant Toil Make from $4 to $8 a Week.</item>
                        <item>Tailors' Serfs Who Are Running a Race <damage agent="smudge" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#bas">for</supplied></unclear> Life Neck and Neck with the Demon of Starvation.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="articleBody">
                    <p><said who="#inspector" ana="male">Do you want to visit a manufacturing establishment, generally held in high repute, where a girl's tenure of place depends upon the degrading concessions she may be induced to make to her employer.</said></p>
                    <p>The question was put to a reporter of <name ref="#CT">The Times</name> by Inspector <persName ref="#promMen">George Bodgers</persName> of the health department. They had just formed a temporary copartnership under the name and style of <hi rend="double">we</hi> to make a thorough examination of the hells and holes where human beings hive, delve, and thrive or die under the guise of <hi rend="double">employees</hi>.</p>
                    <p><said who="#reporter" ana="male">Well, I'll tell you the story I know and I know it to be true and so does my wife. A girl of good development and modest demeanor had for some time been employed in a book-bindery and had become fairly well skilled. One afternoon she turned in, as the result of her day's work, four books. The foreman complained that the work was imperfect—in fact, that the books were spoiled, and told the girl she must pay for them. She asked for particulars but could get little satisfaction. She became indignant and was thrust aside. Remembering that other mouths than hers were awaiting the food her scanty earnings must purchase she pleaded first for justice and then for mercy.</said></p>
                    <p><said who="#reporter" ana="male"><said who="#foreperson" ana="male">You quit work with the rest at 6 o'clock</said>, said the foreman. <said who="#foreperson" ana="male">Come back fifteen minutes later and perhaps I may straighten out your account so that you will lose nothing.</said> The girl, hesitating between hope and fear, crossed the bridge as if to go homeward, and then returned to the office. The foreman was at the door, welcomed by her within, and turned the key. He assured her he had helped many of the girls in the employ of the firm to balance their accounts after business hours. Be that as it may, he had made a grave miscalculation in this case, and in less seconds than it takes to tell it he was glad he hadn't lost the key to the door. The girl came directly to my house, told her story, and never returned to the tiger's lair. Her case is but one of many, and if she adheres to her present decision it will be the particular one of the many before the firm and the foreman hear the last of it. Now come with me and we'll take a trip through the binderies and printing establishments, and before we get through I'll show you the fiend who endeavored to ruin this young girl.</said></p>
                    <p>Our first visit of inspection was made to the five-story and basement building, <placeName type="address" ref="#JMco">118 and 120 Monroe street</placeName>, occupied by the <orgName ref="#JMco">John Morris company</orgName>, printers, binders, and lithographers. On the main floor the superintendent gave us two yellow tickets, each guaranteeing a single ride in a freight elevator at the rear to the fifth floor. <said ana="male" who="#employee">You must walk down,</said> he added, encouragingly. To the fifth floor we went, and to a <damage agent="blurred" unit="chars" quantity="2"/><unclear><supplied resp="#bas">all</supplied></unclear> appearances arrived unannounced, as the foreman was frank. A girl acknowledged she was but 14 years old and worked ten hours a day, and the closets were in bad condition. Groping our way down a dark and narrow stairway to the second floor we learned that the foreman had been called to the office.</p>
                    <p><said ana="male" who="#inspector">How old are you?</said> asked the inspector of a boy feeding a press.</p>
                    <p><said ana="male" who="#employee">Seventeen,</said> he replied, winking at a companion when the inspector's back was turned, as much as to say that he knew his business. Apparently he was about 1<damage agent="blurred" unit="chars" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#bas">3</supplied></unclear>, and probably that was his age, as it was admitted that four boys and two girls under legal age were regularly employed.</p>
                    <p>Save as to ill-kept closets on the three upper floors and a scarcity even of that undesireable kind the sanitary condition of the premises is fair, light and ventilation being abundant. Of the 305 <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#bas">employees</reg></choice> 220 are males and eighty-five are females. The wages of the latter range from $3 to $10 a week, averaging $5, and the male average is $12.50.</p>
                    <p><said ana="female" who="#foreperson">Aren't you from <name ref="#CT">The Times</name>?</said> asked one of the forewomen in a quizzical way.</p>
                    <p><said who="#reporter" ana="male">Do I look like a woman?</said></p>
                    <p><said ana="female" who="#foreperson">You might be <hi rend="single"><persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName></hi> disguised in pants for all I know. But I don't care if you are; I'll tell you all I know.</said></p>
                    <p><hi rend="double">Facilis descensus avemi</hi> doesn't apply to going down-stairs in this factory, because it isn't easy to get down, and the lower you get—that is to say, the nearer you approach the manager's desk—the more heavenly the situation. Ceilings rise in gradation and stairways expand until <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Morris</persName>' handsome office is reached.</p>
                    <p><said who="#inspector" ana="male">The health department claims that there should be one closet for every twenty <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#bas">employees</reg></choice>,</said> said the inspector.</p>
                    <p><said who="#employer" ana="male">But ours are only for use in case of emergency,</said> replied <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Morris</persName>. <said who="#employer" ana="male">We didn't put them in for the accommodation of our help, and they are not expected to visit them during working hours; their time belongs to us. It is work that we want from them.</said></p>
                    <p>This was said partly in self-defense and partly in repartee, but even with apologetic explanation it grates harshly on the ear. By an expenditure of a few hundred dollars the health, safety, and comfort of three-hundred persons employed by a firm having hundreds of thousands of dollars invested could be assured. And at the same time it must be admitted that this is one of the very best regulated establishments of the kind in <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName>. The story told by the inspector did not relate to the <orgName ref="#JMco">John Morris company</orgName>.</p><!-- RJP:2016-07-11: THE REST OF THIS TRANSCRIPTION was completed by Rebecca Parker -->
                    <p>At <orgName ref="#Ettlinger" type="exposedCompany">Ettlinger's</orgName> print-house and bindery, <placeName type="address" ref="#Ettlinger">180 and 182 Monroe street</placeName>, fourth floor, thrity-seven males and thirtyfemales are employed. They have good light and air the only objectionable feature from a sanitary standpoint being the filthy condition of the <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">closet</supplied></unclear> for the men, which is in part but not wholly due to a scarcity of the water supply at times. Many of the young women are engaged in <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">folding</supplied></unclear> and manage to earn from $5 to $8 a week. One, who was rather pretty and even more active than good-looking was making three folds of a printed sheet about the size of a single sheet of <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name>. For this work she received 35 cents a thousand. By working incessantly for ten hours she could fold 3,000, which would beat the rate of a trifle more than 10 cents an hour. If <hi rend="double">my lady</hi> were compelled to do any kind of household or even toilet work for a single hour at a speed requiring a fourth of the energy and intensity of application these girls must bring to their task she would think herself entitled to a martyr's crown.</p>
                    <p><said ana="male" who="#reporter">Do you go out for your noon lunch?</said> this particular girl was asked.</p>
                    <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Certainly not. I bring it with me from my home. If I should eat as I work, <hi rend="single">by the piece</hi> I would swallow my whole wages.</said></p>
                    <p><orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#SheaSmith">Shea Smith &amp; Co.</orgName> run a blank-book establishment at <placeName type="address" ref="#SheaSmith">216 to 234 East Van Buren street</placeName>, occupying the second-floor. They employ forty males and twenty females, the latter making from $4.50 to $8 a week, according to the foreman, although one of the girls, when asked, said she was making but $3.83. The girls are neatly dressed, have plenty of color in their faces, and in fact look like an <hi rend="double">assorted lot</hi>. Good light and ventilation may be in part credited with their condition.</p>
                    <p><placeName type="locRef">West Taylor street, from the river to Halsted street</placeName>, is a busy hive of needlework industry, though only rarely are there any street indications of what is going on within doors. Nearly every other house is a tailor-shop, either in front or rear. Bohemians, Poles, Jews, and Platt Deusch constitute the bulk of the operatives. The bosses receive the <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> work in job lots from the wholesale dealers down-town and employ from five to twenty persons, mostly females, to make it up, paying them by the piece. With each lot is a sort of working invoice showing the exact price to be paid the boss for each piece by the firm, and of course the price paid to <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#rjp">employees</reg></choice> must be enough less to leave a reasonable margin of profit for the boss. On these starvation figures thousands of men and women work the liveling day. But it is quite common for the bosses to become owners of considerable property after a few years, despite the beggarly margin of profit they allow themselves, according to the price list. The fact is that in most instances their main profit comes directly from the house for which they are working, and in the shape of a quarterly or semi-annual bonus, which of course does not show itself on the price list. They are therefore as much responsible for the degredation of labor as are the dealers for whom they manufacture. They are in the conspiracy, or at least most of them are, and if their subordinates do not know it they ought to.</p>
                    <p>The first shop of this kind visited was at <placeName type="address" ref="#Kuppen">Canal and West Taylor streets</placeName>. Five men and seven women, all Bohemians, were engaged in making coats for <persName ref="#employer">B. Kuppenheimer</persName>. The material was what is known as <hi rend="double">corkscrew</hi>, and the nominal price received for each by the boss was from $1 to $1.50 a coat. The girls earn from $2 to $6.50 a week, and the men from $10 to $12. The retail price of the garments would not be less than $15.</p>
                    <p>At <placeName type="address" ref="#Beifeld">105 West Taylor street</placeName> seven men and five women make jackets and cloaks for <orgName ref="#Beifeld" type="exposedCompany">Joseph <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">Beifeld</supplied></unclear> &amp; Co.</orgName>, the jackets for from 30 to 65 cents, and the cloaks for from 35 cents to $1. The women make $3 to $7 a week on full time, but employment is unsteady, and does not average more than six months in the year. Last week, for instance, all hands were idle four days, and two days the week before.</p>
                    <p>In the rear of <placeName type="address" ref="#KNF">131</placeName> a good grade of Prince Albert coats is made for <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#KNF">Kuh, Nathan &amp; Fischer</orgName> for from $2.25 to $2.75 each, the latter faced with satin, and retailing at not less than $20. Chinchilla overcoats are ground out at $2.25 to $<damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">3</supplied></unclear> a week.</p>
                    <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I get more than that</said>, said one who had been <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">veting</supplied></unclear> as interpreter, though never stopping her machine. <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I am the highest priced of all</said> and she smiled with modest pride as she named $10 as her figure. Her companions looked at her in mute surprise. She had evidently been stealing a raise on them.</p>
                    <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I read <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> every morning</said>, she continued, <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">and so do all of us. That is to say, if any of the girls can't read English they have it translated for them. Every one of them loves <hi rend="single"><persName ref="#nellNelson">Nell Nelson</persName></hi></said>. At the mention of the familar name every silent stitcher stopped work long enough to look up appreciatively and pay mute tribute to one whom she regarded as her benefactress. Even the stolid countenance of the boss wore a pleasant express, as much as to say that he at least acquiesced in the general sentiment of gratitude.</p>
                    <p>In the rear of <placeName type="address" ref="#Loewenstein">144</placeName> four girls and seven men make <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#rjp">custom</supplied></unclear> coats for <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#Loewenstein">Louis Loewenstein &amp; Co.</orgName> for from %1.50 to $2.25 a piece. The women get from $2.50 to $3 each and the men $12, but they can't average that, as work is unsteady.</p>
                    <p>At <placeName ref="#Goldstein" type="address">158</placeName> two men and a young woman make Prince Albert coats for <persName ref="#employer">David Goldstein</persName> of <placeName type="address" ref="#Goldstein">484 South Halsted street</placeName>, for $5 a piece and upward. It is custom work of a fine quality. A stout woman with bare arms assumed the attitude of a Raphaelitic cherub from without, and perring into the room in a jolly and at the same time quizzical sort of way, asked if we were <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">writing up the sewing girls</said>.</p>
                    <p><said who="#reporter" ana="male">What do you know about anything of that nature?</said> she was asked.</p>
                    <p><said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Bahnisch!</said> she contemptuously answered. <said who="#foreperson" ana="female">Do you take us for greenies? We have been reading <name ref="#CT">THE TIMES</name> for the last fortnight.</said> And she engaged in a spirited argument with a sandy-haired young fellow whose prinicpal occupation seemed to be shifting his weight from one foot to the other, <damage agent="blurred" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear/> newspapers, and bringing beer from the corner grocery.</p>
                    <p>Cloaks are made for <orgName type="exposedCompany" ref="#Beifeld">Beifeld &amp; Co.</orgName> at <placeName type="address" ref="#Beifeld">163</placeName> for 35 cents to $1.25 each, and a dozen men and women, equally divided get but two or three days' work a week at those figures. The boss is a gental sort of a philosopher, taking the world easy and laughing at dull times. As he has made and saved enough in a few years to enable him to pose as the proprietor of a corner grocery he can afford to be cheerful.</p>
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    
                    <!--RJP:2016-07-11: unfinished transcription-->
                </div>
                <div type="advertisement">
                    <p></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
