<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../webDevelopment/nelsonSchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            
            <title corresp="#CT010"><date when="1888-08-08">Wednesday Morning, August 8, 1888</date></title>
            <sponsor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar: <ref target="http://newtfire.org">newtFire server</ref> at the <ref target="http://www.psc.edu">Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</ref></sponsor>
            <sponsor>David J. Birnbaum: <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref> server</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Rebecca Parker</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#nll">Nicole Lottig</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>with assistance from the Digital Humanities courses at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg from 2014-2016, from</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
               <persName>Gregory Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <!-- RJP: For each person that proofreads or edits the document we will add another <respStmt> with the <resp> containing the work of the editor and the date inside of a <date> element. For example:-->
            <!--<respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="yyyy-mm-dd">yyyy-mm-dd</date>. Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref=”#ebb”>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
            -->
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition> First digital edition in TEI P5, date: <date when="2016-07-14">yyyy-mm-dd</date>. This digital archive began as <persName ref="#rjp">Rebecca Parker</persName>'s in-depth capstone paper and presentation for completion of a History based Social Sciences Bachelor’s degree at the <placeName>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</placeName>. Work to create the digital aspects of the project begain in the Fall of <date when="2014">2014</date>.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Rebecca J. Parker</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg and Pittsburgh, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2014</date>
            <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><p>These articles were transcribed using PDF images available from New York University Digital Library Technology Services (DLTS). More source information can be found in the corresponding Site Index.</p></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Nelson's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the source text. Representation of tables, graphs, signage, and contracts may be altered so as to make a clearer depiction for this digital version of the text; however, the information portrayed in the digital version will be consistent with the original. When the source text is unreadable due to the age or handling of the document we are using the elements damage, unclear, and supplied in combination to provide our best interpretation of the text.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <div type="headlines">
               <list>
                  <item><hi rend="double">Nell Nelson</hi> Investigates the Boston Store and Is Shocked at What She Finds.</item>
                  <item>A Basement That on a Hot Day Is So Stifling It Reminds One of the <hi rend="double">Black Hole of Calcutta.</hi></item>
                  <item>Hundreds of Ill-Fed, Wan-Faced Children Working from 7:45 Until 6:30.</item>
                  <item>And Receiving in Exchange for the Terrible Drudgery and Hard Labor a Miserly $2 or $3 a Week.</item>
                  <item>The Managers Make Haste to Explain, but Their Explanation Scarcely Betters the Matter.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="articleBody">
               <p>For dismal surroundings, economy of comforts, and heartless treatment, to the <orgName ref="#BostonStore" type="exposedCompany">Boston store</orgName> belongs the palm.</p>
               <p>I did not work in that establishment although I tried very hard to do so. I was in the store at 8 o'clock on Friday morning as arranged with <persName ref="#employer"><!-- 2016-07-14: nll: I did some research and Mr. Hillman was the manager of the Boston store for a while in 1888, does this mean he's the employer? -->Mr. Hillman</persName>, who had partially promised to hire me. <said who="#employer" ana="male">One of the girls in the hosiery department</said> he had said <said who="#employer" ana="male">is sick, and if she doesn't come back Friday morning I will try you.</said></p>
               <p>I could not find the gentleman, although I hunted the main floor and the floors above and below. My plan of fluctuation was to take the elevator up one story and walk down, then ride up two and walk down the third flight, in that way I took in the entire store and a great part of the <choice><sic>employes</sic><reg resp="#nll">employees</reg></choice>. I began at the bottom and spent a full hour in the basement, where I saw so much and suffered so much that the upper floors had no surprises for me. In the first place the atmosphere was almost unendurable.</p>
               <p>Hot! It must have been 100 degrees above!</p>
               <p>Out in the open air not a breeze was stirring and the heat was sizzling. Down where I was I could not see a single opening to admit the air, fiery as it was, excepting the open door at the extreme southeast<!-- 2016-07-15: nll: The word 'southeast' is hyphenated because of the linebreak, but I'm not sure if it should still be hyphenated or not. --> corner of the floor, leading up a short flight of steps to the sidewalk. About this doorway so many goods were piled and draped and hung that the passage of air was obstructed. There must have been forty, and there may<!-- 2016-07-15: nll: I believe the word 'have' should be in between 'may' and 'been', but I don't know if I should add a choice tag here or not? --> been eighty, clerks, cash boys, and girls on this floor and five times that number of customers surged in and out under the glaring rays of gas-jets and electric burners. Babies squirmed and cried under the suffocating heat; children screamed and fretted; men and women fanned and wiped their faces, but the little cash-girls and the languid clerks endured their prison uncomplaining. Add to the heat from gas-jets, electric lights, and machinery, the exhalations from so many people, the moldy smell from the damaged goods, the dampness of the freshly mopped floor, the fumes from a stray disinfectant, and the mildew and earthy odor that lurked in dark corners, and you have some idea of the quarters in which customers are invited to look for bargains and where helpless, honest, freeborn American men and women, boys and girls are forced to work for clothes and bread.</p>
               <p>What about the soul? It's mockery to mention it to these slaves in such a dungeon.</p>
               <p>On a rude plank door painted black is the work <hi rend="double">Ladies.</hi> The irony of it! <hi rend="double">Serfs</hi> would be less impertinent and <hi rend="double">bond-women</hi> or <hi rend="double">drudges</hi> better than either.</p>
               <p>The door yields to my touch and I enter the toilet and cloak room. The atmosphere is so intense and the effluvia so offensive that I am almost stifled. A window about eighteen inches square has been cut in the side of the staircase leading from the street, and here I stand, my face turned up to the clouds of dust that float in from the feet and skirts of the passing customers. By and by I get accustomed to the foulness and turn round to explore the place. The floor is black and wet from recent mopping; the janitor has swept all the previous day's rubbish in from the basement and it forms a big pile behind the door. There is only one gas-jet in the room and I do not see the wet sweepings until I have stepped in them. On either side of the inclosure are the cloak-boxes, communication to which is afforded by a window a foot square. A young and very pretty colored woman is in one section and in the opposite window is a little boy possibly 13 years old. All the female help pass their hats, wraps, and lunches through these windows, and they are put in a cubby-hole the number of which corresponds to the number of the clerk. The smell of mold forcibly assails the senses, and mingled with the foul odor from the adjoining closets the effect on the lunches must be left to the imagination. On the east side of the partition is the toilet inclosure, built like the rest, under the pavement. But for the perforated coal-hole covers overhead the place would be pitch dark. It is damp, dirty, and smelly, the stone sidewalk forming the ceiling and gray flagstones the floor. The closets, four or five in number, have not even the luxury of doors, and in a space at one end is a dirty little iron sink into which runs a stream of water. As only two girls can approach the narrow trough for water at a time it is not hard for the reader to understand how great a luxury this single stream of clear, cool water is to the slave-girls. At one time I counted twenty-eight girls in this filthy little hole, which is unfit for cattle and in which no man would water a faithful dog.</p>
               <p>When I had accustomed myself to the deadly smell that pervaded the place it was 9:30 o'clock and the girls were beginning to come in to wash their hands and clean up after arranging their stock. About the little mirror were seven girls, some combing their hair, some dressing it, and all trying to get a peep at their wan faces. The closets were crowded, and while three young girls were washing at the sink five moved about with bits of soap in their hands, their arms and faces covered with lather. The soap may have been furnished by the house, but of the absence of towels I am positive. Most of the girls had their own comb, soap, and towel, and where do you suppose they carried them?</p>
               <p>In the bosom of their dresses.</p>
               <p>I cautioned a girl who had opened the front of her waist against putting the we towel so near her breast, but she only laughed and said <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">nothin'll hurt me.</said></p>
               <p><said who="#nellNelson" ana="female">But it is wet and may cause a lung trouble.</said></p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Indeed it won't. I used to put it here all last winter and it didn't hurt me. When it was awful cold I wore it home and I never even had a cold.</said> As she spoke she folded the little towel, and laying it against her under-waist buttoned her dress and went to the hole in the north cloak-box for a glass of lemonade. I told her I was very thirsty and asked for a drink.</p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">Oh, you have to pay. It's 3 cents a glass.</said></p>
               <p>The colored girl and her little white slave had a bucket full of the beverage&#8212;a very excellent article, by the way&#8212;which they retailed at the price stated. The ebony vender refused to sell to me till I convinced her that I expected to begin in the hosiery stock as soon as <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Hillman</persName> came down. The girl with the wet damask in her bosom drained her glass to the last drop, ate the slices of lemon rind and pulp, and with the help of her finger transferred every gram of undissolved sugar to her mouth. She lapped the mouth of the glass with her tongue and when the boy took it from the ledge it was as dry as could be. I could not get her to confide her salary, but she said: <said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">It ain't nothing like $5. For two years I only got $3, but now I have more.</said></p>
               <p>I found a girl named <persName ref="#workingGirl">Bessie</persName> in the closetroom<!-- 2016-07-19: nll: This is hyphenated in the article because of a linebreak, but it just looks wrong without the hyphen. I'll let someone else decide what it should be. --> lying against the wall, the very picture of death. Her face had no more color in it than a china cup, her lips were blue, dark lines increased the brilliancy of her big blue eyes, and her hands were cold and clammy. She told me she was <hi rend="double">aweful sick,</hi> but her mother made her come because she didn't want her to lose her place.</p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">The floor walker 'ud leave me go home if I ast him, but I haven't any car-fare and I don't want to walk. I lost my tea money and all comin down in the cars this morning. I was asleep.</said> I offered to pay her car-fare.</p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">No; if I ride in the air I'll be better before I get to the bridge.</said></p>
               <p>I bought her a glass of lemonade and gave her <hi rend="double">tea pennies</hi> for a week, after which we became quite confidential.</p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">I get $2 a week here and give it to my mother to buy meat. Sometimes I ride home, but them's the days that I don't buy tea, 'cause it costs too much for both. The tea is 3 cents a cup and the car fare, if you ride both ways, is 10 cents, and that's 13 cents.</said></p>
               <p>Seventy-eight cents subtracted from $2 would leave a precious small sum for meat.</p>
               <p><said who="#workingGirl" ana="female">The most I ever spent is 50 cents a week. That's how much mother let's me keep out. Oh, they're kind of good to us. Last night when it rained <persName ref="#employer">Mr. Hillman</persName> gave nickels to the cash-girls that didn't have car fare nor gossamers. But I guess he'll keep it out of their wages payday. Some of the clerks don't be good to us. They pull us everywhere and push us when we don't go fast, and we never dast ride in the elevator. The clerks can, but the cash-girls has to walk. They don't fine us if we come late, though, and they do the clerks, some 15 cents and some 25 cents, and if any of us is sick we lose the whole day out of our wages. The one I like most is <persName ref="#foreperson">Miss Gannon</persName>; she is awful good; she puts three lumps in the tea, and trusts the girls when they haven't any tea pennies.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="advertisement">
               <p></p>
            </div><!-- RJP: some articles concluded with an advertisement refering to later publications of the series ... I created this <div> because we want to capture those ads but have them sitting separately from the text of the article itself. If the article you are transcribing does not have an advertisement simply delete or comment out this final div-->
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
