<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT001_A1"><div type="advertisement">
    <pb n="1"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-29">Sunday Morning, July 29, 1888</date></head>
    <div><head>Let Romance Rest.</head>
    <head>The Grinding Process</head>
    <p>Women working like slaves for 16c a day.</p>
    <p>Long hours of toil with nothing but wretchedness to look forward to.</p>
    <p>Costs 10 cents to get a seat in a church; can't afford it, and stays home.</p>
    <p>Why a girl of 13 crawled among the rubbish in search of pins.</p>
    <p>Seven and a half cents for making a cotton-back Norfolk.</p>
    <p>How the Jersey jacket is made and what it costs a girl to make it.</p>
    <p>What is costs to work at crocheting and how much is made by it.</p>
    <p>Demanding deposits that are never returned to the girls.</p>
    <p>Villainous treatment of unfortunate women in a big factory.</p>
    <p>One gets $15 for the work of over six months.</p>
    <p>“A concern legally incorporated to grind the lives and souls out of women.”</p>
    <p>Walking miles to work and working eleven hours for 80 cents.</p>
    <p>One cent a gross for cutting dress steels.</p>
    <p>Four cents a gross for sewing buckles on bustles.</p>
    <p>Three cents per dozen for basting and 4c for springing bustles.</p>
    <p>Sixteen cents a day in a box factory.</p>
    <p>A little girl who made all of 11 cents in a day.</p>
    <p>Where Dr. De Wolf will find some work to do.</p>
    <p>A loud and pathetic appeal for the interference of Christian charity and Christian law.</p>
    <head><p>THE WHOLE STORY</p><p>Beginning Tomorrow in <hi rend="italics">The Times</hi> and running every day until finished.</p></head></div>
    <div><head>Life Among the Slave Girls of Chicago</head>
    <p>NO need to draw upon the imagination nor to indulge in fiction. A dreadful, damnable reality is presented to this community. European methods introduced, developing and expanding here, whereby the marrow is ground out of the bones, the virtue out of the souls, and the souls out of the bodies of the miserable, ill-fed, half-starved, underpaid, insulted, roughly-treated, and unprotected Working Girls.</p>
    <head><p>Shocking Revelations</p><p>Resulting from an investigation put on foot by The Chicago Times</p></head>
    <p>Not a batch of sensational stories in which names are fictitious and addresses are suppressed, but a series of articles which point to the men who are growing rich at the expense of human life and blood. <hi rend="italics">The Real Names and Addresses of Chicago manufacturers</hi> who have established a slave trade; who have transformed honest labor into a bondage; who are practicing the arts of the Pharaohs upon the weak and defenseless women of the city; who are running</p>
    <head>Organized Hells on Earth</head>
    <p>Places where virtue counts for nothing; where girlhood and womanhood are degraded; where moral and physical rottenness abound; where an ulcer is festering that will eat a hole through society. The entire sickening story will be told in this paper <hi rend="italics">without regard to persons or places</hi>.</p>
    <head>The First Installment Will Appear Tomorrow</head>
    <p>And the articles will be published daily until the whole truth is made known to the public.</p></div>
    <div><head>Give Truth a Hearing</head>
        <head>The Grinding Process.</head>
        <p>Five cents a yard for making Seal Ball Fringe. Nine hours work for 16 1/2 cents.</p>
        <p>Working on a cloak two and a half days fro 45 cents.</p>
        <p>The pale-faced girls cry “If I didn't live at home I'd starve.”</p>
        <p>Working from June to get enough ahead to buy a pair of shoes.</p>
        <p>How one proprietor “pulls the girls” and takes their little away.</p>
        <p>Thirty-five cents for making a $35 cloak.</p>
        <p>Paying an exorbitant price for a wrap and living three months on tea-dust and broken crackers.</p>
        <p>Twelve and a half cents a day made at a neck-tie factory.</p>
        <p>The girls furnish their own thread and needles and are subjected to fines.</p>
        <p>“The good Jew” whom the Rev. Mr. Goss mentioned.</p>
        <p>Girls use their underclothing for towels.</p>
        <p>The filthy and sickening scenes around and in the “toilet rooms.”</p>
        <p>Brutal and cowardly treatment of the overworked employes.</p>
        <p>Seventy-five cents per doz. for making overall pantaloons.</p>
        <p>Something about 2-cent coffee and 2-cent ice-water.</p>
        <p>Twelve cents per week for the use of a sewing-machine.</p>
        <p>Blinding tears, but not a sympathetic glance.</p>
        <p>Where the Woman's Protective Association might be useful.</p>
        <head><p>THE WHOLE STORY</p><p>Beginning Tomorrow in <hi rend="italics">The Times</hi> and running every day until finished.</p></head></div>
</div></div>
