<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT003_O1"><div type="otherArticle">
    <pb n="1"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-08-02">THURSDAY MORNING. August 2, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>PROTECTION AND SLAVERY.</head>
    <head>The Latter Is Caused by the Former and Labor is Degraded.</head>
    <p>“I notice that THE TIMES of this city has been sued for $50,000 because it has taken up the cause of the down-trodden slave girls of Chicago, and if by any chance a verdict should be returned against the paper I would say that it would be the duty of every laboring man to contribute even of his mite to the payment of that judgment,” said Clinton Furbish in the course of his lecture on “Ethics in Tariff Reform” last evening before the Andrew Jackson league.</p>
    <p>“The curse has laid too long over this unfortunate class, and I am glad to see that there is a newspaper which will take up the cause and endeavor to root out the evils that have been so well known and yet about which so little has ever been said. The curse that is shown up in those cases is the outgrowth of a pernicious taxation. I would rather see a life crushed out in foul murder than see newspapers creating false views in the minds of the public. I am glad to see that one newspaper has the courage to come out boldly and speak the truth. Nor do I admire a paper that preaches one doctrine three months and the opposite for three years and nine months.”</p>
    <p>The speaker opened his lecture by saying that in the coming presidential campaign enemies of tariff reform would be on the defensive, and that the democratic party would be the attacking force. He said he believed that true democracy meant the best protection to American industry. During the present century conditions here have changed. Contrast England with America in 1816, as shown by the letters of Jefferson. At that time England was the home of a large pauper population, while in America no one was rich, but all were comfortable. Today there were men in New York who so far as the expense was concerned could hire the prince of Wales for their lackey and never feel it. The times had truly changed, for contrast those letters of Jefferson with the Mulligan letters. The changes which had occurred had been largely brought about by the protective tariff. This year an onslaught was to be made on this system. Cleveland’s message would lead to that protection which does not hamper industry. High wages were a condition precedent to protection and not the result of it. The manufacturer employed foreign labor under the present tariff to enrich himself, for he cared nothing for American labor.</p>
    <p>“Monopolies were built up by protection,” said the lecturer, “and the system has made brutes of employers. The factories are filled with machinery, protected for the benefit of the owner, while the laborer slaves and pays for it all. Wherever the tariff has been removed - from quinine, from raw hides - the laborers have been benefited and manufacturers have been enabled to enlarge their plants and compete in the markets of the world. Under the protective tariff America’s shipping has become nothing. Bills are introduced to subsidize steamship lines, but as long as the tariff remains and goods can not be bought back here in exchange for good exported shipping will never pay. Now the poor are ground down by oppression far worse than among the blacks during the days before the war. It can not be worse, and in the coming campaign men should think of the causes and work for a better future.”</p>
</div>
</div>
