<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT003_E1"><div type="editorColumn">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-08-02">Thursday, August 2, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>
        <p>The Times.</p>
        <p>PUBLISHED EVERY MORNING <br/> (AT THE TIMES BUILDING) <br/> Corner of Washington Street
            and Fifth Avenue <br/> BY JAMES J. WEST.</p>
        <p>
            <date>THURSDAY, AUGUST 2, 1888</date>
        </p>
    </head>
    <p>COMPLAINTS reach us to the effect that THE TIMES could not be procured in certain parts of the city after 8 o’clock yesterday morning. It is a fact, nevertheless, that the newsboys increased their orders very materially yesterday morning, some of them taking double the number the took on Tuesday.</p>
    <p>The demand for THE TIMES is very great, and the boys sell out rapidly. When possible they return for fresh supplies. They are learning that the people who want THE TIMES will take no other paper. This is a good lesson and they will probably be prepared to meet the demand.</p>
    <p>THE TIMES expose of the rascally manner in which the working girls and women of Chicago are treated by manufacturers has met with universal commendation. The outrages upon human nature, upon honest labor, and upon decency are of a character to call forth the bitterest comment, and the slave drivers are everywhere spoken of as creature deserving of no respect or consideration.</p>
    <p>THE TIMES has only begun to show up a system that is a disgrace to Chicago and to nineteenth century civilization.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE TIMES’ “City Slave Girls” exposure are commended by a Troy manufacturer.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>WHILE some of us are talking so loudly about protecting American industries it wouldn’t be a bad idea to give a little of our attention to the protection of industrious females.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>A WOMAN can not have decently on $3 per week. If she lives honestly on those wages she is a moral heroine.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>CHINESE cheap labor could not compete with Chicago pauper labor.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>WILL Dr. DeWolf take a look at the factories?</p>
</div>
</div>
