<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT002_O1"><div type="otherArticle">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-08-01">Wednesday, August 1, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>DEGRADING FEMALE LABOR.</head>
    <p>Certainly it ought to be the earnest desire of every honest and honorable man to see that the means of making a decent and comfortable living are placed within the reach of those girls and women who are compelled to work their own way through this world. The young women who is willing to work, and there are but few after all who are not, deserves and ought to receive every encouragement from society.</p>
    <p>Instead of this, however, the system now in vogue here, if it were designed for the purpose could not do much more toward making labor utterly obnoxious and revolting to females. The factory workshops of this city, as described already in THE TIMES, are unfit places for girls who have the slightest sense of delicacy or the remotest ideas of propriety.</p>
    <p>They are not treated as honest laborers should be, but rather as serfs. Their individuality is taken away from them as from convicts in the penitentiary, and they are known by numbers. They are addressed as southern overseers in other days addressed the slaves. They are  watched by tax masters as Pharoah’s officers watched the Jews while they made bricks without straw. They are fined upon the slightest pretext. They are wantonly abused and insulted. They are made to feel that they are but the most miserable of God’s creatures - these poor girls and women - who have no recourse but to submit quietly and patiently to the cowardly treatment they have learned to expect. Above all they are made to feel that they can not expect any other compensation for their services than that which their employers may see fit to give them. For doing as much work as a man, and doing it as well as a man, they receive a fourth or a sixth or a tenth of a man’s wages.</p>
    <p>They have no unions these poor, ill-treated, half-starved, swindled girls and women. They have no votes. Glad enough are they to get the pittance which the cloak, the pantaloon, the bustle, the corset, or the jersey manufacturer allows them, if it is only sufficient to buy them 2-cent coffee and black bread for dinner, anything for breakfast and supper, if it will pay for a dirty bed in a dirty room, and if it will help them to keep the rags on their backs patched so as to cover their nakedness.</p>
    <p>This is degrading female labor. This is transforming honest toil into unbearable drudgery. This is tempting the young girl and the young woman of spirit to see herself to the devil. This is filling the bagnios with painted women and the streets with night walkers. This is polluting female chastity - damning souls.</p>
    <p>Let the miserable fellows who conduct these places, and who cowardly and brutally mistreat the friendless girls and women writhe under the accusations. THE TIMES does not hesitate to point them out as dangerous enemies of society, as curs with whom American manhood has nothing in common. The system which they have introduced here should be swept away before it can do any more mischief.</p>
    <p>There is no room for slavery of any kind in Chicago.</p>
</div>
</div>
