<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT004_O2"><div type="otherArticle">
    <pb n="1"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-08-02">Thursday, August 2, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>UNPROTECTED FEMALE LABORERS.</head>
    <p>Advocate of a high tariff for the alleged purpose of “protecting American labor” have gone over every country in Europe for the object of finding persons who work long hours for very short pay. They succeeded in finding them and described their condition for the purpose of securing votes. The persons who have done this work have in many case been members of the literary bureau supported by our wealthy manufacturers, who could well afford to pay liberally for doing fine writing.</p>
    <p>None of these searchers after human wretchedness has succeeded in finding persons who work longer, fare harder, have worse surroundings, or receive smaller remuneration than the women and girls in Chicago whose condition is now being presented in THE TIMES in a series of word-paintings taken from real life. If the hard lot of some of these suffering workers was presented in the form of a story it would awaken as much sympathy as any of the tales of Dickens or Victor Hugo in relation to the worthy poor of London and Paris. The truth should touch the heart and awaken pity and a sense of justice if it lacks some of the peculiar charms of fiction.</p>
    <p>Several protection papers have lately referred to the recent strike of the match girls of London, and remarked that the like of it has never occurred in this country, as there was no occasion for it. The truth is our women and girls employed in great factories are in no condition to engage in a strike. A Glasgow paper in referring to the late demonstration of the London female match-makers says: “They paraded the streets, very expensively and gaudily dressed, from the hat, with its three and in many cases four long ostrich feathers of a brilliant red or royal blue shade down to high-heeled boots of the latest style” It is by no means strange that they were able to dress in this manner since average pay for full work is thirteen English shillings per week. These girls are only 12 or 14 years old and can not be expected to earn large wages.</p>
    <p>The girls employed in some of our manufacturing establishments would not present a very fine appearance parading the streets. They would have no finery to display. They can not appear in public for want of decent clothing. Small as is their pay they can not afford to lose the wages of a day. They can no indulge in one of those costly luxuries known as a strike. They must suffer in silence and seclusion.</p>
</div></div>
