<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="lettersToEditor">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head>“SLAVE GIRLS OF CHICAGO”</head>
    <div id="CT002_LE1">
        <head>The Good Work Begun by “The Times” Heartily Seconded.</head>
        <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-30">CHICAGO, July 30 - TO THE EDITOR:</inLineHead> Oh, how long have I looked for a friendly hand to be extended in behalf of the poor working girls of this city. African slavery in the south never could, I think, compare with the white slavery of Chicago. What are we living for? That’s the question. Here I am, working as a type-writer for a millionaire and getting $3 a week. If such men are not to be punished in this world then I can only cherish the hope that there is another, where punishment will be meted out to them. Whoever connected with your paper too this bold stand to right the wrongs of the hard-worked, industrious, poor girls of this city may heaven bless him. Could I but declare myself and make known the indignities to which I have been subjected the earth might better for them open and swallow up the accursed. My prayer is that your valuable paper will leave no inquiry unsatisfied, but will fearlessly and to the point strike for the rights and the life of the girls; and I hope to see the business men of Chicago aroused to a proper sense of their meanness.</p>
        <p type="signed">MARY.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="CT002_LE2">
        <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-30">CHICAGO, July 30 - TO THE EDITOR:</inLineHead> Your exposure of “Life Among the Slave Girls of Chicago” ought to awaken a deep interest among our people. Who can forget that memorable utterance of Horace Greeley: “I am glad to have lived in that day and generation which gave the deathblow to American slavery and to imprisonment for debt.” But today we have another and most damnable system of slavery carried on for the greed of people at the expense of life and health, virtue, home, and, it may be, heaven. This hideous crime practiced upon defenseless woman is all to make the “rich richer and the poor poorer.” It must come to an end. The thought of this state of things must some day burn the hearts or sting the conscience of our commercial people. ’Tis a shame and disgrace, and I hope your articles will be the means of calling effectual attention to it.</p>
        <p type="signed">J.W.B.</p>
    </div>
</div>
