<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div type="lettersToEditor">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head>FACTORY SLAVES IN CHICAGO.</head>
    <div id="CT003_LE1">
        <head>The People Once Aroused Will Find a Remedy for This Evil.</head>
        <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-31">CHICAGO, July 31 - TO THE EDITOR:</inLineHead> I have been reading your articles on “The White Factory Slaves” with a great deal of interest and astonishment - astonished that its existence is a fact in this city, especially when the great republican party in its declarations are crying down the evil of the importation of pauper labor. “Ubt jus, ibt remedium,” and there is a remedy for this great evil of starving people inches by inches. It seems to me that it would be far more praiseworthy for the Christian philanthropists to spend their spare cash in assisting these poor people from an early grave than in sending missionaries to the Hottentots. There is a larger field and a more humane one right at their thresholds. We have one or two churches in nearly every block in this city, and we are building more, and some of our people are crying, not for tracts, but for work to obtain the common necessaries of life. We are building more theaters and a grand Auditorium, and our people are starving. What a spectacle! And we call this a “Christian country.” How false is the assertion can easily be answered by the simple perusal of your “white slave” articles. The owners of these factories are made up in chief of persons who are void of all sympathy for their fellow beings, and their hearts, if they have hearts, are harder than Pharaoh, king of Egypt, possessed. We have emancipated the colored slaves only to enslave white ones. Is it any wonder that we have street-walkers in our leading cities? Please don’t insert any more: give our religious citizens sufficient time to attend the noonday prayer-meeting, no matter if thousands are working for a premium on early death. Let the saloons flourish; encourage owners of tinder-boxes to fill their dens on Clark street with human beings like packed sardines, so long as they attend their churches regular. Michigan, Prairie, La Salle, and Dearborn avenues will still exist and the churches will persevere in requesting contributions for the heathen in foreign climes. Your paper has taken the position of a public benefactor. You may, perhaps, loose a few “ads” and subscribers, but you may be the means of saving many a poor girl from starvation and worse. Praise be to you.</p>
        <p type="signed">GEORGE BRAHAM</p>
    </div>
    <pb n="5"/>
    <head>“SLAVE GIRLS OF CHICAGO.”</head>
    <div id="CT003_LE2">
        <head>Readers of “The Times” in Sympathy with Nell Nelson’s Earnest Work.</head>
        <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-31">CHICAGO, July 31 - TO THE EDITOR:</inLineHead> I have read with great interest your articles on slavery in Chicago. That such things exist right around us must be a surprise to the Christian charity associations conducted by the noble women here. I have lived all my life in the south and have seen the much-talked of horrors of African slavery, but the old time master and mistress never expected a negro child to live on the wages Nell Nelson says she was paid, nor were they expected to work continuously throughout the day as the slaves of these rich manufactories.</p>
        <p>Where are the women of the Christian Temperance union? Here is a field for them that would show better returns than trying to reform drunken loafers.</p>
        <p>Your paper is certainly attracting great attention from the bravery displayed in giving names and numbers as well as the ingenuity by which the knowledge was obtained. The woman who undertook the mission must possess wonderful courage. Is there any way by which another woman interested in the welfare of her sex can make her acquaintance. She deserves the admiration of all other women. We have the wrongs of all classes ventilated through the newspapers, from the Chinese who don’t want to be converted to the fashionably-dressed woman who does not want dress-reform. Labor unions, babies, newsboys, waifs, “Q.” strikers, Sunday closing, social purity, and servant girlism have in turn had the consideration due their wrongs, and it is quite time attention was called to the white slaves. The prominence given it in your valuable paper can not fail to bear fruit.</p>
        <p type="signed">VIRGINIA.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="CT003_LE3">
        <p><inLineHead place="Chicago" when="1888-07-31">CHICAGO, July 31 - TO THE EDITOR:</inLineHead> Blessings of the working-girls on Nell Nelson’s head for her good work. Send her to the dry goods stores to see the clerks and keep up the exposures till the people are roused to do something.</p>
        <p type="signed">EMMA.</p>
    </div>
</div>
