<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT002_O1"><div type="otherArticle">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday, July 31, 1888</date></head>
    <head>PAUPER LABOR OF CHICAGO.</head>
    <p>Last fall a poor young girl employed in a heel factory on State street was murdered by a lustful wretch, a porter at the same place. The event afforded momentary insight of the poverty, wretchedness, and degradation of the underpaid, undersized, stinted, and stunted operatives of this factory. The porter has hanged and the incident was well nigh forgotten.</p>
    <p>But Green’s heel factory is not the only place in Chicago where poverty is employed at starvation wages to make profit for greedy manufacturers. We lay high tariffs  for the purpose, we are told, of enriching, ennobling, and dignifying American labor. We protect it from the pauper labor of Europe. The policy helps the manufacturer, but labor is neither enriched nor dignified nor ennobled. Labor pauperized, sullen, suffering, gaunt, and hopeless, is the victim partly of its own necessities, partly of the avarice and the inhumanity of men who know how to use it to their own great advantage.</p>
    <p>Breakfasting with the wife of a rich Virginia planter, John Randolph was importuned by his hostess for a contribution in aid of the benighted souls of Africa. He refused. Riding from the house his horse picked its way among a lot of naked pickaninnies rolling in dirt and using their tongues vilely. He returned to the mansion and grimly confronted his hostess with the remark: “Madame, the heathen are at your door.”</p>
    <p>Pauper labor is at our own doorway. It is here in miserable abundance right in this great and wealthy city of Chicago. In the hard struggle for existence it gets more cuffs than half-pence, but its moan is seldom heard above the city’s din and in the hard struggle for existence it finds relief only in the death that it instinctively fights against. Women and girls are the greatest sufferers in an industrials condition where advantage is taken of their poverty and their helplessness. Deft with the needle they turn naturally to employments where that implement is a factor, and their reward is generally the reward of the woman who sang Hood’s song, and who</p>
    <p>“Sewed at once with a double thread</p>
    <p>A shroud as well as a shirt.”</p>
    <p>THE TIMES has patiently gathered and will continue to present a mass of trustworthy information relating to the compensation paid women and girls in various employments in Chicago. The first installment is indicative of the perils, the sufferings, and the slender wage earnings of such women. In all the contracts, in all the regulations of the factories where they labor</p>
    <p>“On seam and gusset and band,</p>
    <p>On band and gusset and seam.”</p>
    <p>the tarred end of the stick goes to them. At one place they may sew upon overalls, finding their own thread, making the fly extra strong, pressing out the bottoms, and they may have 75 cents a dozen. Or they may engage with a hundred other women and girls in the great industry of completing the never-rip jersey, whose dye is no stronger fixed than its wool, pays 12 cents a week for the use of a machine, 2 cents a week for ice-water, and 2 cents for tea at the slender lunch which must be provided by the operative herself, and realize as the fruit of their labor barely enough to keep body and soul together.</p>
    <p>One might well wish to be a “slave among the barbarous Turk, where woman has never a soul to save,” if Christianity and the protective tariff can do no more for wage-earners than is done for the poor creatures of Chicago who wear themselves out in an effort to gain by a week of labor what an employer would spend on a single lunch for himself and a friend.</p>
</div></div>
