<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT002_E1"><div type="editorColumn">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-07-31">Tuesday, July 31, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>
        <p>The Times.</p>
        <p>PUBLISHED EVERY MORNING <br/> (AT THE TIMES BUILDING) <br/> Corner of Washington Street
            and Fifth Avenue <br/> BY JAMES J. WEST.</p>
        <p>
            <date>TUESDAY, JULY 31,1888</date>
        </p>
    </head>
        <p>THE great demand for THE TIMES of yesterday morning proves that the public is deeply interested in the exposures of factory life in Chicago, which this newspaper is now engaged in making. A sufficient number of copies of yesterday’s edition to meet all reasonable demands have been run off, so that those who have not yet seen the first chapter and who would like to have the story entire can be supplied at the business office.</p>
        <p>The second installment of hard facts is presented this morning. People engaged in reformatory work will find plenty of food for reflection in the recital.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE TIMES’ lady reporter, investigating further among Chicago factories, reveals some startling facts relative to brutal treatment of working girls and low wages paid.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE sewing girl must furnish her own needle and thread, must pay rent for her machine and keep it in order, must sweep up around it, must pay for her ice water, must pay fines if she is late or if she talks and all out of about 45 cents a day. She ought not to complain. Her employers might insist upon her furnishing the materials she works on. Poor girl.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>Our country, ’tis of thee,</p>
    <p>Sweet land of pov-liberty,</p>
    <p>Of the we si-hum;</p>
    <p>Land where our pants are made,</p>
    <p>Land where our shirts are stayed,</p>
    <p>Where girls can learn a trade,</p>
    <p>And live on - gum.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>CHEVIOT shirts, with gusseted tails and sleeves, the bosoms and arm-holes stayed, and the collars and wrist-bands made extra strong, pay the unfortunate girl or woman who makes them 75 cents per dozen. How is that for protection?</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>If a suit of clothes can be bought as cheaply in this country as in England it is because some poor, miserable, half-starved girl has made them. The protectionist will please read THE TIMES’ exposure of slavery in Chicago.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE girl who works in one of those cloak or corset or jersey factories is like unto the man who furnished his own boat, picked up cordwood, and was given half of what he got as compensation for his services.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>WE protect everything except human flesh and blood in this country. Let us see if the girls and women who are willing to work hard for an honest living can not be protected.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE next time you buy a pair of $6 pantaloons try and remember the girl who received 35 cents for making them and pray for her.</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>WHAT has protection done for the working girl? What protection has she got?</p>
</div>
<div type="editorial">
    <p>THE TIMES is in favor of protecting the working girl.</p>
</div>
</div>