<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT004_O2"><div type="otherArticle">
    <pb n="2"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times: <date when="1888-08-02">Thursday, August 2, 1888.</date></head>
    <head>WILL FREE THE WHITE SLAVES.</head>
    <head>A Troy Manufacturer Agrees to Employ Factory Girls at Good Wages.</head>
    <p>“I do not know where I read an article that has interested me more than the one this morning in THE TIMES regarding the deplorable condition of the working girls in Chicago,” said F.B. Ide last evening.</p>
    <p>Mr. Ide is a manufacturer of collars and cuffs at Troy, N.Y., which city enjoys almost a monopoly of the manufacture of that line of goods in this country. He is stopping in Chicago for a day or two and ran across THE TIMES article accidentally.</p>
    <p>“There are no two chapters in the bible,” he said, “which are doing more good than these TIMES articles will do. I hope the paper will keep right in and let the public know the real state of things. I am a manufacturer and employ a large number of girls and my sympathies are with them. I am glad to say that the working girls in Troy are in far better circumstances than they are here. The public may be interested in knowing by way of contrast with the situation here how the girls in Troy are treated.”</p>
    <p>“In the first place, we employ no girls under 16. That has been regulated by law. In the manufacture of collars, cuffs, and shirts, and boxes in which they are put up, there are in Troy eighty or eighty-one establishments which employ girls. There are no other manufactories in Troy to speak of. Within a radius of twelve miles of the city hall there are 30,000 girls who are furnished work by these establishments. Fully 75 per cent of the money paid for labor in Troy is paid to women, and the women’s pay averages 24 per cent higher than that of men. A girl has a better chance more than a boy has. If a man has a daughter 18 or 20 years old and a son 20 or 22 who start out to earn their living there the girl will earn on an average $2 or $2.50 a week more than the boy will. A girl who works steadily must be a poor hand if she does not earn $14 a week. There is a division of labor in manufacturing collars and cuffs. The collars are cut out by men and then pass successively through the hands of girls who we call “runners,” “turners,” “top-stitchers,” “banders,” “band-turners,” “button-holers,” “starchers,” etc. The “runners” make from $12 to $14 a week and the other classes all the way from $10 to $25. It is not unusual for a skilled button-holer to make $25, and I have paid as high as $32 to a girl for a week’s work. That is a rare exception however. Of course this is skilled labor but the girls become skilled in a very short time. We have girls 16 years old who can run errands or stamp the trade mark or brand on the goods who get only from $4 to $8, but there are not many of them compared with the mass of workers.”</p>
    <p>“You will see no cash girls in the store in Troy. That work is done by boys. The girls can do better in the factories. Saleswomen in the stores get about $10 a week. One of the finest saleswomen in the city came to me a few weeks ago and applied for work, believing that she could do better in the factory. I set her at work, and she made $8.05 the first week, being, of course, an unskilled hand. In a few weeks she will make, perhaps, twice as much as she could in a store. And then our manufactories are palaces compared with most of the places in which girls have to work in Chicago. I have been into some of these and they are simply awful. We would not allow the male and female help to work in the same room or to intermingle at all. The ceilings are high, the ventilation excellent, and the accommodations in the way of dressing rooms, closets, etc., as good and neat as one will find in a private house. The girls dress as well and as stylist as do the wives of the manufacturers. Many of them come to the factory in silk dresses and other wearing apparel to match. They go into the dressing-rooms and put on their working clothes and work until noon. They they put on their nice clothes again and go home to their dinner. It is the same in the afternoon. Milliners and shoe dealers say they sell as fine goods to the girls who work in the shirt and collar factories as they do to the wives of the richest men in town. Of course among such a large numbers of girls there will be some black sheep, but there are very few. The girls as a rule are refined and ladylike. The work is not considered degrading, and the girls not only have self-respect but are respected. Some of the daughters of quite well-to-do parents take work home or have it brought to them, and by putting in spare time at it make their $5, $6, or $7 a week for pin-money.”</p>
    <p>“Now this state of things which we have in Troy is exceptional of course, but I believe THE TIMES, if it keeps up the agitation of this subject which it has so very ably begun, can do a great deal toward bringing about a similar condition of affairs in Chicago. The influence of a great newspaper is tremendous. I admit that I can’t see a very encouraging prospect for securing an immediate increase of the girls’ pay, but a very great improvement can be effected in the way of having comfortable, well-lighted, and well-ventilated quarters to work in, and in having them work separately from the men and treated generally as human beings. Factory inspectors can be made to enforce regulations and the enactment of new regulations as needed can be enforced. If a girl has nice and neat quarter to work in she will want her home to be nice and neat and will be more circumspect and ladylike herself. There was a time, not many years ago, either, when the girls in Troy were not so well off as they are now, and the newspapers had a very great deal to do in bringing about their improved condition. THE TIMES can do the same work here. It can shame the manufacturers into doing something. If it becomes widely known that this or that manufacturer pays his girls only 60 cents a day his trade is bound to be injured. All buyers are not heartless. The manufacturers will be forced, for their own protection and for the good name of their goods in the market, to treat their help better.”</p>
    <p>“The working-girls in each line of manufacturing can do a great deal toward increasing their wages if they organize. They should organize for themselves and run their own organization. They should not let any walking delegates or anyone in any other line of business control or interfere in the lest. The girls in Troy have their protective association and so have the manufacturers. When any differences arise the committees of the two associations meet and settle it, usually without any difficulty. This is one of the results which is quite likely to follow agitation of the subject. I think THE TIMES is engages in a great work, and I predict that if it persists good results will follow and that in a year from now there will be a very marked improvement in the condition of working-girls in Chicago. It is a shame that in the most enterprising city in the west girls should be forced to work for 60 cents a day. Anyone who has a spark of humanity in his soul must pity them. I will agree to take to Troy half a car-load of girls who earn only 60 cents a day and give them a much better show than that.”</p>
</div></div>