<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="CT001_A2"><div type="advertisement">
    <pb n="4"/>
    <head type="main">The Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-29">Sunday Morning, July 29, 1888</date></head>
    <head><p>The Times.</p>
    <p>PUBLISHED EVERY MORNING <br/> (AT THE TIMES BUILDING) <br/> Corner of Washington Street and Fifth Avenue <br/> BY JAMES J. WEST.</p>
    <p><date>SUNDAY, JULY 29,1888</date></p>
    <p>TWENTY-PAGE SHEET</p></head>
    <p>COMMENCING tomorrow morning THE CHICAGO TIMES will give from day to day the results of an inquiry which it has had under way for some time past into the condition of certain classes of the working girls and working women of Chicago.</p>
    <p>The fact will be revealed that there are thousands of females in the city, young, middle-aged, and old, who are compelled to lead lives which are more miserable in many respects than were ever endured by the black race in the south, because even the plantation negroes in their days of slavery were at least well fed, decently clad, and comfortably housed.</p>
    <p>When our readers shall have read the articles, which are not founded upon fiction, but are written from the experience of a young lady reporter who has worked for a day or more among the women she describes, and when they observe that names and places are given openly and fearlessly, the wonder will be that vice in all its hideous forms does not confront us more openly on the streets, that degradation, shame, and wretchedness do not haunt us at every step, that the prostitution of female virtue in not greater than it is.</p>
    <p>The mills that are grinding the health, the spirits, and even the lives out of young women in Chicago do not stop there. They grind the souls of these unfortunates as well - grind them until every tender, womanly feeling, every holy and noble instinct, every chaste and honest purpose that God in his benevolence has planted in the female heart is stunted in its growth or withered in its stem.</p>
    <p>When honest labor is transformed in to humiliating servitude; when the reward of faithful service is an insult or a sneer; when girls who try to lead decent lives are ridiculed; when virtue is looked upon as one of the last things a working-girl should claim possession of; when grasping, brutal, miserly, and bestial slave-drivers take the place of considerate and friendly employers, it is time to pause and consider what had better be done.</p>
    <p>The readers of THE TIMES during the coming week will have ample opportunity of judging for themselves as to which lot is the more enviable - that of the beast of burden or the working-girl of Chicago.</p>
</div></div>
