<div type="section" n="10">
CHILDREN THIRTEEN YEARS OLD WORKING FROM NOON TILL NIGHT ON HEAVY COATS AND TROUSERS.
PAYING $3.50 FOR HEAVY TOIL THAT GRINDS THE MARROW FROM THE BONES AND KILLS MORALITY.
Never so long as reason reigns shall I forget the day I
worked in H. G.'s tailor-shop, and never when I pray shall I
forget to add "God help the shop girls."
<pb n="56"/>
Thursday morning I stepped from an Ogden avenue car and
walked down Market street in search of work. It was broiling
hot and I carried my brown veil on the breeze, and a small
pasteboard box containing a cracker and a lemon, a paper of
needles, a thimble, and a pair of scissors. On the way I met
two unhappy looking girls of whom I made labor inquiry.
One had sewed carpet at five dollars a week for the C. C. Co.
but was out of employment. The other said she earned six
dollars a week in Wilson Brothers' cravat department. Her
cousin was sick and the forewoman had "let her off for the
day."
The first clew I got to a place was a wooden sign with
"Sewing Girls Wanted" that hung below the north window
of 155 Market street, where Messrs. H---, A---; &amp; M---
manufacture clothing. I read the sign and entered the main
store - a nice, big, clean, cool place. A little girl sat at the
big typewriter making such a clatter with her letters that it
was useless to try to call her. In the office were two gentlemen. One was the very prototype of Munkacsy's Jesus Christ
and he I addressed for work.
"The gentleman that attends to the work is not here just
at present. Take a seat a moment." I thanked him and
looked at the vacant chair. It wouldn't do. It was too conspicuous. I knew the credit man in the building opposite and
didn't care to be seen in my factory togs, so I went in a dark
corner, where I stood, first on one foot and then on 'tother, for
exactly forty minutes. Nobody came. Finally he with the
Nazarene face appeared and said : "Ill go up and see if we
want any more help." Again I said "Thank you," and
watched him as he walked to the back of the store.
No, he didn't have a halo, but a monstrous pair of pedal
extremities that curled up like an old-fashioned skate.
When he got to the back of the store he simply retraced
his steps and told me "We have all the girls we need."
<pb n="57"/>
"Why don't you take your sign in then? I have lost an
hour."
A sneer made his face so hideous that I apologized to the
Hungarian painter.
"Supposing you take it in," he said following me to the
doorstep.
"Why should I?"
"And for what purpose, please, should I take that sign in?"
"For Christain charity, but Christain charity is not in your
line."
I then went over to Messrs. S. L. and Co. There I encountered the manager of the work-room and the most contemptuous treatment it was possible for a man to show a hapless
woman. Suffice it to say H. A. &amp; M. were avenged.
At A. L. S. &amp; Co.'s, 178 Market street, I received the
most courteous consideration. The manager took my name,
or rather a name and address, and said he would give it to any
of his patrons who needed help. Then he wrote me a letter
of which the following is a copy:
H. G---- Rumsey street - Sir: This girl wants work. I don't know
what she can do, but I think you can use her. Respectfully,
A. L. S.---- per S---.
Rumsey street is two blocks west of Ashland avenue. It
begins at Division street and runs south a quarter of a mile or
so over heaps of yellow clay, rubbish and holes. The road is
almost impassable for teams, and only the residents of the
locality can take the upheavals and depressions of the sidewalk for a block without getting sea-sick. Filth of every
description litters the ground, and following the line where a
curbstone should be, are garbage-boxes where the children
mold mud pies during the day where the men sit and smoke
their pipes after the day's work is done, and where now and
then old termagants back-bite their neigbors and tear each
other's hair. Some of the cottages are so low that the chim-
<pb n="58"/>
neys barely reach above grade, and all swarm with children,
pale, eager, dirty little creatures that root about in the yellow
clay and fresh dumpngs<!-- RJP:10/21/15: retained spelling --> like the dogs they play with. Poor
children, it is not their mothers' fault that they are wild and
unkept, for the languid parents give all their strength to the
shop-work in order to half feed and partly clothe them. I had
only walked a few blocks in this deep-rutted street in search of
H. G---- before being convinced that I was not in the district
of protuberant optimists.
The first woman I made inquiry of was carrying a bucket of
sawdust from a neighboring ale-house. She didn't know the
name, but when I mentioned coats she grew loquacious.
"Oh, yes, the 'slave hole' it's called; that's the sheeny
tailor's! Don't go to him, my dear; he'll grind the marrow
from your bones. Go to service, girl, go to service. You can
have a cot in my room till you find a place. I was with him
one fortnight and worked my eyes most blind and he paid me
$1.75. No, I m from England, but I never had harder times in
the old country than now. There I paid five shillings for
lodgings and here they cost me four dollars." She told me she
got the sawdust for sweeping out a corner dram-shop and used
it to boil her tea-kettle with.
The grandeur of 258 quite over-powered me. Instead of a
"hole" I found myself entering a large two-story red brick
house still in process of construction. I ascended the front
steps, and after the maneuver of the celebrated king of France
marched down again to the basement - to the shop - into the
presence of Mr. H. G---. I handed him my letter and while
he read it I took him in - optically. He was an unctious
little fellow with kinky hair, cunning brown eyes, hatchet
features, and a small mustache the color of roasted coffee. He
was attired in two shirts - a nether one of chocolate flannel
and a linen one a few shades lighter - a pair of check pantaloons, carpet slippers, and a huge gold ring of masonic design.
<pb n="59"/>
He read the letter with the cigar in his mouth, the smell of
which combined with the flavor of his feet and the exhalations
of his toilel was something preponderant.
He asked me what I had worked at, and after a few gasps I
gave him some of my history slightly distorted.
I was told to take off my hat and while doing so he stepped
back out in the entry and vacated a hook among the factory
girl's wraps, but as I did not care to take the chances of tempting the gutter snipes and going home bare-headed I declined his
attention and hung them in a corner on the floor. All ready,
sewing box in hand, I faced the gaping, silent throng, and was
pointed to a chair at a long table, about which ten girls were
sewing with a speed and a silence that was terrible to contemplate. They wore cotton dresses of the poorest quality, some
of them open at the neck and nearly all rolled to the elbow.
The youngest were four little girls of it, one of whom was
operating, two basting, and the fourth finishing a blue cloth
cloak. One large Irish hand, possibly 25, sat at the upper end
of the table. Of the rest, 15 years would be a fair average
age. One poor girl who was very lame had a machine, and it
made my heart ache fo watch her pale face and follow her thin
little hands guide coat after coat under the needle. All the
girls were thin and haggered, some were very pretty, some few
had color in their cheeks, but it was the hectic flush, not the
healthy glow of youth and physical strength.
In all we were twenty girls, eight men and two boys - poor
young fellows in their teens, with mealy complexions, wild
eyes, hollow cheeks and sunken chests. Neither weighed a
hundred pounds, but both pressed goods with heavy irons and
were cuffed and pushed about by the boss and his assistant.
The men worked in slippers and undershirt without straps or
suspenders to keep their trousers in place, and the girls wore
heavy peg shoes. I noticed some of the machine hands worked
the foot-plate in their Stocking feet.
<pb n="60"/>
I had taken all this in when the boss came near my chair
and threw a plaid sack coat in my lap and without a word
walked away. Here was a nice predicament I thought, as I
looked the galley over. I asked the little yellow-haired Swede
girl at my right where to begin, but she looked at me and resumed her "feeling" without a word of reply. Then I asked
a big, yellow-haired, dough-faced German girl on my left and
received the same kind of response. Instantly I realized their
position. Compulsory silence.
I put twist in my needle, squeezed on my thimble and
selected a side-seam in the farmer satin lining, for if there is
any one kind of needle work that I pride myself on it is "felling." Well, I felled an hour, up one seem and down another,
around the collar and along the bottom of the coat. Then I
stitched and tacked the tail pockets, took a deep breath and
settled back in my chair to take a rest. I didn't take it long,
though. Before I could reel off two lines of Hood's "Song of
the Shirt" the boss was at my elbow looking over my work
with his nasty smelly cigar so near my face that I was obliged
to pull back to escape being burned.
" Take smaller stitches," he said. " Don't ' fell ' through.
You havn't though. Now put in the sleeve-lining," and he
left me muttering inwardly, "put in the sleeve-lining." I did.
In a great deal less time I was told to rip it out. I put it in
a second time and a second time did Penelope's work. The
third time was not a charm, and when his unctions honor, who
had been watching me all the time, neared my chair I politely
asked him to show me how to arrange the fullness. He
grabbed the coat, shook the "muffy" thing in my face,
dropped the ashes from his two-for-a-nickel in my hair and ob-
served: " I don't think you'll do. I want experienced hands,"
and though mute I thought: "You monster, to talk about ex-
perienced hands and pay $3.50 a week?"
Well, he showed me how tailors put in sleeve linings, and I
The White Slave Girls of Chicago.	61
showed the merits of his teaching. In future I shall never let
a coat-sleeve go about my waist without wanting its owner to
unbutton and let me see where the lining is fulled and how the
top seam is felled.
At noon we had forty minutes for—I will not say dinner, be-
cause no one had anything that could be so designated, unless
it were "Boss" G. and he went home. Most of the men had
nothing to eat. I only saw two with a lunch. The girls had
black bread and a can of cold coffee, which they consumed
with evident relish. Not more than five minutes were spent
over the repast. I devoured my crackers and gnawed at my
lemon by way of dessert. In a hurry to get at my work as
soon as possible to make up for lost time I threw the sucked
Messina under the table and in a few moments saw a little
stitcher pick it up and hide it in her pocket.
By a series of questions I got the following information from
a pretty Jewess who had been in the shop for three years and
was getting $3.50 a week. She said regarding the salary: " Oh,
I don't care. G. won't pay any more. My mother has money
and doesn't mind so long as I learn to sew. I am 15 in Octo-
ber. I came here at 12, and don't know how much longer I
will have to stay. G. thinks women are cows, that they must
be driven. So he drives us. We have to be at work at 7 in
the morning and stay till 6 in the evening."
"Half holiday Saturday?"
"Nix."
"What if you are sick ? "
" If you're sick he 'pulls' you. He 'pulled' me for twenty
cents for being late last week. He ' pulls ' all the hands when
they come late, and he 'pulls ' if we talk."
That's why I could not get my neighbors to tell me how to
start my work.
Rosy told me that she was thirteen, that her father peddled
fish, and that she was the eldest of five sisters and two broth-
</div>